Officials of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Pittsburgh</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">H.H. Robertson</ENAMEX>, which makes steel roofs, store fronts and building parts, declined comment. As reported last month, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kass</ENAMEX> said he was interested in making an offer to buy <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">H.H. Robertson</ENAMEX> for $13 a share.
In the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">SEC</ENAMEX> filing, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Kass-Pedone group</ENAMEX> said it intends to acquire additional H.H. <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Robertson</ENAMEX> shares ``with a view towards a possible change in control of the company.'' It has not, however, made a formal proposal.
The group also is engaged in talks with third parties regarding obtaining financing to buy more shares, but no agreements have yet been reached, the filing said.
In <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> composite trading yesterday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">H.H. Robertson</ENAMEX> closed at $11.625, up 62.5 cents.
