<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">International Business Machines Corp.</ENAMEX> said its board approved the purchase of $1 billion of its common shares, a move that should help support its battered stock.
The announcement came after the market's close.
The move by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IBM</ENAMEX> wasn't exactly a surprise. The company has spent some $5 billion over the past 3 1/2 years to buy back 42 million common shares, or roughly 7% of those outstanding.
In addition, despite <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IBM</ENAMEX>'s well-publicized recent problems, the computer giant still generates enormous amounts of cash. As of the end of the second quarter, it had $4.47 billion of cash and marketable securities on hand.
As a result, some securities analysts had predicted in recent days that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IBM</ENAMEX> would authorize additional purchases.
In <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Armonk</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.Y.</ENAMEX>, a spokesman said that although <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IBM</ENAMEX> didn't view its spending as necessarily a way to support the stock, it thought the purchases were a good way to improve such financial measurements as per-share earnings and return on equity.
``We view it as a good long-term investment,'' the spokesman said.
Over the long term, however, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IBM</ENAMEX>'s stock repurchases -- along with its hefty, $4.84-a-share annual dividend and generally loyal following among large institutional investors -- are providing a floor for the stock price.
Although <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IBM</ENAMEX> last year produced its first strong results in four years and was expected to continue to roll this year, it began faltering as early as January. First, it had trouble manufacturing a chip for its mainframes, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IBM</ENAMEX>'s bread-and-butter business. Then it had a series of smaller glitches, including problems manufacturing certain personal computers and the delay in the announcement of some important workstations. Finally, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IBM</ENAMEX> had to delay the introduction of some high-end disk drives, which account for 10% of its $60 billion of annual revenue.
Still, investors will take some convincing before they get back into <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IBM</ENAMEX>'s stock in a big way. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steve Milunovich</ENAMEX>, a securities analyst at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Boston</ENAMEX>, said that while investors were looking for an excuse to buy <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IBM</ENAMEX> shares a year ago, even the big institutional investors are looking for a reason to avoid the stock these days.
