A # 320 million ($508 million) <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Airways PLC</ENAMEX> rights issue flopped badly -- the victim of recent market turbulence and the collapse of the buy-out bid for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Airlines</ENAMEX>' parent, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL Corp.</ENAMEX>
The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">United Kingdom</ENAMEX> carrier had planned the issue to help finance its $750 million purchase of a 15% stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX>. But <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Airways</ENAMEX> withdrew from the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> labor-management buy-out plan last Friday, after the group failed to get bank financing for its $6.79 billion buy-out.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Airways</ENAMEX> said its shareholders accepted only 6.3% of the convertible capital bonds, but that the rest of the issue will be taken up by underwriters. Analysts said that 6.3% level marked the poorest showing for any major British rights issue since the 1987 global stock market crash.
``It is close to being a record undersubscription,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bob Bucknell</ENAMEX>, an analyst with <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX> broker <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Smith New Court Securities.</ENAMEX> ``Fund managers don't like to have rights issues that don't have an obvious reason. The obvious reason was (for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Air</ENAMEX>) to buy a stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Airlines</ENAMEX>.''
In a statement, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Air</ENAMEX> Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lord King</ENAMEX> said the company was ``obviously disappointed that the issue was not taken up, but it would have been unreasonable to expect a better result given the volatility of the stock market since the launch of the issue.''
But except for the embarrassment, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Air</ENAMEX> will emerge relatively unscathed from the flopped issue. Underwriters led by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lazard Brothers & Co.</ENAMEX> will pick up the rest of the airline's offer of four convertible capital bonds for every nine common shares. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lazard</ENAMEX> and other primary underwriters have reduced or eliminated their exposure by sub-underwriting the issue among U.K. institutional investors. ``The (paper) loss here is very small'' for these sub-underwriters, observed <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John Nelson</ENAMEX>, a Lazard managing director. In any case, he added, ``most institutions probably won't sell'' the bonds. And instead of buying the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> stake, the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.K.</ENAMEX> carrier will be able to reduce its high debt level and build an acquisition war chest. ``From a cash flow point of view, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Airways</ENAMEX> is better off not being in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Airlines</ENAMEX> in the short term,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Andy Chambers</ENAMEX>, an analyst at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nomura Research Institute</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX>. Added another U.K. analyst: ``It gives them some cash in the back pocket for when they want to do something.''
For instance, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Air</ENAMEX> is continuing to negotiate with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">KLM Royal Dutch Airlines</ENAMEX> about each acquiring a 20% stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sabena World Airlines</ENAMEX>, the air transport subsidiary of the Belgian national airline. A definitive agreement had been expected by the end of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">July</ENAMEX>.
The failed rights issue also should have a modest impact on <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Air</ENAMEX> shares. The airline's share price already is far below the 210 pence ($3.33) level seen after the company announced the rights issue in late September. In late trading on <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> yesterday, the shares were off three pence at 194 pence. And because <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Air</ENAMEX> is issuing convertible bonds rather than ordinary shares, the share price won't be directly hurt by any surplus left with underwriters after they try to sell the issue in the open market.
But <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Air</ENAMEX>'s withdrawal from the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> buy-out could have further repercussions. Some analysts speculated yesterday that the move has set off a board room split, which may lead to the resignation of Sir <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Colin Marshall</ENAMEX>, the carrier's chief executive officer. ``The stories are rubbish,'' a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Air</ENAMEX> spokesman said. ``There is no difference of opinion between (<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chairman</ENAMEX>) Lord King and Sir <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Colin</ENAMEX> on any aspect of company policy.
