<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pitney Bowes Inc.</ENAMEX> directors authorized the company to seek buyers for its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Wheeler Group Inc.</ENAMEX> subsidiary, a direct mail marketer of office supplies.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pitney Bowes</ENAMEX> said the decision was based on a long-term analysis of the compatibility of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Wheeler Group</ENAMEX>'s marketing business with other <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pitney Bowes</ENAMEX> operations. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pitney Bowes</ENAMEX> acquired the core of what evolved into <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Wheeler Group</ENAMEX> in 1979 by buying <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dictaphone Corp.</ENAMEX>
A spokeswoman wouldn't comment on whether the company had talked with any potential buyers for the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New Hartford</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Conn.</ENAMEX>, unit, which had 1988 sales of about $75 million. She said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Wheeler Group</ENAMEX> was profitable but wouldn't give figures.
The spokeswoman said the company doesn't have a timetable for the sale, adding that the board's decision just starts the search for a buyer.
The company said the growth was led by its major operations, particularly mailing, shipping, dictating and facsimile businesses.
