After more than a year of losing accounts and watching its reputation slide, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ogilvy & Mather</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> office hired away a top creative executive from flashy <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chiat</ENAMEX>\ as its creative head.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ogilvy</ENAMEX>, a unit of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">WPP Group</ENAMEX>, named <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bill Hamilton</ENAMEX>, 47, to the top creative post in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hamilton</ENAMEX> had been an executive vice president and creative head of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chiat\</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> office, known for its funky work for Arrow shirts, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nynex</ENAMEX> yellow pages and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Anne Klein II</ENAMEX>. At <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ogilvy</ENAMEX>, he succeeds <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Norman Berry</ENAMEX>, who left the agency in June but now plans to return to the parent company, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">WPP</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chiat/Day</ENAMEX> said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lee Clow</ENAMEX>, the agency's president and chief creative director, will fill in as acting <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> creative director until the naming of Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hamilton</ENAMEX>'s successor -- or possibly successors -- within the next few weeks.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hamilton</ENAMEX> faces a daunting task in reviving <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ogilvy's</ENAMEX> stagnant <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> office. Just a few months ago, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Maxwell House</ENAMEX> yanked its $50 million account from the office, following the loss last year of the $40 million Hallmark account. The office has won just a single piece of new business -- and a tiny one, at that -- this year, and new business wins weren't substantial last year, either.
The office is suffering from ``a dead battery,'' as <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Alan Gottesman</ENAMEX>, an analyst with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Painewebber</ENAMEX>, puts it. And while it can be turned around, he says, ``It ain't easy, and it's been parked underneath a snowdrift for a very long time.''
The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> office is just one of many <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ogilvy outposts</ENAMEX>, plenty of which are performing well. But it is the largest and most visible. With about $800 million in billings, it's bigger than most entire agencies. And while it has won praise for some of its creative work, especially for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Express</ENAMEX>, it hasn't been able to attract substantial new business. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ogilvy</ENAMEX> last spring hired <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Michael Lesser</ENAMEX>, 47, from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Lowe Marschalk</ENAMEX> to head up the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> operations, but Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lesser</ENAMEX> hasn't had a strong creative leader to work with him.
Industry executives generally lauded the move to bring in Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hamilton</ENAMEX>, saying the office needs a kick from the outside. But they questioned whether there might be a culture clash between buttoned-up <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ogilvy</ENAMEX> and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hamilton</ENAMEX>, an 11-year veteran of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chiat/Day</ENAMEX>'s freewheeling, no-walls-no-doors culture. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hamilton</ENAMEX>, after all, presided over -- among other things -- the weird U.B.U. Reebok campaign while at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chiat/Day.</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ogilvy</ENAMEX> creates more-mainstream ads for clients including <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Express</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Seagram</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mattel</ENAMEX>.
But in an interview, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hamilton</ENAMEX> said a culture clash ``is part of the agenda. I think they want some infusion of a different attitude about how you go about communicating the advantages of a certain client.'' He added, ``A certain amount of chaos is very good in agencies.'' And he said he hopes within three months to be ``playing football in the halls at 5:30 in the afternoon.''
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hamilton</ENAMEX> talked broadly of some of the changes he'd like to make at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ogilvy.</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chiat/Day</ENAMEX> is one of the few American agencies to successfully use British account planning -- a method <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ogilvy</ENAMEX> attempted briefly and largely unsuccessfully, and which Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hamilton</ENAMEX> hopes to ultimately bring with him. In account planning, an executive with a research background represents the consumer, working closely with creative and account executives. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hamilton</ENAMEX> also said he might also bring over some <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chiat/Day</ENAMEX> veterans, though from non-<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> offices.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hamilton</ENAMEX> accepted the job after repeated discussions not just with Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lesser</ENAMEX>, but with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">WPP Group</ENAMEX>'s chief executive officer, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Martin Sorrell</ENAMEX>, who has taken a hands-on approach with his acquisition. ``I probably wouldn't have accepted the job had it not been the combination of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mike {Lesser}</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Martin</ENAMEX>,'' he said.
``I've always been intrigued by those things people say can't be done. Most of the wags and the pundits of the world will say it's pretty tough stuff to turn around an agency that's been going in one direction for a long time,'' he said. ``But I don't think it {the issue} is turning it around -- I think it's getting back to where it was 10 or 15 years ago. There are pockets of brilliance there now.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kraft</ENAMEX> Taps Margeotes
Kraft <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">General Foods Group</ENAMEX> has asked <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Margeotes Fertitta & Weiss</ENAMEX>, a small <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> agency, to try its hand at some creative work on a new product.
A <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Kraft General Foods</ENAMEX> spokesman said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Margeotes</ENAMEX> has been given an assignment to do ``some development work on a venture project.'' Executives close to the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Glenview</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ill.</ENAMEX>-based food giant said the work is for a new coffee beverage product currently in development.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Margeotes</ENAMEX>, whose clients include <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Godiva</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Maccabee</ENAMEX> beer, has had a string of new business wins. It recently picked up the ad accounts for <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Haagen-Dazs</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Newsday</ENAMEX> and for a number of jewelry lines from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Crystal Brands</ENAMEX>.
Separately, the Kraft <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">General Foods</ENAMEX> spokesman said it selected <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">D'Arcy Masius Benton & Bowles</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>, to handle its Sealtest Free non-fat ice cream account. Executives estimated that account is worth about $6 million. The account had been handled by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mccann-Erickson</ENAMEX>.
Ad Notes....
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">LINTAS LAYOFFS</ENAMEX>: About 20 people were laid off at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lintas</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ceco Communications</ENAMEX> subsidiary in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Warren</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mich.</ENAMEX>, on Tuesday. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dick O'Connor</ENAMEX>, chairman and chief executive of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lintas</ENAMEX>:<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Campbell-Ewald</ENAMEX>, said the office isn't growing as expected.
