Stock of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Airlines</ENAMEX> parent <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL Corp.</ENAMEX> gyrated wildly yesterday amid speculation that one or more investors may challenge the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> board's decision to remain independent instead of pursuing a buy-out or other transaction.
The board's decision, announced after the market closed Monday, initially prompted a severe sell-off in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> shares, which at midday traded as low as $145 a share, down $33 a share, in composite trading on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX>.
The deepening bloodbath for takeover-stock traders, who by then had seen <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> stock tumble 49% since Oct. 12, also triggered a marketwide sell-off that sent the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> Industrial Average down more than 80 points at 10:40 a.m.
But then steady, concentrated buying by Bear, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Stearns & Co.</ENAMEX>, which frequently buys stock for corporate raiders, took hold and steadied the fall in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX>, which eventually buoyed the entire market. The industrial average closed down only 3.69 points at 2659.22.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> stock closed at $170 a share, down $8.375. Volume was a tumultuous 4.9 million shares, or 22% of the 21.8 million <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> shares outstanding. Traders estimated that Bear, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stearns</ENAMEX> bought more than 1 million shares.
Takeover-stock traders, stung by their huge losses in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> stock, remained eager for some action by an outside catalyst following the collapse Oct. 13 of a $300-a-share, $6.79 billion labor-management buy-out. Their hope was that the catalyst would seek to oust the board in a solicitation of shareholder consents.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Baker</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nye Investments</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> takeover-stock trader that owns <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> stock, wouldn't comment on reports the firm is considering seeking such a shareholder vote. But partner <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Richard Nye</ENAMEX> said, ``This is the most extraordinary failed transaction I've seen in 25 years in this business. It would make sense for somebody to do it. I have never seen a case of incompetence shared by so many participants.''
In 1986, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Baker</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Nye</ENAMEX> waged a proxy fight for control of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Leaseway Transportation Inc.</ENAMEX> that ultimately led to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Leaseway</ENAMEX>'s being sold.
Some traders pointed hopefully to earlier estimates by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX>'s investment adviser, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Boston Corp.</ENAMEX>, that recapitalizations could yield $245 to $280 a share. But those would require pilots' cooperation.
Any investor who acquires <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> stock in an attempt to force a buy-out or recapitalization must deal with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United</ENAMEX>'s contentious unions. The pilots are working under an expired contract, and the machinists contract expires next month. That gives them enormous leverage, including the threat of a strike to block any buy-out or recapitalization attempt they oppose.
However, a catalyst like <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coniston</ENAMEX> could seek shareholder support for a sale to a labor-management group at the last price discussed by that group before the board meeting Monday. The pilots had been working on a buy-out bid between $225 and $240 a share, or $5.09 billion to $5.42 billion.
One person familiar with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> said the unsettled labor situation and the uncertain world-wide financial markets contributed to the board's decision to avoid ``rushing around selling the company at a bargain price,'' particularly since it accepted a $300-a-share offer just last month.
Even some takeover-stock traders said they couldn't quarrel with the board's logic. But the board's decision prompted many to bail out of the stock yesterday. ``We had a lot of people who threw in the towel today,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Earl Ellis</ENAMEX>, a partner in <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Benjamin Jacobson & Sons</ENAMEX>, a specialist in trading <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> stock on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX>.
Another trader noted that many arbitrage firms are afraid to sell their <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> stock at the bottom, but already own so much they can't buy any more. ``This deal is like a Roach <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Motel</ENAMEX>,'' he said. ``They check in, but they can't check out.''
But both the traders and the pilots remain interested in some transaction. So too, according to many reports, is <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Airways PLC</ENAMEX>, despite its public withdrawal from the buy-out.
The pilots might end up teaming up with their longtime adversaries, the machinists union, in a recapitalization. The machinists are reviewing proposals they made in the past for recapitalizations that would pay a special shareholder dividend and give employees a minority stake. The company rejected those past proposals.
It is unclear, however, if the machinists would support a majority stake, as the pilots want. A machinist official said that would depend on how much in concessions machinists would have to give in return for the majority stake.
Some investors whose names were bandied about by traders as potential <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> stock buyers said they weren't buying. ``I'm not interested,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dallas</ENAMEX> investor <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Harold Simmons</ENAMEX>. A source close to <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Carl Icahn</ENAMEX>, a corporate raider who owns <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Trans World Airlines Inc.</ENAMEX>, said he hasn't owned any <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> stock and isn't buying.
One person familiar with <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Texas</ENAMEX> billionaire <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Robert Bass</ENAMEX> said he isn't likely to make any hostile moves. And a spokesman for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Reliance Group Holdings Inc.</ENAMEX>, which had held 7% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> before the first buy-out bid but later reduced its holdings below 5%, wouldn't comment.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Marvin Davis</ENAMEX>, whose $5.4 billion takeover bid originally put the nation's second-largest airline in play, is limited by a standstill agreement with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> he signed in September. The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Los Angeles</ENAMEX> investor can't buy <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> stock, solicit shareholder consents or make a new offer unless he makes a formal offer of $300 a share or <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> accepts an offer below $300.
However, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Davis</ENAMEX> could pressure the board by asking that the agreement be waived, or letting it be known that he has financing for an offer at a lower price.
