This <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Toronto</ENAMEX> closed-end fund cut the annual dividend on its Class A common shares to one Canadian cent from 10 Canadian cents. The fund invests mainly in gold and silver bullion. It said the reduced dividend reflects the low price for precious metals. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Greg Davies</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Central Fund</ENAMEX>'s vice president, finance, said losses for the fiscal year ending Oct. 31 could be as high as one million Canadian dollars (US$852,000). The fund last had a profit in 1985. The new dividend rate is payable Nov. 15 to holders of record Oct. 31. In <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> composite trading Friday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Central Fund</ENAMEX> was unchanged at $4.6875 a share.
