<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Charles S. Mitchell</ENAMEX>, a vice president with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Homart Development Co.</ENAMEX>, the real estate development subsidiary of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sears</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Roebuck & Co.</ENAMEX>, was named president of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Figgie Properties</ENAMEX>, a real estate development unit. He succeeds <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">William Kohut</ENAMEX>, who resigned earlier this year. Also, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Richard A. Barkley</ENAMEX>, a former marketing executive with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FMC Corp.</ENAMEX>, was appointed president of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Continental Container Systems</ENAMEX>, a producer of can closing machinery that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Figgie</ENAMEX> acquired late last year. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Figgie</ENAMEX> is a fire protection, electronics and industrial products concern.
