Without federal subsidies to developers of beach houses, the economic and structural damage by Hurricane Hugo in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">South Carolina</ENAMEX> would have been much less, as highlighted by your Oct. 3 editorial ``Subsidizing Disaster.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Congress</ENAMEX> should stop throwing tax dollars out to sea by subsidizing the development of beach communities on ecologically fragile coastal barrier islands, such as the hard-hit Isle of Palms near <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Charleston</ENAMEX>.
This bill simply says that if you want to develop property on a barrier island you have to do so without taxpayer support. Private-property rights would be upheld because the legislation would not ban coastal development. However, home builders would have to bear the full costs of such beach-house construction.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Marshall Y. Taylor</ENAMEX>
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Communications Director</ENAMEX>
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">National Taxpayers Union</ENAMEX>
