The loan guarantee would amount to about $127.5 million, or 85% of the cost of the aircraft.
Because of the size of the proposed loan guarantee, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ex-Im Bank</ENAMEX>'s preliminary commitment is subject to review by the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">House</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Senate Banking</ENAMEX> committees. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ex-Im Bank</ENAMEX> officials said this review process currently is under way.
