We read with interest <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Robert Tomsho</ENAMEX>'s Sept. 28 page-one article on <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Robert Redford</ENAMEX> (``The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sundance</ENAMEX> Kid Gets Little Respect Around Sundance''). Misunderstanding conversations with us, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Tomsho</ENAMEX> argued that Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Redford</ENAMEX>'s environmental views are at odds with <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Utah</ENAMEX> residents. This may have been true 10 years ago, but times have changed, even in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Utah</ENAMEX>. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Redford</ENAMEX> no longer stands out as an extremist. He has not changed, but those around him have. Many of his views on the protection of wilderness areas, rivers and canyons are now embraced by mainstream, conservative Utahans.
Recently, some 60 environmental and outdoor groups representing such divergent points of view as the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sierra Club</ENAMEX>, the League of Women Voters and the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">National Rifle Association</ENAMEX> joined together to request a reassessment of the environmentally unsound <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Central Utah</ENAMEX> Project. While <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Utah</ENAMEX> is not yet a haven for environmentalism, public views toward the environment have significantly improved. In one of the most conservative, Republican states in the entire nation, the greening of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Robert Redford</ENAMEX>'s neighbors is the real story that Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Tomsho</ENAMEX> missed.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">David Vranian</ENAMEX>
M.B.A. Student
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">University</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Colorado</ENAMEX>
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Boulder</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Colo</ENAMEX>.
Personally, I'm glad there are people like him around to slow down the profit takers, and those who are in such a blind hurry for something that may appear to benefit them in the immediate future, not caring about the long-range implications.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ron Dyer</ENAMEX>
