<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Armstrong World Industries Inc.</ENAMEX> agreed in principle to sell its carpet operations to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Shaw Industries Inc.</ENAMEX> The price wasn't disclosed but one analyst estimated that it was $150 million.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Armstrong</ENAMEX>, which has faced a takeover threat from the Belzberg family of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Canada</ENAMEX> since <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">July</ENAMEX>, said that disposing of the carpet business would improve ``total financial performance.'' The move also would allow the company to concentrate on core businesses, which include ceramic tile, floor coverings and furniture.
Moreover, such a sale could help <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Armstrong</ENAMEX> reassure its investors and deter the <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Belzbergs</ENAMEX>, who own a 9.85% stake in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Lancaster</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Pa.</ENAMEX>, company. Analysts expect <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Armstrong</ENAMEX> to use proceeds of the sale to reduce debt, buy back stock or perhaps finance an acquisition.
For the past year or two, the carpet division's operating profit margins have hovered around 5%, high by industry standards, but disappointing compared with the 13% to 19% margins for two of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Armstrong</ENAMEX>'s chief businesses, flooring and building products.
Yesterday, in composite trading on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Shaw's</ENAMEX> shares closed ex-dividend at $26.125, up $2.25. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Armstrong</ENAMEX>'s shares, also listed on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX>, closed at $39.125, up 12.5 cents.
Yesterday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Armstrong</ENAMEX> reported flat earnings for the third quarter and nine months, worsened by the stock dilution of an employee stock ownership plan adopted earlier this year.
For the quarter, earnings were $47 million, or 92 cents a share, including a one-time gain of $5.9 million. In the year-ago quarter, earnings were $42.9 million, or 93 cents a share.
Yesterday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Armstrong</ENAMEX> announced an agreement to sell its small <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Applied Color Systems</ENAMEX> unit to a subsidiary of the Swiss company, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Brauerei Eichof Ltd.</ENAMEX> The price wasn't disclosed.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Armstrong</ENAMEX> expects to close the sale of the color unit in late November and the carpet sale in December, with the gains to be applied to fourth quarter or first-quarter results.
