<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">H.F. Ahmanson & Co.</ENAMEX>, the nation's largest thrift holding company, posted a 12% earnings decline for the third quarter while another large <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">California</ENAMEX> savings and loan, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Great Western Financial Corp.</ENAMEX>, reported a slight earnings gain.
Most of the earnings decline reflected an increase in the company's effective tax rate to 44% from 37% in the year-ago third quarter when nonrecurring tax credits were recorded, the company said. Pretax earnings declined 1.3%.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Great Western Financial</ENAMEX> said third-quarter profit rose slightly to $68.4 million, or 52 cents a share, from $67.9 million, or 53 cents a share, from a year ago. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Great Western</ENAMEX>, based in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Beverly Hills</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Calif.</ENAMEX>, is a financial services firm and parent to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Great Western Bank</ENAMEX>, an <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">S&L.</ENAMEX>
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Great Western</ENAMEX> said it had a sharp increase in margins in the recent third quarter. Margins are the difference between the yield on the company's earning assets and its own cost of funds.
But a reduction in one-time gains on the sale of various assets and an increase in the company's provision for loan losses held down the earnings gain, the company said. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Great Western</ENAMEX>'s provision for loan losses was increased to $27.9 million for the recent quarter compared with $21.8 million a year ago primarily as a result of ``continued weakness in various commercial and multifamily real estate markets outside <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">California</ENAMEX>.''
