<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">COCA-COLA Co.</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Atlanta</ENAMEX>) -- <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Anton Amon</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">George Gourlay</ENAMEX> were elected vice presidents of this soft-drink company. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Amon</ENAMEX>, 46 years old, is the company's director of quality assurance; most recently, he served as vice president, operations, for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coca-Cola Enterprises</ENAMEX>. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gourlay</ENAMEX>, 48, is manager for corporate manufacturing operations; he was assistant vice president at the company.
