Two major drug companies posted strong third-quarter earnings, in line with profits already reported by industry leaders and analysts' expectations. But <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pfizer Inc.</ENAMEX>, based in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>, reported flat earnings.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Schering-Plough Corp.</ENAMEX>, based in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Madison</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.J.</ENAMEX>, reported a 21% rise in earnings as <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Home Products Corp.</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> posted an 11% increase in net.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Home Products</ENAMEX> said sales and earnings for the third quarter and nine months were at record levels. Sales for the third quarter increased 6.5% to $1.51 billion from $1.42 billion.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Home Products</ENAMEX> said net income benefited from a ``lower effective tax rate,'' reflecting a reduction of foreign tax rates, and additional operations in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Puerto Rico</ENAMEX>. Net also was aided by a gain on the sale of the company's equity interests in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">South Africa</ENAMEX> effective Sept. 1.
In <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> composite trading yesterday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Home Products</ENAMEX> closed at $102.25 a share, down 75 cents.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pfizer</ENAMEX>
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pfizer</ENAMEX> said third-quarter sales increased 4% to $1.44 billion from $1.38 billion. The company said net income was flat because of investment in research and development and costs related to launches of several products.
The company said the dollar's continued strengthening reduced world-wide sales growth by three percentage points.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pfizer</ENAMEX> posted its largest gains in healthcare sales, up 3%, and consumer products, up 23%. Sales by the specialty chemicals and materials science segments were flat, and sales by the agriculture segment declined 5%.
In <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> composite trading yesterday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pfizer</ENAMEX> closed at $67.75 a share, up 75 cents.
Schering-Plough
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Schering-Plough</ENAMEX> said sales gained 2.7% to $743.7 million from $724.4 million.
In the period, the company completed the sale of its European cosmetics businesses, sold a majority interest in its Brazilian affiliate, and announced the reorganization of its over-the-counter drug businesses into a new unit, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Schering-Plough Health Care Products</ENAMEX>. These actions didn't affect results because the gain on the sale of the European cosmetics businesses was offset by provisions relating to the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Brazil</ENAMEX> divestiture and drug restructuring.
U.S. pharmaceutical sales rose 15%, led by allergy, asthma and cold products; dermatological products; anti-infectives and anti-cancer products; and cardiovascular products.
World-wide consumer product sales declined 12%, primarily because of the European cosmetics sale. Significantly lower sales of `Stay Trim' diet aids also were a factor in the drop. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Maybelline</ENAMEX> beauty product line had higher sales following a sluggish first half.
In <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX> composite trading, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Schering-Plough</ENAMEX> shares fell 75 cents to close at $74.125.
