<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MCA</ENAMEX> said revenue rose 14% to $918.4 million from $806.7 million. The entertainment concern said the success of several movies released during the quarter, including ``Parenthood'' and ``<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Uncle Buck</ENAMEX>,'' contributed to record revenue for its film unit. Both <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MCA</ENAMEX>'s music-entertainment and book-publishing units also posted record revenue and operating profit.
The parent company's net included a loss -- which it didn't specify -- that was related to the company's 50% stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cineplex Odeon Corp.</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cineplex</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Toronto</ENAMEX> theater chain, had a second-quarter net loss of $38.7 million.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MCA</ENAMEX> said net also included certain reserves related to the restructuring of its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">LJN Toys</ENAMEX>' international operations. These items were partly offset, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MCA</ENAMEX> said, by an unspecified gain on the sale of its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Miller International</ENAMEX> unit, a maker and distributor of budget-priced audio cassettes.
In <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> composite trading, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MCA</ENAMEX> rose $1.50 to $64.
