<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Filenet Corp.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Costa Mesa</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Calif.</ENAMEX>, said it expects to report a third-quarter loss of about $1.8 million, or 17 cents a share, because of a $2.5 million reserve to be taken against potential losses on a contract with the state of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">California</ENAMEX>. Revenue is estimated at $18.6 million.
The maker of document image processing equipment said the state procurement division had declared Filenet in default on its contract with the secretary of state uniform commercial code division. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Filenet</ENAMEX> said it doesn't believe the state has a valid basis of default and is reviewing its legal rights under the contract, but said it can't predict the outcome of the dispute.
The disagreement centers on testing deadlines and other issues involving a Filenet system installed earlier this year. State officials couldn't be reached for comment late yesterday.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Filenet</ENAMEX> noted that it had cash and marketable securities totaling $22.5 million on Sept. 30, and stockholders' equity is $60.1 million. The company made the announcement after the close of the markets, where its stock finished at $10.75, up 25 cents, in over-the-counter trading.
