The bank holding company also reported that third-quarter profit dropped 41%, to $42.7 million, or 61 cents a share, from the year-earlier $72.3 million, or $1.04 a share.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Walter Connolly</ENAMEX>, chairman, said in an interview that the company expects to record pretax gains of $100 million to $125 million from the sale of its leasing operations and of certain financial processing services. In a prepared statement, the company said it expects to realize those gains before year end.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Driscoll</ENAMEX> said that, despite continued weakness in the region's real estate market, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bank of New England</ENAMEX> expects the rate of increase in nonperforming assets to slow in coming quarters. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Connolly</ENAMEX> noted that net third-quarter charge-offs, at $63 million, improved slightly from the $67 million in the second quarter. And he indicated that more substantial improvement is expected in the next couple of quarters.
The company increased its loan loss reserve to $354 million from $342 million at the end of the second quarter. Total assets slipped to $31.4 billion, from $32 billion as of June 30.
Among other restructuring measures, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">bank</ENAMEX> said it will close its loan production offices in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chicago</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Philadelphia</ENAMEX>. The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chicago</ENAMEX> office figured prominently in the bank's problems earlier this year, when $65 million in loans to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chicago</ENAMEX> businessman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">William Stoecker</ENAMEX> went sour.
