Spanish stock exchange regulators plan to hand <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Drexel Burnham Lambert Inc.</ENAMEX> the maximum fine for irregularities by its former <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Madrid</ENAMEX> unit in connection with Spanish oil company <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Repsol S.A.</ENAMEX>'s stock issue in May, a senior government official said.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Pedro Perez</ENAMEX>, secretary of state for economic affairs, said the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">National Stock Exchange Commission</ENAMEX> intends to propose the maximum penalty because of what he called the ``decidedly fraudulent'' nature of the operations under scrutiny.
Under Spanish stock market rules, the commission can call for a fine equivalent to as much as five times the profits generated. Based on what <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Drexel</ENAMEX> has said its office made on the transaction, the maximum fine would be 72.5 million pesatas ($621,624).
But <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Carlos Croissier</ENAMEX>, chairman of the commission, yesterday said that figure is incorrect. He declined to say if the actual fine will be higher or lower. He said he hasn't submitted a formal proposal. Under Spanish law, the fine must be proposed by the commission and approved by the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Economy Ministry</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Drexel</ENAMEX> closed its Spanish unit, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">DBL Capital Markets Espana S.A.</ENAMEX>, in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">July</ENAMEX> after confirming that it had used the names of 400 individuals to buy <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Repsol</ENAMEX> shares, which it then resold to institutional clients, circumventing restrictions designed to make shares available to private investors.
In <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>, a spokesman for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Drexel</ENAMEX> said, ``There is nothing to comment on; nothing has been settled yet.
