The banking company couldn't be reached to comment beyond a written announcement. It didn't specify the nature of the differences, saying only that they related to ``management style'' and ``strategic objectives.''
Neither Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Payne</ENAMEX> nor Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Decker</ENAMEX> could be reached to comment.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Decker</ENAMEX>'s resignation surprised many industry officials. He was brought to the company in September 1988 after 15 years at <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Los Angeles</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Interstate Bancorp</ENAMEX>. The bank had been suffering in late 1987 from a slew of bad real estate loans made in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Arizona</ENAMEX>. When he was hired, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Payne</ENAMEX> lauded Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Decker</ENAMEX>'s ``extraordinary... skills'' and his ``outstanding reputation as one of the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">West</ENAMEX>'s brightest bankers.''
Its stock also has risen lately, at least partly because it is considered a possible takeover candidate. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Interstate banking</ENAMEX> is scheduled to begin in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">California</ENAMEX> in 1991, and larger <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">California</ENAMEX> banks, such as <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Wells Fargo & Co.</ENAMEX>, have been paying fat premiums to buy smaller banks to control markets before any out-of-state banks enter the fray.
