The stock market went on a dizzying ride as <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX>, parent of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Airlines</ENAMEX>, once again led shares into a breathtaking decline and then an afternoon comeback.
``October 13th left us with a cut and exposed nerve,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jack Solomon</ENAMEX>, technical analyst for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bear Stearns</ENAMEX>. ``People are fearful and sensitive. Everybody's finger is one inch closer to the button. I have never had as many calls as I had this morning. Volatility is here to stay.''
For many, it began to look like a replay of Oct. 13. As stocks and stock-index futures fell, a trading limit was hit in the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">S&P</ENAMEX> 500 stock futures pit. Under a post-1987 crash reform, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chicago Mercantile Exchange</ENAMEX> wouldn't permit the December <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">S&P</ENAMEX> futures to fall further than 12 points for a half hour. That caused a brief period of panic selling of stocks on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX>. But at a critical moment, stock-index arbitrage traders showed their power and control. They scooped up hundreds of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">S&P</ENAMEX> futures when the market needed it most.
At about 10:40 a.m. <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">EDT</ENAMEX>, several big buy orders hit the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">S&P</ENAMEX> pit simultaneously, lifting the futures up out of the trading limit and eventually into ranges that caused computer-driven program buying of stocks.
``It is very clear that those buy orders came from people who wanted their franchise protected,'' said one <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chicago</ENAMEX>-based futures trader. ``These guys wanted to do something to show how powerful they are.''
Traders said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Goldman Sachs</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Shearson Lehman Hutton</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Salomon Brothers</ENAMEX> were the main force behind the futures buying at the pivotal moment. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Shearson Lehman Hutton</ENAMEX> declined to comment. Officials at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Goldman Sachs</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Salomon Brothers</ENAMEX> were unavailable for comment.
As in the Oct. 13 massacre, yesterday morning's drop was triggered by bad news for speculators in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX>. A <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> statement after the market closed Monday indicated that the airline's board wanted to keep the company independent, effectively crushing hopes of an immediate buy-out. Five minutes before the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX> opened, a preliminary price was flashed for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> -- somewhere between 135 and 155, a loss of as much as $43 a share from Monday's close.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> finally opened for trading at 10:08 a.m. at 150, down $28. Floor traders said there was a huge crowd around the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX> specialist's post where <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> trades. ``There was a seething mass of people,'' said one floor trader. ``Then there was a big liquidation of stock'' across the board, he added.
Takeover speculators -- who have already taken a record loss estimated at more than $700 million on <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> -- started selling other stocks as well as <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">S&P</ENAMEX> futures in an attempt to hedge against a further <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> blood bath. Shortly after the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> opening, program traders started selling stocks in the Major Market Index and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">S&P</ENAMEX> 500 index. The 20-stock MMI mimics the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones Industrial Average</ENAMEX>.
By 10:30 a.m. the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow</ENAMEX> was down 62.70. All 20-stocks in the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MMI</ENAMEX> except <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Exxon</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">General Motors</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sears</ENAMEX> were down $1 to $2.
At 10:33, when the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">S&P</ENAMEX> 500 December futures contract crunched to a 12-point loss under the force of sell programs, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">S&P</ENAMEX> futures trading was halted and program trades on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX> were routed into a special computer that scans for order imbalances. Under the rules adopted by the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chicago Mercantile Exchange</ENAMEX>, the futures contract can not drop below the limit, but buyers can purchase futures. At this point, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow</ENAMEX> industrials were down 75.41 points and falling.
The trading halt in the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">S&P</ENAMEX> 500 futures exacerbated selling and confusion, many traders maintain. But as the fright began to spread through the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">S&P</ENAMEX> pit, the big brokerage firms came in and bought futures aggressively.
Traders said the futures buying was finely calculated by program traders. These firms sold stock into the big morning decline, but seeing the velocity of the market's drop, held back on their offsetting purchases of futures until the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">S&P</ENAMEX> futures hit the trading limit. Then they completed the other side of the trade by buying futures, which abruptly halted the stock market's decline as traders began to buy stocks.
From then on, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow</ENAMEX> industrials held at a loss of 40 to 50 points. Then, in late-afternoon trading, hundred-thousand-share buy orders for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> hit the market, including a 200,000-share order through <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bear Stearns</ENAMEX> that seemed to spark <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX>'s late price surge. Almost simultaneously, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Painewebber</ENAMEX> began a very visible buy program for dozens of stocks. The combined buying rallied the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow</ENAMEX> into a small gain, before closing at a slight loss.
Some institutional traders loved the wild ride. ``This is fun,'' asserted <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Susan Del Signore</ENAMEX>, head equity trader at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Travelers Investment Management Co.</ENAMEX> She said she used the market's wild swings to buy shares cheaply on the sell-off. On the comeback, Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Del Signore</ENAMEX> unloaded shares she has been aiming to get rid of.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> climbed 5 3/4 to 41 on very heavy volume of 786,100 shares. Analysts said a big Japanese buy order was behind the rise. A <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> spokesman said there were no corporate developments that would account for the activity. Other issues said to be included in the buy program were <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Procter & Gamble</ENAMEX>, which rose 2 7/8 to 133 1/2; <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Atlantic Richfield</ENAMEX>, which gained 2 to 103 3/4, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rockwell International</ENAMEX>, which jumped 2 3/4 to 27 1/8. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Painewebber</ENAMEX> declined to comment.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> finished at 170, off 8 3/8. Other airline stocks fell in response to the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> board's decision to remain independent for now, including <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Usair Group</ENAMEX>, which separately reported a third-quarter loss of $1.86 a share compared with a year-ago profit. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Usair</ENAMEX> fell 2 1/2 to 40.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AMR</ENAMEX>, the parent of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Airlines</ENAMEX>, fell 1 3/4 to 68 7/8 on 2.3 million shares; <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Delta Air Lines</ENAMEX> lost 1 1/2 to 66, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Southwest Airlines</ENAMEX> slid 3/4 to 24 1/4 and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Midway Airlines</ENAMEX> dropped 1/4 to 14 7/8. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Texas Air</ENAMEX>, which owns Continental and Eastern airlines, lost 3/8 to 13 1/8 on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Stock Exchange</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Goodyear Tire & Rubber</ENAMEX> tumbled 2 7/8 to 43 7/8. Its third-quarter earnings were higher than a year ago, but fell short of expectations. Other stocks in the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow</ENAMEX> industrials that failed to benefit from the market's rebound included <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Technologies</ENAMEX>, which dropped 1 to 53 5/8, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bethle hem Steel</ENAMEX>, which fell 1 to 16 7/8.
Dividend-related trading swelled volume in two issues: <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Security Pacific</ENAMEX>, which fell 7/8 to 44 1/2 and led the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX>'s most actives list on composite volume of 14.8 million shares, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nipsco Industries</ENAMEX>, which lost 3/8 to 17 3/8 on 4.4 million shares. Both stocks have dividend yields of about 5% and will go ex-dividend Wednesday.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Kellogg</ENAMEX> surged 4 1/4 to 75. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Donaldson, Lufkin & Jenrette</ENAMEX> placed the stock on its list of recommended issues. The company noted that its third-quarter results should be released later this week or early next week.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Georgia Gulf</ENAMEX>, another producer of commodity chemicals, advanced 2 to 49 1/2; <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dallas</ENAMEX> investor <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Harold Simmons</ENAMEX>, who holds about 10% of its shares, said he hasn't raised his stake.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Airborne Freight</ENAMEX> climbed 1 1/8 to 38 1/2. Its third-quarter earnings more than doubled from a year earlier and exceeded analysts' expectations.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John Harland</ENAMEX>, which will replace <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Medical International</ENAMEX> on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">S&P</ENAMEX> 500 following Wednesday's close, gained 5/8 to 24 1/8.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Amex</ENAMEX> Market Value Index fell 3.10 to 376.36. Volume totaled 14,560,000 shares.
