<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bank of New York Co.</ENAMEX> said it agreed in principle to acquire the credit-card business of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Houston</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First City Bancorp.</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Texas</ENAMEX> for between $130 million and $134 million.
The move, subject to a definitive agreement, is part of a trend by big-city banks that have been buying up credit-card portfolios to expand their business. Just last month, a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bank of New York</ENAMEX> subsidiary agreed to buy the credit-card operation of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dreyfus Corp.</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dreyfus Consumer Bank</ENAMEX> for $168 million, a transaction that is expected to be completed by the end of the year.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First City</ENAMEX> said that because of increased competition in the credit-card business, it had decided it either had to expand its own holdings substantially or sell them. ``We think there's a good prospect that competition is going to get pretty fierce in this market,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">James E. Day</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First City</ENAMEX> vice president. ``We see it becoming a bargain-basement kind of business.''
The company estimated that the transaction would enhance its book value, which stood at $28.55 a share on Sept. 30, by more than $100 million, or about $4 a share. The company also said the transaction would bolster after-tax earnings by $3.25 a share when completed and boost its primary capital ratio to 7% from 6.63%.
``I think they'll be able to move faster to make acquisitions in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Texas</ENAMEX>,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Brent Erensel</ENAMEX>, an analyst with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Donaldson, Lufkin & Jenrette.</ENAMEX> ``That's something they can do very well.
