``<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mattel</ENAMEX>'s world-wide volume has grown 25% in a climate of relatively flat industry sales,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John W. Amerman</ENAMEX>, chairman. He said the toy company's ``prospects for a strong fourth quarter'' are also good.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mattel</ENAMEX> attributed the jump in quarter net to strong world-wide sales of its Barbie doll, Hot Wheels cars, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Disney</ENAMEX> toys and other well-known toy lines. The company also cited retail trade and consumer demand for new products introduced this year, such as Cherry Merry <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Muffin</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Turtle Tots.</ENAMEX>
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mattel</ENAMEX> said the company's sale of rights to land and buildings at its <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hawthorne</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Calif.</ENAMEX>, headquarters resulted in a $13 million charge to third-quarter operating profit. The charge didn't affect net for the quarter as it was offset by tax benefits.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mattel</ENAMEX> has purchased a new headquarters building in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">El Segundo</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Calif.</ENAMEX>, which it will occupy by the end of next year.
