Growth is good.
At least, that's a theme emerging among many money managers who are anxious both to preserve the handsome stock-market gains they have already achieved this year and to catch the next wave of above-average performers. They are starting to buy growth stocks.
``I think it is a good theme for what looks to be an uncertain market,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steven Einhorn</ENAMEX>, partner at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Goldman Sachs</ENAMEX>.
Growth stocks may be as big as <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Philip Morris</ENAMEX> or medium-sized such as <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Circuit City Stores</ENAMEX>, but their common characteristic is a history of increasing profits on the order of at least 15% to 20% a year, money managers say.
``The period when growth stocks should be performing well is when their earnings are growing at a superior rate to the general level of corporate profits,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stephen Boesel</ENAMEX>, president of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">T. Rowe Price's Growth and Income Fund</ENAMEX>.
Growth stocks also are attractive in periods of market volatility, which many investors and analysts expect in the weeks ahead as everybody tries to discern where the economy is heading. This kind of jumpy uncertainty reminds <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John Calverley</ENAMEX>, senior economist for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Express Bank</ENAMEX>, of the 1969-72 period, when the industrial average rolled through huge ranges and investors flocked to the shares of companies with proven earnings records, which became known as the ``nifty 50.''
And they will again, say money-manager proponents of the growth-stock theme. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Cabanne Smith</ENAMEX>, president of a money management company bearing his name, predicts that investment companies using computers to identify companies with earnings ``momentum'' will climb on the growth-stock bandwagon as the overall corporate earnings outlook deteriorates further. He also thinks foreign investors, who are showing signs of more discriminate investing, will join the pursuit and pump up prices.
``We're just seeing the beginning of a shift,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Smith</ENAMEX> says. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Smith</ENAMEX> recommends <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cypress Semiconductor</ENAMEX> that is currently showing a robust 63% earnings growth rate.
Others preach the gospel of buying only blue-chip growth stocks. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Carmine Grigoli</ENAMEX>, chief market strategist for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Boston</ENAMEX>, who still says, ``We expect the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow</ENAMEX> average {to be at} 3000 by mid-1990,'' nonetheless foresees a sluggish economy in the meantime. He recommends such blue-chip growth stalwarts as <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Philip Morris</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pepsico</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CPC International</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Reebok International</ENAMEX>, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Limited Inc.</ENAMEX> All have a fiveyear earnings growth rate of more than 20% a year.
Some money managers are pursuing growth stocks at the expense of those that rise and fall along with the economic cycle. ``One of the stories of the fourth quarter is that we will get an unusual number of earnings disappointments from companies sensitive to the economy,'' says Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Boesel</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">T. Rowe Price</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">James Wright</ENAMEX>, chief investment officer for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Banc One Asset Management</ENAMEX>, says, ``We've been selling a disproportionate share of cyclical companies and buying a disproportionate share of high earnings stocks.'' He recently trimmed his portfolio of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">International Paper</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Chemical</ENAMEX>, Quantum <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chemical</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">International Business Machines</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Digital Equipment.</ENAMEX> He is putting money in Dress Barn, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Circuit City Stores</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bruno's</ENAMEX>, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rubbermaid</ENAMEX>.
Big cyclical companies are using ``all the tricks they can to stabilize earnings,'' says Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Sloan</ENAMEX>. He cites <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IBM</ENAMEX>, which reported a 30% earnings decline in the third quarter, and which last week announced a $1 billion buy-back of its shares.
But not all strategists or money managers are ready to throw in the towel completely on cyclicals. Growth stocks may underperform cyclical stocks next year if the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal Reserve</ENAMEX> begins to let interest rates drift sufficiently lower to boost the economy. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Goldman Sachs</ENAMEX>'s Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Einhorn</ENAMEX>, for one, subscribes to that scenario. He suggests investors think about buying cyclical shares in the weeks ahead, as well as growth issues.
Stock prices finished about unchanged Friday in quiet expiration trading.
Traders anticipated a volatile session due to the October expiration of stock-index futures and options, and options on individual stocks. But there were fewer price swings than expected. Buy order imbalances on several big stocks were posted by the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX>. But block trading desks and money managers made a concerted effort to meet the imbalances with stock to sell, one trader said.
As a result, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> Industrial Average drifted in narrow ranges in the final hour of trading, and closed 5.94 higher to 2689.14. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> volume was 164,830,000. Advancers on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX> lagged decliners 662 to 829.
For the week, the industrial average gained 119.88 points, or 4.7%, the biggest weekly point advance ever and a better than 50% rebound from the 190.58 point loss the industrial average logged Oct. 13.
Broader market averages were little changed in the latest session. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Standard & Poor</ENAMEX>'s 500-Stock Index gained 0.03 to 347.16, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> Equity Market Index fell 0.02 to 325.50, and the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> Composite Index fell 0.05 to 192.12.
That contrast was reflected in the smaller weekly percentage gains recorded by the broader averages. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">S&P</ENAMEX> 500 rose 4%, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> Equity Market index gained 3.7% and the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> composite index added 3.5%.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones Transportation Average</ENAMEX> fell 32.71 to 1230.80 amid renewed weakness in the airline sector.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> skidded 21 5/8 to 168 1/2 on 2.2 million shares. On the week, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> was down nearly 40%. The latest drop followed a decision by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Airways</ENAMEX>, which had supported the $300-a-share buy-out offer for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> from a labor-management group, not to participate in any revised bid. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Airways</ENAMEX> fell 1 to 31 7/8.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dun & Bradstreet</ENAMEX> dropped 3/4 to 51 1/8 on 1.9 million shares on uncertainty about the company's earnings prospects. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merrill Lynch</ENAMEX> cut its rating and 1990 earnings estimate Thursday, citing weakness in its credit-rating business.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lamson & Sessions</ENAMEX>, which posted sharply lower third-quarter earnings and forecast that results for the fourth quarter might be ``near break-even,'' fell 1/2 to 9 1/4.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Winnebago Industries</ENAMEX> slid 5/8 to 5 1/4. The company, which reported that its loss for the fiscal quarter ended Aug. 26 widened from a year earlier, cut its semiannual dividend in half in response to the earnings weakness.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Massmutual Corporate Investors</ENAMEX> fell 3 to 29 after declaring a quarterly dividend of 70 cents a share, down from 95 cents a share.
