The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">California Department of Insurance</ENAMEX> charged <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Farmers Insurance Exchange</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mid-Century Insurance Co.</ENAMEX> with discriminating against three groups of automobile insurance customers.
The department didn't specify how many consumers have been hurt by the alleged discriminatory practices, saying only that they ``affect a substantial number of people.'' The department claims, however, that Farmers and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mid</ENAMEX>-<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Century</ENAMEX>, both members of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Farmers Group of Insurance Cos.</ENAMEX>, are steering customers who might qualify for Farmers policies toward higher-priced Mid-Century policies. The customers affected are under the age of 25, youths living in households of preferred policyholders and drivers under the age of 50 who seek minimal coverage, the department said.
``As <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mid</ENAMEX>-<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Century</ENAMEX>'s rates are up to 40 percent higher than Farmers for the same coverage, we have a situation in which the companies effectively raise rates for the new business by denying coverage in Farmers,'' Roxani <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gillespie</ENAMEX>, the state's insurance commissioner, said in a prepared statement. ``And that's discrimination in our book.''
A spokesman for Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gillespie</ENAMEX> said the department expected to hold a hearing on the matter within 30 days. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Farmers Group of Insurance</ENAMEX> is a unit of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">B.A.T Industries PLC</ENAMEX>.
In <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Los Angeles</ENAMEX>, Farmers strongly defended its practices, saying its rating guidelines are ``fair and reasonable and in line with common industry practices. We have carefully considered our underwriting practices and we believe they are in compliance with the law and its intent,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John Millen</ENAMEX>, a spokesman for the company.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Millen</ENAMEX> said Farmers would review the insurance department's charges and respond within the ten days allowed.
