<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rio Algom Ltd.</ENAMEX> said it agreed to acquire <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Uranium Resources Inc.</ENAMEX> for $2.55 a share, or about $66 million.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rio Algom</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Toronto</ENAMEX>-based mining concern, said the transaction is subject to a comprehensive review of the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dallas</ENAMEX>-based company's business and the signing of a definitive agreement.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Uranium Resources</ENAMEX> earlier this month said it had signed a non-binding letter of intent for the acquisition of all of its shares but didn't identify the proposed purchaser. The closely held uranium producer also said it agreed to pay <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rio Algom</ENAMEX> $2 million plus expenses if the proposed deal isn't completed and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Uranium Resources</ENAMEX> enters certain other transactions.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rio</ENAMEX> said the proposed acquisition reflects its expectation that uranium prices will begin to pick up in coming months from their recent depressed state.
Separately, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rio Algom</ENAMEX> said it agreed to pay <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Whittaker Corp.</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Los Angeles</ENAMEX> $30 million to acquire <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Whittaker Metals</ENAMEX>, a metals distribution business with four facilities in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Southwest</ENAMEX> region.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rio</ENAMEX> said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Whittaker Metals</ENAMEX>' geographical base complements <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rio</ENAMEX>'s Vincent Metals business, with outlets mainly in central and southeastern states.
