<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Health Care Property Investors Inc.</ENAMEX> said it acquired three long-term care facilities and one assisted-living facility in a purchase-and-lease transaction valued at $15 million.
The real estate investment trust said that it leased the three <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Florida</ENAMEX> facilities to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">National Health Care Affiliates Inc.</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Buffalo</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.Y.</ENAMEX>
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Health Care Property</ENAMEX> holds an interest in 139 facilities in 30 states.
