<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Accor S.A.</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">France</ENAMEX> withdrew from an agreement to acquire a 51% stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Greetings Group Ltd.</ENAMEX>, an Australian hotel operator.
A spokesman for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Credit Lyonnais May Mellor Ltd.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Accor</ENAMEX>'s Australian financial adviser, said in a telephone interview that Accor ``decided that the deal as originally structured wasn't suitable.''
But negotiations are continuing and a new agreement might be reached next month, the spokesman added.
``<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Accor</ENAMEX> would still like to have a presence in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Australia</ENAMEX>, and alternative arrangements are being considered,'' the spokesman said. He wouldn't discuss any details of the new proposals.
In September, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Accor</ENAMEX> entered into an option agreement with major shareholders of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Greetings</ENAMEX> that would have given Accor a 51% stake through an issue of new shares.
