Lawyers for former <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Housing and Urban Development</ENAMEX> Secretary <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Samuel Pierce</ENAMEX> say he again will refuse to answer questions from a congressional subcommittee investigating federal housing scandals.
In a letter to Rep. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Tom Lantos</ENAMEX> (D., <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Calif.</ENAMEX>), chairman of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">House Government Operations</ENAMEX> subcommittee on housing and employment, the lawyers said Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Pierce</ENAMEX> would invoke his Fifth Amendment protection against self-incrimination at hearings scheduled for today and Friday.
On Sept. 26, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Pierce</ENAMEX> invoked the Fifth Amendment and refused to testify. At that time, he said his lawyers hadn't been given enough time to prepare. The letter sent yesterday to Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lantos</ENAMEX> says Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Pierce</ENAMEX> ``is concerned that there continues to be an atmosphere wherein he remains a target of the subcommittee's hearings.''
In the letter, lawyers <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Paul Perito</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Robert Plotkin</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Inez Smith</ENAMEX> say they ``hope that sometime in the near future the present level of tension may be reduced such that Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Pierce</ENAMEX> can reconsider his present position and testify under fair and mutually agreeable circumstances.
