<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Berkshire Hathaway</ENAMEX> earlier this year bought $600 million of preferred stock in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Gillette</ENAMEX> that is convertible into an 11% stake, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Gillette</ENAMEX> said at the time that Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Buffett</ENAMEX> would be added to the board.
Separately, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Gillette</ENAMEX> said its third-quarter earnings rose 2% to $65.2 million, or 57 cents a share, from $63.9 million, or 57 cents a share, in the year-earlier period; per-share earnings remained flat despite an increase in net income in part because the company paid a $10.4 million dividend on the new preferred stock in the period. Sales rose 9% to $921.6 million from $845.7 million, with sales of the company's international\ operations ``well above'' the year earlier-period.
For the nine months, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Gillette</ENAMEX>'s net income declined 1% to $205.3 million, or $2.02 a share, from $207 million, or $1.82 a share, in the 1988 period. Sales rose 6% to $2.77 billion from $2.61 billion.
