Benjamin <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Franklin Federal Savings & Loan Association</ENAMEX> said it plans to restructure in the wake of a third-quarter loss of $7.7 million, or $1.01 a share, reflecting an $11 million addition to loan-loss reserves.
In over-the-counter trading yesterday, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Benjamin Franklin</ENAMEX> rose 25 cents to $4.25.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Initially</ENAMEX>, the company said it will close its commercial real-estate lending division, and stop originating new leases at its commercial lease subsidiary.
Details of the restructuring won't be made final until regulators approve the regulations mandated by the new federal act, the company said.
