U.S. steel imports in August fell 14% from a year earlier to 1,531,000 tons, according to the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Iron and Steel Institute</ENAMEX>.
The trade group's compilation of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Commerce Department</ENAMEX> data showed that August imports, the second largest monthly total of the year, were up 5% from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">July</ENAMEX>'s 1,458,000 tons but below last year's high of 1,979,000 tons in June 1988.
August imports claimed 18.5% of the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> market, compared with 19.3% in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">July</ENAMEX> and 20.5% in August 1988. The latest month's figures show that imports of steel from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">European Community</ENAMEX> nations fell to 466,000 tons from 481,000 a month earlier, while imports from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX> rose to 323,000 tons from 288,000 in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">July</ENAMEX>. Imports from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Canada</ENAMEX> rose to 272,000 tons in August from 209,000 in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">July</ENAMEX>.
