<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Chemical Co.</ENAMEX> said its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Destec Energy Inc.</ENAMEX> unit has agreed to buy <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">PSE Inc.</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Houston</ENAMEX> energy company, in a deal valued at about $115 million.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow</ENAMEX>, of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Midland</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mich.</ENAMEX>, said its unit will begin by Thursday a tender offer of $12.25 a share for all <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">PSE</ENAMEX> common shares outstanding. Among other conditions, the offer depends on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow</ENAMEX> unit acquiring at least 66 2/3% of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">PSE</ENAMEX> shares outstanding, the companies said in a joint statement Friday.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">PSE</ENAMEX> has about 9.2 million shares outstanding. The company said the approximately $115 million acquisition price includes its total $33 million of long-term debt outstanding. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow</ENAMEX> said it already has agreements with <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Albert J. Smith Jr.</ENAMEX>, chairman and chief executive officer of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">PSE</ENAMEX>, and certain other officers of the company under which <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow</ENAMEX> may buy about 40% of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">PSE</ENAMEX> common shares outstanding.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">PSE</ENAMEX> is a designer and operator of energy-cogeneration facilities and had 1988 sales of $234 million. The company is owner and operator, or an equity partner, in six cogeneration facilities -- two in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Texas</ENAMEX> and four in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">California</ENAMEX>.
The company said recently it expects third-quarter earnings will be in range from $1.3 million to $1.7 million, or 14 cents to 18 cents a share, compared with $326,000, or four cents a share, a year ago.
