<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar PLC</ENAMEX>'s chairman said he hopes to reach a friendly pact with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">General Motors Corp.</ENAMEX> within a month that may involve the British luxury-car maker's producing a cheaper executive model.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> figures a friendly alliance with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX> will fend off unwelcome advances from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford Motor Co.</ENAMEX> But <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX>'s biggest shareholder since lifting its stake to 10.4% this week, is pressing harder for talks with Sir <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John</ENAMEX>. ``We're getting to the point where we are going to have to meet'' with him, one <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> official said yesterday. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> probably will renew its request for such a meeting soon, he added.
Sir <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John</ENAMEX> has spurned <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX>'s advances since the U.S. auto giant launched a surprise bid for as much as 15% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> last month. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> has signaled it might acquire a majority interest later. ``I'm not obligated to sit down and talk to anybody,'' the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> chairman asserted yesterday. He didn't rule out negotiations with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX>, however. The fiercely proud but financially strapped British company prefers to remain independent and publicly held, despite <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX>'s promise of access to cash and technological know-how.
Sir <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John</ENAMEX> noted that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX>, a longtime <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> supplier, agrees ``we should remain an independent company.'' He said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> started negotiating with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX> and several other car makers over a year ago, but the rest ``dropped by the wayside ever since the share price went above # 4 ($6.30) a share.'' <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> shares stood at 405 pence before <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX>'s initial announcement, but the subsequent takeover frenzy has driven them up. The stock traded late yesterday on <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX>'s stock exchange at 673 pence, up 19 pence.
Developing an executive-model range would mark a major departure for <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX>'s leading luxury-car maker. A typical British executive car is mass produced and smaller than a luxury car. It generally fetches no more than # 25,000 ($39,400) -- roughly # 16,000 less than the highest-priced <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Jaguars</ENAMEX>, which are all known for their hand-crafted leather work.
A pact with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX> may emerge in as little as two weeks, according to sources close to the talks. The deal would require approval by a majority of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> shareholders. ``We have to make it attractive enough that {holders} would accept it,'' Sir <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John</ENAMEX> said.
But with its 10.4% stake, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> can convene a special <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> shareholders' meeting and urge them to drop the restrictions prematurely. ``It's a very valuable weapon in their armory,'' which could enable <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> to bid sooner for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX>, observed Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Barber</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">James Capel.</ENAMEX>
