<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Norfolk Southern Corp.</ENAMEX> directors authorized the railroad company to buy back as many as 45 million of its shares, which would have a current value of more than $1.7 billion.
In a statement, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Arnold B. Mckinnon</ENAMEX>, chairman and chief executive officer, noted that the new repurchase program ``should serve to enhance shareholder value.'' A spokeswoman said the company will finance the buy-back with cash on hand, borrowing and ``cash Norfolk expects to generate.''
Analysts said they expected the action, and investors applauded the move. In composite trading on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Norfolk Southern</ENAMEX> shares closed at $37.875, up $1.125.
Still, analysts don't expect the buy-back to significantly affect per-share earnings in the short term. ``The impact won't be that great,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Graeme Lidgerwood</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Boston Corp.</ENAMEX> That is in part because of the effect of having to average the number of shares outstanding, she said. In addition, Mrs. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lidgerwood</ENAMEX> said, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Norfolk</ENAMEX> is likely to draw down its cash initially to finance the purchases and thus forfeit some interest income.
Longer term, however, the buy-back is expected to increase earnings, especially after 1990, Mrs. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lidgerwood</ENAMEX> said.
Moreover, the extensive program in effect establishes a floor for the stock price, said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Joel Price</ENAMEX>, analyst for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Donaldson, Lufkin & Jenrette.</ENAMEX> The buy-back ``is really a comfort to those who want to buy the stock that there is a {price} floor,'' he said. ``At a certain price, if the management thinks {the stock} is cheap, they can go in and buy it.''
Under the program, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Norfolk</ENAMEX> plans to acquire shares in the open market.
Under the earlier plan, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Norfolk</ENAMEX> was authorized in 1987 to buy up to 20 million shares. It has purchased about 19 million of them.
