<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Carl E. Pissocra</ENAMEX>, president and chief executive officer of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bank One</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dover</ENAMEX>, has been named regional president, a new post at the bank-holding company. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Pissocra</ENAMEX>, 56 years old, will be responsible for the company's 10 banks in the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Eastern</ENAMEX> region. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dan J. Hartwell</ENAMEX>, 41, executive vice president of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bank One</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dover</ENAMEX>, was named president and chief executive of the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dover</ENAMEX> bank, succeeding Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Pissocra</ENAMEX>. No one was named to succeed Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hartwell</ENAMEX>.
