THE HIGH-SCHOOL dropout rate in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Pope County</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ill.</ENAMEX>, is markedly lower than one stated in a page-one article Oct. 13, according to the area's high-school principal. The figure in the article was based on federal data provided by the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lower Mississippi Delta Development Commission</ENAMEX>.
(See: ``River of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Despair</ENAMEX>: Along the Rich Banks of the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mississippi Live</ENAMEX> Poorest of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.S. Poor</ENAMEX> -- They Endure a Lack of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Jobs</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Plantation Mentality</ENAMEX>, While <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Landowners Thrive</ENAMEX> -- Where Dreams of Blacks Die'' -- <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">WSJ</ENAMEX> Oct. 23, 1989
