Regional thrift regulators charged that phone calls were bugged during the examination of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lincoln Savings & Loan Association</ENAMEX> and that federal officials in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Washington</ENAMEX> delayed <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Lincoln</ENAMEX>'s seizure until its $2.5 billion cost made it the most expensive thrift failure ever.
``Clearly, we were shot in the back... as we battled to protect the taxpayers,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">William Black</ENAMEX>, acting district counsel for the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">San Francisco</ENAMEX> region of thrift regulators.
In a day of extraordinary testimony before the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">House Banking Committee</ENAMEX>, officials from the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">San Francisco Office of Thrift Supervision</ENAMEX> also testified that a Big Eight accounting firm, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Arthur Andersen & Co.</ENAMEX>, participated in back-dating loan documents and that the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Washington</ENAMEX> officials even agreed in one document not to prosecute <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Lincoln</ENAMEX> over certain infractions.
The hearing may also add to the unease of Sens. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Alan Cranston</ENAMEX> (D., <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Calif.</ENAMEX>) and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dennis Deconcini</ENAMEX> (D., <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ariz.</ENAMEX>), who are being scrutinized for intervening on behalf of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lincoln</ENAMEX>, a unit of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Continental Corp.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Phoenix</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ariz.</ENAMEX> The officials said Sen. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Deconcini</ENAMEX> and an aide to Sen. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Cranston</ENAMEX> called <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">California</ENAMEX> state thrift officials to press for a sale of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Lincoln</ENAMEX>, instead of its seizure.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Witnesses</ENAMEX> said the room in which <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">California examiners</ENAMEX> were auditing <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Lincoln</ENAMEX> this past spring was bugged. According to a government memo, regulators who took control of the thrift in August discovered that a phone line in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Lincoln</ENAMEX>'s headquarters in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Irvine</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Calif.</ENAMEX>, had been ``compromised'' to allow calls to be monitored on other extensions. It didn't say who was monitoring the calls, but said the matter was turned over to the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal Bureau</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Investigation</ENAMEX>.
A <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lincoln</ENAMEX> spokesman said its management ``never authorized or participated in any bugging of anyone.''
The regional officials said <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Washington</ENAMEX>'s chief thrift regulator, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Danny Wall</ENAMEX>, and his principal lieutenants repeatedly ignored warnings that <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Lincoln</ENAMEX> was being operated in a reckless manner, certain to cause its failure. They also accused Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Wall</ENAMEX> of holding improper meetings with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lincoln</ENAMEX> officials, while refusing to listen to field examiners.
Members of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Banking Committee</ENAMEX> generally received the regional officials as bureaucratic heroes and sharply criticized their <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Washington bosses</ENAMEX>, who had relieved them of their responsibility for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lincoln</ENAMEX> two years before the thrift's parent filed for bankruptcy-law protection.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Committee</ENAMEX> Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Henry Gonzalez</ENAMEX> (D., <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Texas</ENAMEX>) said Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Wall</ENAMEX> ``willingly cut the legs out from under his regulatory troops in the middle of the battle,'' and renewed his call for Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Wall</ENAMEX> to step aside. Rep. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Joseph Kennedy</ENAMEX> (D., <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mass.</ENAMEX>) said, ``The higher up in the regulatory process, the more corrupt it would appear.''
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Wall</ENAMEX> is scheduled to testify Nov. 7, and his agency said that all sides of the issue should be heard before drawing conclusions. Separately, other <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Washington</ENAMEX> thrift officials disputed the regional examiners' statement that they had called specifically for the seizure of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Lincoln</ENAMEX> in 1987, saying that it was only one option they presented.
The regional officials also said that <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Arthur Andersen</ENAMEX> backdated data to support loans that were made with no underwriting standards. Over two years, until April 1986, $1 billion in loans were approved, even though <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Lincoln</ENAMEX> had no written loan standards, said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mike Patriarca</ENAMEX>, acting principal supervisory agent with the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Office of Thrift Supervision</ENAMEX>. Fifty-two loans were made in March 1986, he said, and none had credit reports or other background work completed.
``At a later time, the files looked good because they had been stuffed,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Patriarca</ENAMEX> said. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Leonard Bickwit</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Washington</ENAMEX> attorney for <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Lincoln</ENAMEX>, conceded that some memos had been written after the fact. He said that ``memorialization of underwriting activities that had been undertaken at an earlier time'' did occur, but that <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Lincoln</ENAMEX> believed it adhered to lending standards superior to the industry average.
A spokesman for <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Arthur Andersen</ENAMEX> denied any improprieties, adding, ``At the request of our then-client, we provided staff personnel to work for a limited period of time under the direction of client personnel to assist them in organizing certain files.''
The matter is under active criminal investigation at the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Justice Department</ENAMEX>, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Black</ENAMEX> said.
The hearings also disclosed that <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Washington</ENAMEX> officials promised in May 1988 not to launch any civil or criminal actions based on an examination in which regional officials concluded that <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Lincoln</ENAMEX> was being operated in an unsafe and unsound manner.
``Giving up the right to make criminal referrals to me is inconceivable,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Black</ENAMEX> said.
The committee also heard testimony from two officials who said that Sens. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Cranston</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Deconcini</ENAMEX>, who received campaign contributions from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lincoln</ENAMEX> Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Charles Keating Jr.</ENAMEX>, arranged for telephone calls on their behalf to state thrift regulators. The officials said both calls encouraged a sale of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Lincoln</ENAMEX> to an outside buyer, which Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Keating</ENAMEX> sought, rather than putting it in receivership.
A spokesman for Sen. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Cranston</ENAMEX> said that telephone-company records for three months disclosed no phone calls to the state regulators from his office. An aide to Sen. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Deconcini</ENAMEX> said the phone call to a top <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">California</ENAMEX> thrift regulator was ``informational.
