The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">University of Toronto</ENAMEX> said it will drop its objections to the offer by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Institut Merieux S.A.</ENAMEX> to acquire <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Connaught Biosciences Inc.</ENAMEX> for 942 million Canadian dollars (US$803.7 million) after reaching a research agreement with the French vaccine manufacturer.
Under the terms of the accord, similar to an agreement reached last week between the university and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merieux</ENAMEX>'s rival bidders for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Connaught</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ciba-Geigy Ltd.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chiron Corp.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merieux</ENAMEX> agreed to spend 15 million Canadian dollars (US$12.8 million) to fund vaccine-related research in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Canada</ENAMEX>, C$9/NNP million of which would go to the university's research programs.
The university had sued <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Connaught</ENAMEX>, arguing its directors had broken a 1972 agreement not to sell the company to a foreign concern by recommending <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merieux</ENAMEX>'s offer to shareholders. A decision in the case, heard last week by the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ontario Supreme Court</ENAMEX>, is expected this week. A decision in the university's favor could block <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Connaught</ENAMEX>'s directors from recommending <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merieux</ENAMEX>'s offer to shareholders, but couldn't block the company's sale.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">James Keffer</ENAMEX>, vice president, research, at the university, said the university isn't favoring one bid over another.
``Both of these agreements are good, both add substantial benefits to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Canada</ENAMEX>,'' he said. ``<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ciba-Geigy {and Chiron</ENAMEX>} are offering slightly more investment dollars to Canadian universities and some new products, but <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merieux</ENAMEX> is proposing to build a new biotechnology center.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ciba-Geigy</ENAMEX>, a Swiss pharmaceutical company, and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">California</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chiron</ENAMEX>, a pharmaceutical research concern, are offering C$866 million, or C$30 a share, for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Connaught</ENAMEX>.
The Canadian government said earlier this month that the proposed <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merieux</ENAMEX> acquisition didn't appear to offer enough ``net benefit'' to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Canada</ENAMEX> to approve.
``Reaching an agreement is an advantage to both the university and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merieux</ENAMEX>, both in terms of business and politically, since the university has been quite vocal about the issue of foreign ownership,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Philippe Stoeckel</ENAMEX>, president of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merieux Institute Inc.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merieux</ENAMEX>'s U.S. subsidiary.
