<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Philip Morris Cos.</ENAMEX> posted a 20% jump in third-quarter profit on a 45% revenue increase, reflecting strength in the company's cigarette, food and brewing businesses.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Philip Morris</ENAMEX> disclosed little detailed information about performance by major business lines except to say that most, including <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Philip Morris U.S.A.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Kraft General Foods</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Miller Brewing Co.</ENAMEX>, posted increased revenues.
For the nine months, net increased 4.4% to $2.08 billion, or $2.25 a share, from $2 billion, which included $273 million reflecting the effect of an accounting change.
