<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">General Motors Corp.</ENAMEX> wants to buy as much as 15% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar PLC</ENAMEX>, marking its first salvo in a possible full-scale battle against <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford Motor Co.</ENAMEX> for control of the British car maker.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX> sought U.S. antitrust clearance last week to purchase more than $15 million worth of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> shares but doesn't own any yet, according to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX> officials here and at the company's <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Detroit</ENAMEX> headquarters. The No. 1 U.S. auto maker then wrote <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> that it intends ``to go to that 15%'' level once it wins the U.S. clearance to go beyond $15 million, a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> spokesman said yesterday.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX> move follows Tuesday's declaration by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX>, which holds an unwelcome 12.45% stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX>, that it is prepared to bid for the entire company. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX> is close to completing a friendly deal with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> that is likely to involve an eventual 30% stake and joint manufacturing ventures. Speculative investors, betting on an imminent clash between <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX>, pushed up <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX>'s share price five pence (eight U.S. cents) to a near-record 720 pence ($11.60) in late trading on <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX>'s stock exchange yesterday. Since Tuesday, the shares have gained nearly 4%.
But an all-out bidding war between the world's top auto giants for <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX>'s leading luxury-car maker seems unlikely. ``We will not go over a certain level,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">David N. Mccammon</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX>'s vice president for finance, at a news conference yesterday in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dearborn</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mich.</ENAMEX> ``There's some price at which we'd stop bidding.'' He wouldn't specify what it was.
And powerful political pressures may convince the Conservative government to keep its so-called golden share, which limits any individual holding to 15%, until the restriction expires on Dec. 31, 1990.
``I really don't see the government doing something that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> doesn't want over the next 14 months,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kenneth Warren</ENAMEX>, a Conservative member of Parliament and chairman of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Select Committee on Trade and Industry</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">House of Commons</ENAMEX>. ``The golden share is a single share, but it is the magic share.''
The government retained the single share after selling its stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> in 1984 -- part of a nationalistic practice of protecting former government-owned enterprises to deflect criticism of privatization. The 15% restriction covers any would-be suitor, British or foreign.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> is willing to bid for 100% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX>'s shares if both the government and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> shareholders agree to relax the anti-takeover barrier prematurely. As <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX>'s biggest holder and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX>'s biggest car maker, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> could turn up the heat by convening a special shareholders' meeting and urging holders to drop the limits early. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> might succeed because many shareholders are speculators keen for a full bid or institutional investors unhappy over <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> management's handling of its current financial difficulties.
The government probably wouldn't give in readily to a hostile foray by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX>, however. It has relinquished a golden share only once before -- during <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Petroleum Co.</ENAMEX>'s # 2.5 billion ($4 billion) takeover of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Britoil PLC</ENAMEX> in 1988.
In wooing British lawmakers, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX> has pointed out that its willingness to settle for a minority stake would keep <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> British-owned and independent. This week, the U.S. auto giant paid for 10 <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">House of Commons</ENAMEX> members and two <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">House of Lords</ENAMEX> members to fly to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Detroit</ENAMEX> and tour its operations there. While the visit was unrelated to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX> Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Roger Smith</ENAMEX> answered the legislators' questions about it over lunch Tuesday. He said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> ``shouldn't be smothered by anyone else,'' recalled one participant.
Prime Minister <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Margaret Thatcher</ENAMEX> might, however, be receptive to any request by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> Chairman Sir <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John Egan</ENAMEX> for the restriction's early removal to let <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX> amass more than 15% or mount a friendly suitor bid against <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX>. In the end, Sir <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John</ENAMEX> -- rather than the government or <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> shareholders -- may hold the key that unlocks the golden share.
