Just when it looked like the Nasdaq over-the-counter market might be firming, nervous investors dumped shares of the biggest nonfinancial issues and sent the market tumbling.
Because of the heavy selling of such large stocks as <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Intel</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Oracle Systems</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Apple Computer</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Microsoft</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lotus Development</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nasdaq</ENAMEX> Composite Index slumped 4.74, or 1%, to 458.15. Those stocks and other industrial issues are part of the Nasdaq 100 Index, which plunged 8.12, or 1.8%, to
Every Nasdaq industry index was lower. The Utility Index, which includes <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tele-Communications</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MCI Communications</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">LIN Broadcasting</ENAMEX>, plummeted 9.55 to 734.41. All three of those stocks declined. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Industrial</ENAMEX> stocks fell 5.80 to 444.19 and transportation issues slid 4.03 to 478.28.
The Other <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Finance Index</ENAMEX> -- the barometer of regional banking, real-estate-investment and brokerage issues, dropped 2.58 to 536.94. The index of small commercial banks was down 2.54 to 440.99 and the index of insurance stocks eased 0.84 to 536.04. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nasdaq Financial</ENAMEX> Index of the 100 largest stocks in the group lost 2.11 to 452.75.
``The market felt sloppy. I didn't see any buying at all,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">William Sulya</ENAMEX>, head OTC trader at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">A.G. Edwards & Sons</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">St. Louis</ENAMEX>.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Sulya</ENAMEX> also noted that volume was tepid, totaling only 128.7 million shares. ``We were down and it was quiet on top of it. Those are two nails in a trader's coffin,'' he commented.
Some traders complained that OTC market makers are becoming more risk-averse because of the recent volatility. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Tony Cecin</ENAMEX>, managing director of equity trading at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Piper, Jaffray & Hopwood</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Minneapolis</ENAMEX>, said the overall OTC market is drifting lower in part because ``nobody has the nerve to make a bid for anything,'' he said. Mostly in response to news from bellwether <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Compaq Computer</ENAMEX>, the OTC market's technology stocks were battered all day. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Compaq</ENAMEX>'s quarterly earnings were at the low end of analysts' forecasts, and the company said it is experiencing problems with a new microchip from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Intel</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Intel</ENAMEX> confirmed the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Compaq</ENAMEX> report, but said the problems aren't expected to affect most users, except in ``certain scientific applications.'' <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Intel</ENAMEX> said it has more than 200 customers using the chip.
Nevertheless, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Intel</ENAMEX> dropped 7/8 to 32 on 3.6 million shares. Other computer stocks caught in the fallout included <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Apple</ENAMEX>, which fell 1 1/4 to 45 1/4. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Oracle Systems</ENAMEX> dropped 1 to 24 5/8. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Microsoft</ENAMEX> tumbled 2 to 77 3/4 and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lotus Development</ENAMEX> was off 1 5/8 to 30 5/8.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sun Microsystems</ENAMEX> eased 5/8 to 17 1/8, despite better-than-expected fiscal first-quarter earnings. Yesterday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sun</ENAMEX> reported net income of seven cents a share, compared with 26 cents a share a year earlier. But the report was better than the flat earnings the company had projected this summer, after reporting a loss for its fiscal fourth quarter. Also, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sun</ENAMEX>'s sales in its first quarter, ended Sept. 29, were up 39% from the year-earlier period.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MCI</ENAMEX> lost 1/4 to 42 3/4. In response to a similar lawsuit by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MCI</ENAMEX> filed earlier, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Telephone & Telegraph</ENAMEX> sued its competitor for misleading advertising.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> fell 5/8 to 11. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">General Motors</ENAMEX> said it is seeking clearance to buy as much as 15% of the company. On Wednesday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford Motor</ENAMEX> said it had already bought 12.45% of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British company</ENAMEX>'s shares and may bid for the rest. Yesterday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> said it won't enter an unlimited bidding war with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX> for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX>'s shares.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Buffets</ENAMEX> slid 1 to 14 after reporting third-quarter earnings of 17 cents a share, one cent below the low end of analysts' estimates. The company earned 14 cents a share in the year-earlier period.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chartwell Group</ENAMEX> plunged 1 1/2 to 1 1/2 after estimating that it had a loss of about $3.2 million in the latest third quarter, before a $5,350,000 addition to loss reserves. The company also said it wouldn't make the semiannual interest payment on its $40 million of 7% convertible subordinated debentures by the Nov. 1 due date or within the grace period. It blamed softness in the interior-furnishings industry for its financial troubles.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Astec Industries</ENAMEX> tumbled 2 1/8 to 9 7/8 after it reported a $2.4 million loss in the latest third quarter, compared with net income of more than $1 million a year earlier. The paving-equipment maker said the loss was caused by bad weather, which had hurt sales in its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Barber-Greene Co.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telsmith Inc.</ENAMEX> units.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Foremost Corp.</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">America</ENAMEX> surged 2 1/8 to 36 1/2. The company's third-quarter net income rose to eight cents a share from five cents a share the year before. The mobile-home insurer said Hurricane Hugo cost it 80 cents a share in the latest quarter.
