<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Sheldon B. Lubar</ENAMEX>, chairman of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lubar & Co.</ENAMEX>, and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John L. Murray</ENAMEX>, chairman of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Universal Foods Corp.</ENAMEX>, were elected to the board of this engine maker. They succeed <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Robert W. Kasten</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John R. Parker</ENAMEX>, who reached the mandatory retirement age.
