<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">LTV Steel Co.</ENAMEX> is boosting the prices of flat rolled steel products by an average of 3% following a recent erosion in the prices of such crucial steel products.
The big questions are whether the increase, effective Jan. 1, 1990, will stick, and whether other major steelmakers will follow suit. It is widely expected that they will. The increase is on the base price, which is already being discounted by virtually all steel producers.
But <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">LTV</ENAMEX>'s move marks the first effort by a major steelmaker to counter the free fall in spot prices. Major steel producers are selling cold rolled sheet steel at about $370 a ton, compared with a peak price of $520 a ton in 1988. Second-tier companies are receiving even less per ton. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">LTV</ENAMEX>'s planned increase, which was announced in an Oct. 26 memo to district managers, doesn't affect electrogalvanized steel or tin plate.
But analysts say the company is also trying to prevent further price drops. Moreover, they note that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">LTV</ENAMEX> may be trying to send a signal to major customers, such as <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chrysler Corp.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Whirlpool Corp.</ENAMEX>, that steelmakers need more money. Both companies are in the process of negotiating contracts with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">LTV</ENAMEX> and others.
``They {<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">LTV</ENAMEX>} may believe this can impact contract negotiations and is their signal to the world that now is the time to get tough on prices,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peter Marcus</ENAMEX>, an analyst with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Painewebber Inc.</ENAMEX> Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Marcus</ENAMEX> believes spot steel prices will continue to fall through early 1990 and then reverse themselves. He isn't convinced, though, that the price decline reflects falling demand because the world economy remains relatively strong. And while customers such as steel service centers are continuing to reduce inventories through the fourth quarter, they eventually will begin stocking up again, he notes.
It won't be clear for months whether the price increase will stick. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Steelmakers</ENAMEX> announced a round of base-price increases last year, but began offering sizable discounts over the summer. In fact, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">LTV</ENAMEX> was the first steelmaker to publicly boost discounts for buyers of cold rolled sheet steel and hot-dipped galvanized sheet steel.
