<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Poughkeepsie Savings Bank</ENAMEX> said a plan to sell its <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">South Carolina</ENAMEX> branch offices to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Citizens Bank</ENAMEX>, of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Columbia</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">S.C.</ENAMEX>, fell through.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Poughkeepsie</ENAMEX> also expects to post a one-time charge of $8.3 million, resulting in a net loss for the third quarter. The charge represents a write-down of the goodwill associated with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Poughkeepsie</ENAMEX>'s investment in the banks it is trying to sell and its <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">North Carolina</ENAMEX> branches as well.
The thrift announced the plan Aug. 21. Among other reasons, high fees regulators imposed on certain transfers of thrift deposits to commercial banks ``substantially altered the economics of the transaction for both parties,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Poughkeepsie</ENAMEX> said.
Additionally, the bank is increasing its loan-loss reserves for the third quarter by $8.5 million before taxes.
