<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Vitro S.A.</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Monterrey</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mexico</ENAMEX>, said its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">THR Corp.</ENAMEX> subsidiary has entered into definitive loan agreements in connection with <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Vitro</ENAMEX>'s $21.25-a-share tender offer for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Anchor Glass Container Corp.</ENAMEX>
The agreements are with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Security Pacific National Bank</ENAMEX> and an affiliate of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Donaldson, Lufkin & Jenrette Securities Corp.</ENAMEX> Proceeds of the loan agreement, together with funds from <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Vitro</ENAMEX>, will permit the purchase of all shares outstanding of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Anchor</ENAMEX> and the payment of all related costs and expenses.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Vitro</ENAMEX> said the definitive agreements require that Anchor obtain a waiver from its bank lenders of existing covenant defaults under its bank facilities. Since <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Anchor</ENAMEX> is still seeking this waiver, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Vitro</ENAMEX> said the tender offer is being extended until 5 p.m. EST tomorrow.
