<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">B.A.T Industries PLC</ENAMEX> may delay aspects of its defensive restructuring plan -- including the sale of its <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Saks Fifth Avenue</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Marshall Field</ENAMEX> units -- in the wake of the current upheaval in financial markets, company officials said.
The British conglomerate, planning its own defensive restructuring to fight off a # 13.35 billion ($21.03 billion) takeover bid by Anglo-French financier Sir <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">James Goldsmith</ENAMEX>, intends to press ahead with an extraordinary shareholder vote today to clear the way for its value-boosting measures. If anything, the gyrations in world stock markets -- and in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">B.A.T</ENAMEX>'s share price -- since last Friday's sharp Wall Street sell-off have increased the likelihood of shareholder approval for the restructuring, analysts and several big institutional holders said. ``Thank God we have some deal on the table,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stewart Gilchrist</ENAMEX>, a director at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Scottish Amicable Investment Managers</ENAMEX>, which intends to vote its roughly 1% stake in favor of the restructuring.
Investors in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">B.A.T</ENAMEX> have been on a roller coaster. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">B.A.T</ENAMEX> has been <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX>'s best-performing blue chip over the past six months, up 40% against a 4% rise in the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Financial Times</ENAMEX> 100-Share Index. But this week, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">B.A.T</ENAMEX> has been hit harder than other big <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.K.</ENAMEX> stocks -- first by the market gyrations, then by Tuesday's <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">San Francisco</ENAMEX> earthquake, which could leave <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">B.A.T</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Farmers Group Inc.</ENAMEX> insurance unit facing big claims. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">B.A.T</ENAMEX> rose five pence (eight cents) to 756 pence ($11.91) in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX> yesterday as a late market rally erased a 28-pence fall earlier in the day.
To fight off predators, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">B.A.T</ENAMEX> plans to spin off about $6 billion in assets, largely by selling such U.S. retailing units as <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Marshall Field</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Saks</ENAMEX> and by floating its big paper and U.K. retailing business via share issues to existing holders. Proceeds will help pay for a planned buy-back of 10% of its shares and a 50% dividend increase.
``I think the restructuring will get the required support,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Michael Pacitti</ENAMEX>, an analyst at <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX> stockbroker <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UBS Phillips & Drew</ENAMEX>. ``The shareholders effectively will support the share price by clearing the share buy-back.''
But <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">B.A.T</ENAMEX>'s restructuring, which was never going to happen quickly, now will take longer because of the market upheaval. Company officials, holders and analysts who previously expected the disposals to be substantially complete by the end of next year's first half now say the market gyrations could delay the actions well into the second half. ``We aren't forced sellers. We don't have an absolute deadline and if market conditions are truly awful we might decide it is not the right time,'' to take particular steps, said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Michael Prideaux</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">B.A.T</ENAMEX> spokesman.
Even if <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">B.A.T</ENAMEX> receives approval for the restructuring, the company will remain in play, say shareholders and analysts, though the situation may unfold over the next 12 months, rather than six. The new <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">B.A.T</ENAMEX> will be a smaller tobacco and financial-services hybrid whose price-earnings ratio may more closely reflect the lower-growth tobacco business than the higher-multiple financial-services business, these holders believe. Thus <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">B.A.T</ENAMEX>'s restructuring may only make the company a more manageable target for other corporate predators -- possibly such acquisitive bidders as <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hanson PLC</ENAMEX>.
``The last few days will surely slow down the pace of events,'' says Scottish Amicable's Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gilchrist</ENAMEX>. ``But I wouldn't write off'' Sir <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">James</ENAMEX> or other potential bidders.
Among possible delays, the sales of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Saks</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Marshall Field</ENAMEX> -- which were expected to be on the block soon after the crucial Christmas season -- may slide into the second quarter or second half. Analysts estimate that sales of the two businesses could raise roughly $2 billion.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">B.A.T</ENAMEX> isn't predicting a postponement because the units ``are quality businesses and we are encouraged by the breadth of inquiries,'' said Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Prideaux</ENAMEX>. But the delay could happen if <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">B.A.T</ENAMEX> doesn't get adequate bids, he said.
People familiar with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">B.A.T</ENAMEX> say possible acquirers for the units include managers from both retailing chains, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">General Cinema Corp.</ENAMEX>, which is interested in bidding for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Saks</ENAMEX>. Other potential bidders for parts of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">B.A.T</ENAMEX>'s U.S. retail unit include <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dillard Department Stores Inc.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">May Department Stores Co.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Limited Inc.</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">B.A.T</ENAMEX> has declined to identify the potential bidders.
Though Sir <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">James</ENAMEX> has said he intends to mount a new bid for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">B.A.T</ENAMEX> once approval from U.S. insurance regulators is received, jitters over prospects for junk-bond financing and U.S. leverage buy-outs are making investors more skeptical about Sir <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">James</ENAMEX>'s prospects. His initial offer indicated he needed to raise as much as 80% of the takeover financing through the debt markets.
Market uncertainty also clouds the outlook for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">B.A.T</ENAMEX>'s attracting a premium price for its <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> retailing properties. Finally, Tuesday's <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">California</ENAMEX> earthquake initially knocked 3.7% off <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">B.A.T</ENAMEX>'s share price in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX> yesterday because of fears of the potential claims to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Los Angeles</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Farmers</ENAMEX>, which has a substantial portion of its property and casualty exposure in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">California</ENAMEX>.
On Farmers, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Prideaux</ENAMEX> said it is too early to quantify the level of potential claims. He added <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">B.A.T</ENAMEX> ``has no expectation of a material impact on Farmers.
