<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Reuters Holdings PLC</ENAMEX> said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Michael Reupke</ENAMEX> resigned as general manager to pursue unspecified interests, a move the news organization termed an ``amicable separation.''
In a telephone interview, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Reupke</ENAMEX> said his departure was for ``personal reasons,'' which he declined to specify. ``There is no business reason for my departure,'' nor any disagreement over policy, he added. He also rejected reports that his departure stemmed from disappointment the general manager's post hadn't also led to a board directorship at the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX>-based news organization.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Reupke</ENAMEX> was one of three executives on <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Reuters</ENAMEX>'s eight-person executive committee who didn't also serve on the company's board of directors. ``If I were choosing the people of tomorrow, I would have chosen the people who are now on the board,'' he said.
The senior of the three executives who will assume Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Reupke</ENAMEX>'s duties is <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Nigel Judah</ENAMEX>, 58, finance director and a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Reuters</ENAMEX> board director. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peter Holland</ENAMEX>, 45, deputy general manager, becomes director of corporate affairs. And <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Patrick Mannix</ENAMEX>, 46, international technical manager, becomes director of group quality programs.
