<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Colgate Palmolive Co.</ENAMEX> reported third-quarter net income rose 27%, bolstered by strong sales in its Latin American business and surprisingly healthy profits from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> operations.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Colgate</ENAMEX> said net income for the quarter rose to $76.7 million, or $1.06 a share, on sales that increased 6% to $1.3 billion. In the year-earlier period, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Colgate</ENAMEX> posted net income of $60.2 million, or 88 cents a share. Last year's results included earnings from discontinued operations of $13.1 million, or 19 cents a share.
``We've done a lot to improve (<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX>) results and a lot more will be done,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mark</ENAMEX> said. ``Improving profitability of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> operations is an extremely high priority in the company.''
For the nine months, net increased 14% to $217.5 million, or $3.09 a share. Sales rose 7% to $3.8 billion. The company earned $191.1 million, or $2.79 a share, in the year-earlier period. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Colgate</ENAMEX>'s 1988 net income included $40.1 million, or 59 cents a share, from discontinued operations. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Colgate</ENAMEX> sold its hospital supply and home health care business last year.
Separately, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Colgate</ENAMEX> Wednesday finalized an agreement with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Macrochem Corp.</ENAMEX>, a tiny dental products and pharmaceutical concern based in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Billerica</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mass.</ENAMEX>, to market in the U.S. four of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Macrochem</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FDA</ENAMEX>-approved dental products. The products -- sealants and bonding materials used by dentists -- all contain fluoride that is released over time. The move is part of a drive to increase <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Colgate</ENAMEX>'s business with dentists, a company spokeswoman said. Terms of the agreement weren't given.
