<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Helmsley Enterprises Inc.</ENAMEX> plans to close its company-owned insurance business and is seeking other brokers to take over its policies, according to individuals familiar with the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> firm.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Helmsley Enterprises</ENAMEX> is the umbrella organization for companies controlled by <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Harry B. Helmsley</ENAMEX>. These include office and residential real estate giant, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Helmsleyspear Inc.</ENAMEX>, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Helmsley Hotels.</ENAMEX> The insurance brokerage agency, just a fragment of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Helmsley</ENAMEX>'s vast empire, would be the first piece of the company to be stripped away since last summer when Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Helmsley</ENAMEX>'s wife, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Leona Helmsley</ENAMEX>, was found guilty of tax evasion.
Adverse publicity from the scandal surrounding its founder's wife and related management strife have put pressure on the entire Helmsley organization. However, individuals close to the company insist shuttering the insurance division, a sideline from the company's core property management business, isn't the beginning of a sale of assets.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Helmsley</ENAMEX>'s insurance premiums are expected to be transferred to several different insurance brokerage companies. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Frank B. Hall</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Inc.</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Briarcliff Manor</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.Y.</ENAMEX> is reportedly working out an agreement with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Helmsley</ENAMEX>. Officials there declined to comment, as did <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Helmsley</ENAMEX> management.
