<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Eastern Enterprises</ENAMEX>, bolstered by improved tonnages in its marine-shipping unit, had a narrower third-quarter net loss of $1.1 million, or five cents a share.
Last year, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Eastern</ENAMEX> had a quarter loss of $1.7 million, or eight cents a share.
Quarter revenue rose 44% to $160.1 million from $111.2 million a year ago.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Weston</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mass.</ENAMEX>, utilities and marine-transport concern said results for the third quarter, usually a money-losing one because of the seasonality of the gas business, were also aided by higher gas sales and the May 1989 acquisition of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Water Products Company.</ENAMEX>
For the nine months, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Eastern</ENAMEX> had net income of $41.8 million, or $1.80 a share, up 23% from $33.9 million or $1.46 a share a year ago. Revenue grew 24% to $614.5 million from $497.1 million.
