<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">San Francisco</ENAMEX> area officials gave the media high marks for helping people find shelter and obtain emergency information after Tuesday's catastrophic earthquake.
``The press has been doing an excellent job. They are telling people what roads are closed and just keeping the public informed has helped to keep the panic down,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">James Ball</ENAMEX>, a station supervisor at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Daly City Police Department</ENAMEX>.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ball</ENAMEX> noted that television stations featured people holding up phone books, explaining where to call for help. Radio stations provided an emergency number for people who smelled gas but didn't know how to turn off their gas supply.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kim Schwartz</ENAMEX>, a spokesperson for the American Red Cross in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Los Angeles</ENAMEX>, said television and radio stations in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">San Francisco</ENAMEX> played a ``very positive role'' by providing the address of 28 shelters of the Red Cross and by giving out the Red Cross number for contributions to help earthquake victims (1-800-453-9000).
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">San Francisco Examiner</ENAMEX> issued a special edition around noon yesterday that was filled entirely with earthquake news and information. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Examiner</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">San Francisco Chronicle</ENAMEX> were able to publish despite Tuesday's quake, which occurred close to deadline for many newspapers.
