<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Enviropact Inc.</ENAMEX> said it entered into an agreement in principle to sell its pump and tank division and drilling division to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GSX Chemical Services</ENAMEX> for $4 million.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Miami</ENAMEX>-based environmental engineering concern said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GSX Chemical</ENAMEX> also will assume about $1.6 million in debt related to those divisions.
Further, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GSX</ENAMEX> will buy $1 million of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Enviropact</ENAMEX> common stock, at $2.625 a share, plus an option to acquire an additional $1.5 million of common at the same price, the company said. In <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> composite trading yesterday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Enviropact</ENAMEX> closed at $3 a share, up 25 cents.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Enviropact</ENAMEX> said the proceeds will be used as working capital for expansion and to pay its existing tax liability of about $1.5 million that was due Sept. 15.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GSX</ENAMEX> is a unit of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Laidlaw Transportation Ltd.</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Burlington</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Canada</ENAMEX>.
