The collapse of a $6.79 billion labor-management buy-out of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Airlines</ENAMEX> parent <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL Corp.</ENAMEX> may not stop some of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Wall Street</ENAMEX>'s top talent from collecting up to $53.7 million in fees.
According to one person familiar with the airline, the buy-out group -- led by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United's</ENAMEX> pilots union and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stephen Wolf</ENAMEX> -- has begun billing <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> for fees and expenses it owes to investment bankers, law firms and banks.
The tab even covers $8 million in commitment fees owed to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Citicorp</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chase Manhattan Corp.</ENAMEX>, even though their failure to obtain $7.2 billion in bank loans for the buy-out was the main reason for its collapse.
Under a merger agreement reached Sept. 14, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> board agreed to reimburse certain of the buy-out group's expenses out of company funds even if the transaction wasn't completed, provided the group didn't breach the agreement. The failure to obtain financing doesn't by itself constitute a breach.
The merger agreement says the buy-out group is entitled to be repaid $26.7 million in fees for its investment bankers, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lazard Freres & Co.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Salomon Brothers Inc.</ENAMEX>, and its law firm, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Paul Weiss Rifkind Wharton</ENAMEX> & Garrison.
The buy-out group is also entitled to $16 million to repay a fund created by the pilots union for an employee stock ownership plan. In addition to the $8 million for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Citicorp</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Chase</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Salomon Brothers</ENAMEX> is also owed $3 million for promising to make a $200 million bridge loan.
A spokesman for the buy-out group wasn't immediately available for comment.
Separately, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> stock rose $4 a share to $175 in composite trading on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> on reports that <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Los Angeles</ENAMEX> investor <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Marvin Davis</ENAMEX> has asked <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Airlines</ENAMEX> unions if they're interested in cooperating with Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Davis</ENAMEX> in a new bid for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX>.
But neither the pilots nor the machinists appear interested, and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Davis</ENAMEX> is barred from making a new bid under terms of an agreement he made with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> in September unless <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> accepts an offer below $300 a share.
