<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mcdonald's Corp.</ENAMEX>, under pressure by environmental groups to stop using polystyrene containers, announced a program here to foster recycling of the plastics at 450 of its <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New England</ENAMEX> restaurants.
Environmentalists, however, attacked <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mcdonald</ENAMEX>'s program as a public relations ploy and the wrong way to address the nation's garbage crisis.
Under the program, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mcdonald</ENAMEX>'s restaurants will be equipped with recycling bins for plastic items and with posters encouraging customers to use them, the company said. The plastic will be sent to a plant in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Leominster</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mass.</ENAMEX>, near <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Boston</ENAMEX>, which is owned by a joint venture recently formed by plastics makers. It then will be processed into plastic pellets for use in making products such as trash cans, flower pots and food trays, but not food containers, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mcdonald's</ENAMEX> said.
The program will reduce trash, help educate youngsters about recycling and ``is a big step toward a better environment,'' asserted <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Shelby Yastrow</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mcdonald</ENAMEX>'s senior vice president, environmental affairs.
However, it will be a small step for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mcdonald</ENAMEX>'s as a whole. The program will include 4% of the company's 11,000 restaurants. And because many customers won't participate, such as people who drive through, it is likely that less than 2% of the company's plastic containers will be recycled under the program. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mcdonald's</ENAMEX> said it plans to expand the program when and if more plastic recycling plants are built near its restaurants.
The plant in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Leominster</ENAMEX> is the first of five planned by the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">National Polystyrene Recycling Co.</ENAMEX>, the plastics-industry joint venture. It was formed earlier this year by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Chemical Co.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mobil Corp.</ENAMEX> and six other concerns in response to concerns about growing amounts of non-biodegradable plastic trash. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Paul Keough</ENAMEX>, acting regional director for the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Environmental Protection Agency</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Boston</ENAMEX>, said, ``We hope that other large companies follow <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mcdonald</ENAMEX>'s lead to undertake similar programs.'' But <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Amy Perry</ENAMEX>, a spokeswoman for the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Massachusetts Public Interest Research Group</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Boston</ENAMEX> offshoot of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ralph Nader</ENAMEX>'s lobbying outfits, argued that the program ``just serves to legitimize increasing the use of throwaway plastics. It would be far better for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mcdonald</ENAMEX>'s to use durable goods {that could be reused for serving food}, instead of promoting the throwaway society.''
Last year, a network of environmental groups commenced a ``<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mctoxics Campaign</ENAMEX>'' to pressure <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mcdonald</ENAMEX>'s to stop using polystyrene. Among other things, the groups have urged consumers to mail used <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mcdonald</ENAMEX>'s plastic containers to its Oak <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Brook</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ill.</ENAMEX>, headquarters.
Concerns about plastic trash also have sparked legislative initiatives, such as one in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Berkeley</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Calif.</ENAMEX>, to ban polystyrene products as of January. Such laws are causing major headaches for companies like <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mcdonald's</ENAMEX>, which increasingly must wrestle with different local rules across the nation.
``Political pressure has been a factor'' in the introduction of recycling programs by plastics makers and sellers, conceded <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ken Harman</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">National Polystyrene</ENAMEX>'s acting president and chairman, at the news conference, which was held in a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mcdonald</ENAMEX>'s restaurant next to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Boston</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Children's Museum</ENAMEX>.
Some of the pressure became evident during the news conference when a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mcdonald</ENAMEX>'s customer startled company officials by blurting out, ``Why do you produce so much trash in the first place?'' The customer, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jeff Simpson</ENAMEX>, a visitor from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX>, later explained that he was vexed by all the plastic, paper and cardboard that came with the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mcdonald</ENAMEX>'s breakfast he had just eaten. The recycling program ``is laudable,'' he said, ``but why not use china plates?
