<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Monopolies and Mergers Commission</ENAMEX> said the proposed # 395 million ($637.7 million) acquisition of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tootal Group PLC</ENAMEX> by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coats Viyella PLC</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.K.</ENAMEX> textile manufacturer, could go ahead pending certain conditions.
The commission said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Coats</ENAMEX> must first dispose of its interest in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX>'s domestic sewing thread industry and its shares in the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Gutermann Group</ENAMEX>.
The panel was concerned that the merger of the two groups would damage competition in British markets for industrial and domestic sewing thread and clothing.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Coats</ENAMEX> has offered one ordinary Coats share and 400 pence in cash for every four shares in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tootal</ENAMEX>, which is the equivalent of 138.4 pence per share.
