Two exchanges' new stock ``basket'' products got off to a slow start yesterday.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange's Exchange Stock Portfolio</ENAMEX>, which allows investors to trade all 500 stocks in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Standard & Poor</ENAMEX>'s index in a single transaction, received permanent regulatory approval Wednesday. However, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Securities and Exchange Commission</ENAMEX> will review three rules regarding <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX>'s basket trading over the next six months.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">SEC</ENAMEX> also approved the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chicago Board Options Exchange</ENAMEX>'s basket product. Both exchanges will compete for institutional business in the months ahead, and one probably will emerge as the dominant market for stock baskets.
Only nine ESP contracts traded on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX> -- equivalent to about one million shares of stock, with a value of about $45 million. ``It was a slow start, but we expected it would be,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX> President <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Richard Grasso</ENAMEX>. ``We were generally pleased with the way the systems acted.''
At the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CBOE</ENAMEX>, 14 baskets traded -- the equivalent of about 500,000 shares with a value of about $24 million. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CBOE</ENAMEX>'s basket requires a minimum of $1.7 million a trade, compared with a $5 million minimum for the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX> basket.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">David Hall</ENAMEX>, vice president at the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">CBOE</ENAMEX>, said five to six firms traded the stock basket product, located on the floor of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CBOE</ENAMEX> near the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">S*/NNP&P</ENAMEX> 500-stock index options pit.
