<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">H. Marshall Schwarz</ENAMEX> was named chairman and chief executive officer of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.S. Trust Corp.</ENAMEX>, a private-banking firm with assets under management of about $17 billion.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Schwarz</ENAMEX>, 52 years old, will succeed <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Daniel P. Davison</ENAMEX> Feb. 1, soon after Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Davison</ENAMEX> reaches the company's mandatory retirement age of 65. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Schwarz</ENAMEX>, who is president of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.S. Trust</ENAMEX>, will be succeeded in that post by <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jeffrey S. Maurer</ENAMEX>, 42, who is executive vice president in charge of the company's asset-management group.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.S. Trust</ENAMEX>, a 136-year-old institution that is one of the earliest high-net worth banks in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX>, has faced intensifying competition from other firms that have established, and heavily promoted, private-banking businesses of their own. As a result, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.S. Trust</ENAMEX>'s earnings have been hurt.
But Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Schwarz</ENAMEX> welcomes the competition in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.S. Trust</ENAMEX>'s flagship businesses, calling it ``flattery.'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Schwarz</ENAMEX> says the competition ``broadens the base of opportunity for us.'' Other firms ``are dealing with the masses. I don't believe they have the culture'' to adequately service high-net-worth individuals, he adds. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.S. Trust</ENAMEX> recently introduced certain mutual-fund products, which allow it to serve customers with minimum deposits of $250,000. Previously, the company advertised at the $2 million level.
``We have always taken smaller accounts, but now we are looking for smaller accounts that will grow,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Schwarz</ENAMEX> says. ``Our bread and butter is still the $2 million to $20 million account,'' he says. The new services allow <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.S. Trust</ENAMEX> to cater to the ``new wealth,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Schwarz</ENAMEX> says.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Schwarz</ENAMEX>'s great-grandfather founded the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> toy store <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">F.A.O. Schwarz</ENAMEX>, but his family no longer has ties to the company. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Schwarz</ENAMEX>'s father was a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.S. Trust</ENAMEX> trustee until 1974.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.S. Trust</ENAMEX> also created a four-member office of the chairman, effective Feb. 1. It will include Messrs. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Schwarz</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Maurer</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Donald M. Roberts</ENAMEX>, 54, treasurer, and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Frederick S. Wonham</ENAMEX>, 58, who takes responsibility for the funds-service group, were named vice chairmen and will serve in the office of the chairman. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Roberts</ENAMEX> continues as treasurer, and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Wonham</ENAMEX> remains responsible for the offices of comptroller, planning, marketing and general services.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Frederick B. Taylor</ENAMEX>, 48, also was named a vice chairman and chief investment officer, a new post. He previously held similar responsibilities. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Taylor</ENAMEX> also was named a director, increasing the board to 22, but is not part of the new office of the chairman.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">James E. Bacon</ENAMEX>, 58, executive vice president, who has directed the funds-service group, will retire.
