This <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Brooklyn</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.Y.</ENAMEX>, generic-drug maker announced a 5% stock dividend payable Dec. 15, to holders of record Nov. 15. As of Sept. 30, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Halsey</ENAMEX> had 5.3 million common shares outstanding. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jay Marcus</ENAMEX>, president, said the move ``reflects the confidence of our board and management in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Halsey</ENAMEX>'s long-term prospects and our desire to provide our shareholders with an attractive return on their investment.'' In <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> composite trading, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Halsey</ENAMEX> closed at $5.8125 a share, up 6.25 cents.
