In a stunning shift in direction, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Provigo Inc.</ENAMEX> said it will sell all its non-food operations to concentrate solely on its retail and wholesale grocery business. The non-food operations accounted for about 27% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Provigo</ENAMEX>'s 7.38 billion Canadian dollars (US$6.3 billion) in sales in the latest fiscal year.
In a related move, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Pierre Lortie</ENAMEX>, chairman and chief executive, resigned. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lortie</ENAMEX> joined <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Provigo</ENAMEX> in 1985 and spearheaded the company's drive to grow outside its traditional food business. He couldn't be reached for comment.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bertin Nadeau</ENAMEX>, newly appointed chairman and interim chief executive of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Provigo</ENAMEX>, wouldn't say if Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lortie</ENAMEX> was asked to leave. ``Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lortie</ENAMEX> felt less pertinent,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Nadeau</ENAMEX> said, given the decision to dump <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Provigo</ENAMEX>'s non-food operations. ``At this stage it was felt I was perhaps more pertinent as chief executive.'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Nadeau</ENAMEX> also is chairman and chief executive of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Unigesco Inc.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Provigo</ENAMEX>'s controlling shareholder.
Investors and analysts applauded the news. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Provigo</ENAMEX> was the most active industrial stock on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Montreal Exchange</ENAMEX>, where it closed at C$9.75 (US$8.32), up 75 Canadian cents.
``I think it's a pretty positive development,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ross Cowan</ENAMEX>, a financial analyst with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Levesque Beaubien Geoffrion Inc.</ENAMEX>, of the decision to concentrate on groceries. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lortie</ENAMEX>'s departure, while sudden, was seen as inevitable in light of the shift in strategy. ``The non-food operations were largely Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lortie</ENAMEX>'s creation {and} his strategy didn't work,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steven Holt</ENAMEX>, a financial analyst with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Midland Doherty Ltd.</ENAMEX>
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Provigo</ENAMEX>'s profit record over the past two years tarnished the company's and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lortie</ENAMEX>'s reputations. For the six months ended Aug. 12, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Provigo</ENAMEX> posted net income of C$6.5 million, or eight Canadian cents a share, compared with C$18.1 million, or 21 Canadian cents a share, a year earlier. Sales were C$4.2 billion compared with C$3.7 billion. Last month, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Canadian Bond Rating Service</ENAMEX> downgraded <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Provigo</ENAMEX>'s commercial paper and debentures because of its lackluster performance.
Analysts are skeptical <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Provigo</ENAMEX> will be able to sell the non-food businesses as a group for at least book value, and are expecting write-downs. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Nadeau</ENAMEX> said he couldn't yet say if the sale prices would match book values. He said all three non-food operations are profitable.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Nadeau</ENAMEX> said discussions are under way with potential purchasers of each of the units. He declined to confirm or deny reports that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Provigo</ENAMEX> executive Henri <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Roy</ENAMEX> is trying to put together a management buy-out of the catalogue showroom unit. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Roy</ENAMEX> couldn't be reached.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Yvon Bussieres</ENAMEX> was named senior executive vice president and chief operating officer of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Provigo</ENAMEX>, a new position. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bussieres</ENAMEX> was president and chief operating officer of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Provigo</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Quebec</ENAMEX> retail and wholesale grocery unit. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Nadeau</ENAMEX> said he intends to remain <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Provigo</ENAMEX>'s chief executive only until the non-food businesses are sold, after a which a new chief executive will be named.
