<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tokyo</ENAMEX> stocks closed higher in moderately active but directionless trading as the recent anxiety in world stock markets continued to fade.
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX> shares also closed firmer in thin trading driven largely by technical factors and support from a new Wall Street rally. Prices also rose on almost every other major exchange in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Europe</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Asia</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Pacific</ENAMEX>.
The morning session was dominated by individuals and dealers, but some institutions participated in the afternoon, encouraged by the market's firmness, traders said. Sentiment was helped by the small gain made by <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> stocks Wednesday despite anxiety over possible effects of the major earthquake that struck <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">northern California</ENAMEX> Tuesday.
Having survived both last Friday's 6.9% Wall Street plunge and the immediate aftermath of the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">San Francisco Bay</ENAMEX> area earthquake, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tokyo</ENAMEX> market participants expressed relief that trading had returned to normal.
But traders said the market lacks a base on which to set long-term buying strategy, as the future direction of U.S. interest rates remains unclear.
``Investor interest switches back and forth ceaselessly as they are unable to shift their weight to one side for sure,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mitsuoka</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Daiwa Investment Trust</ENAMEX> said.
Many of Wednesday's winners were losers yesterday as investors quickly took profits and rotated their buying to other issues, traders said.
Leading construction companies also attracted interest for their strong earnings outlooks, traders said. They and many other major Japanese corporations will issue results soon for the fiscal first half ended Sept. 30. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ohbayashi</ENAMEX> was up 60 to close at 1,680, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Shimizu</ENAMEX> gained 50 to 2,120, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Kumagai-Gumi</ENAMEX> advanced 40 to 1,490.
Other winners included real estate issues <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mitsubishi Estate</ENAMEX>, which closed at 2,500, up 130, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mitsui Real Estate Development</ENAMEX>, which gained 100 to 2,890.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mitsubishi Rayon</ENAMEX>, a leading advancer Wednesday, fell 44 to 861 as investors grabbed profits.
Dealers said the market was underpinned by a squeeze in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FT</ENAMEX>-SE 100 stocks, particularly among market-makers seeking shares that had been hit hard in recent weeks, such as retailers and building-related concerns.
But despite the flurry of interest in those shares, dealers said, the market remains nervous about <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Wall Street</ENAMEX>'s volatility and high U.K. interest rates.
U.K. money supply figures for September, released yesterday, showed continued growth in corporate and personal lending, which will keep pressure on the government to maintain tight credit.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">General Universal Stores</ENAMEX>, another top-tier stock hit recently by concerns over retail demand in the face of high interest rates, gained 20 to # 10.44. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Storehouse</ENAMEX> gained 2 to
Insurers recovered ground again on market-maker demand and speculative buying linked to talk of mergers in the industry before the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">European Community</ENAMEX>'s planned market unification in
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">B.A.T Industries</ENAMEX> surged in afternoon dealings after its shareholders approved a plan to dispose of its <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.K.</ENAMEX> retailing operations to fend off <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hoylake Investment</ENAMEX>'s # 13.4 billion ($21.33 billion) hostile bid. With the company also exercising a plan to buy back as many as 10% of its shares outstanding, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">B.A.T</ENAMEX> closed at 783, up 27. Turnover was 6.8 million shares, including about four million shares traded in the afternoon after the shareholders' meeting. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">B.A.T</ENAMEX> said it purchased 2.5 million shares at 785.
In other European markets, shares closed sharply higher in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Stockholm</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Frankfurt</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Zurich</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Paris</ENAMEX> and higher in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Milan</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Amsterdam</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Brussels</ENAMEX>. South African gold stocks closed firmer.
Prices also closed higher in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Singapore</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Sydney</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Taipei</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Wellington</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hong Kong</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Manila</ENAMEX> but were lower in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Seoul</ENAMEX>.
