<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Enimont S.p. A.</ENAMEX> said net income totaled 525 billion lire ($390 million) for the first half of 1989.
The Italian chemicals company didn't provide year-earlier figures because it was formed on Jan. 1 as a joint venture between <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Montedison S.p. A.</ENAMEX> and state-owned <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Enichem S.p. A.</ENAMEX>
A joint statement issued by the two partners said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Enimont</ENAMEX> rang up revenue of 8.2 trillion lire ($6.09 billion), while gross operating profit amounted to 1.4 trillion lire in the opening half of the year.
The statement didn't address the issue of a possible change at the top management as Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lorenzo Necci</ENAMEX> is expected to be appointed chairman of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ente Nazionale Idrocarburi</ENAMEX>, succeeding <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Franco</ENAMEX> Reviglio whose term expires in November. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ENI</ENAMEX>, the state energy concern, is <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Enichem</ENAMEX>'s parent.
According to local news reports, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gabriele Cagliari</ENAMEX>, a member of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ENI</ENAMEX>'s executive council, is a front runner to take over Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Necci</ENAMEX>'s post at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Enimont</ENAMEX>.
