<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">N.V. Philips</ENAMEX> said third-quarter net profit surged 41% to 227 million guilders ($109.4 million), or 84 guilder cents a share, from 161 million guilders, or 63 cents, a year earlier.
Separately, the Dutch electronics group announced it will spin off about 20% of its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Polygram BV</ENAMEX> recording subsidiary in an international stock offering. It said it plans to file the share offer with the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.S. Securities and Exchange Commission</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Amsterdam Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> ``within the next few weeks.'' It didn't elaborate.
The big earnings improvement reflected extraordinary gains and the accounting impact of subsidiary disposals, as well as restructuring charges, mixed market factors, higher taxes and plunging financing costs and other spending reductions.
The 1989 third-quarter's jump in net profit was aided by a 277 million guilder, or 47.4%, drop in net financing charges.
Disappointments in the quarter included intense competition causing downward price pressure that led to unspecified operating losses in two key product lines, especially in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> As a result, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Philips</ENAMEX>'s pretax operating profit before financing items tumbled 15.7% from a year earlier to 592 million guilders.
Third-quarter sales world-wide were unchanged from a year ago at 13.57 billion guilders.
