<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Homefed Corp.</ENAMEX> said third-quarter net income slid 14% to $23.9 million, or $1.10 per fully diluted share, from $27.9 million, or $1.21 a fully diluted share, because of increased bad assets and unexpected trouble in unloading foreclosed property.
The decline surprised analysts and jolted <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Homefed</ENAMEX>'s stock, which lost 8.6% of its value, closing at $38.50 on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX>, down $3.625.
However, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Homefed</ENAMEX>'s loan originations and purchases plunged 26% in the quarter, to $1.4 billion from $1.9 billion a year earlier. Meanwhile, non-performing assets rose to $593 million from $518.7 million. Some $380 million of the troubled assets is repossessed real estate, a 55.6% surge from the $244.2 million of repossesed property Homefed held a year ago. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Homefed</ENAMEX> has $17.9 billion of assets.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Homefed</ENAMEX> said most of the troubled assets are apartment complexes, shopping malls and other commercial real estate. It said about half are in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">California</ENAMEX>, with the rest scattered across the country. It said sales of such properties were slower than anticipated in the third quarter, but it expects sales to pick up in the rest of the year.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Homefed</ENAMEX> said the slide in loan originations was more a matter of design than a sign of cooling in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">California</ENAMEX> market. Any such downturn in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">California</ENAMEX> would be grim news for <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">West Coast</ENAMEX> thrifts, particularly the less healthy ones, which have performed poorly even with a torrid market. But <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Homefed</ENAMEX> said it purposely curbed loan originations in the quarter because of uncertainty over the new capital requirements and regulations that will emerge from negotiations over implementing the government's massive thrift bailout bill. It said its real-estate operations earned a record $21.7 million, more than double year-earlier real estate profit of $9 million. And analysts said they see no signs of an imminent swoon in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">California</ENAMEX> real estate, even with last week's earthquake.
