<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford Motor Co.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Saab-Scania AB</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Sweden</ENAMEX> broke off talks about a possible alliance after <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> officials concluded that the cost to modernize <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Saab</ENAMEX>'s car operations would outweigh the likely return.
With the collapse of the talks Friday, European analysts expect <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> to intensify its pursuit of British luxury car maker <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar PLC</ENAMEX>, which is scrambling to fend off a hostile <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> bid by negotiating a friendly alliance with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX>'s archrival, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">General Motors Corp.</ENAMEX>
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Saab</ENAMEX>, meanwhile, is left to continue its search for an ally to shore up its sagging car business. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Saab</ENAMEX> said last week it ``has had and will continue to have contacts with other manufacturers.'' Among the possible suitors is <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Italy</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Fiat S.p. A</ENAMEX>, analysts said last week.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Saab</ENAMEX> officials declined to elaborate publicly on the announcement Friday that their negotiations failed to yield an agreement ``that could make long-term business sense to both parties.''
Individuals close to the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> side of the negotiations said late last week that the No. 2 U.S. auto maker lost interest as it became clear that the Swedish auto maker's automotive operations had little to offer in the way of image or technology. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> originally had seen a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Saab</ENAMEX> alliance as a way to expand its presence in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">European</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> luxury car markets. In addition, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Saab</ENAMEX> had discussed a possible link between their heavy truck operations.
Meanwhile, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> officials became convinced they couldn't expect to recover the investment it would require to make <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Saab</ENAMEX>'s cars competitive in the increasingly crowded luxury market.
Industry analysts in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Europe</ENAMEX> said the most likely suitor for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Saab</ENAMEX> now is Fiat. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Saab</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Fiat</ENAMEX> have worked together in the past, in one case developing jointly a new auto chassis that became the foundation of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Saab</ENAMEX>'s 9000 model, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Fiat</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Croma</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lancia</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Thema</ENAMEX>. Last month, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Saab-Scania</ENAMEX> Chief Executive Georg <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Karnsund</ENAMEX> said his company has had talks with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Fiat</ENAMEX> about a broader alliance. But the talks yielded ``nothing so advanced that we needed to make a public announcement about it,'' he said.
As for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX>, analysts expect the end of the <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Saab</ENAMEX> play will allow the U.S. auto maker to focus its resources on the intensifying struggle with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX> for a stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX>.
The failure of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Saab</ENAMEX> talks ``makes it even more crucial for {<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX>} to be victorious'' in the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> contest, said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stephen Reitman</ENAMEX>, European auto industry analyst at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UBS-Phillips & Drew</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> faces an uphill fight for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX>, however. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> executives said last week they expect to have a friendly alliance with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX> wrapped up by the end of the month. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX>, meanwhile, is hosting a delegation of members of the British Parliament who are touring the auto maker's headquarter operations in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Detroit</ENAMEX>. A <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX> spokesman said the visit isn't connected to the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> situation.
