<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX> shares rallied to post strong gains after initial fears evaporated that the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">California</ENAMEX> earthquake would depress Wall Street prices.
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tokyo</ENAMEX> stocks, which rebounded strongly Tuesday, extended their gains yesterday, but most other Asian and Pacific markets closed sharply lower.
In <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Financial Times-Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> 100-share index jumped 34.6 points to close at its intraday high of 2170.1. The index was under pressure for most of the morning over concerns that the effects of Tuesday night's major earthquake in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">San Francisco</ENAMEX> area would undermine the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> market. The mood changed after dealers reappraised the direct impact of the disaster on shares and Wall Street rebounded from early losses.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.K.</ENAMEX> composite, or non-life, insurers, which some equity analysts said might be heavily hit by the earthquake disaster, helped support the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX> market by showing only narrow losses in early trading. The insurers' relative resilience gave the market time to reappraise the impact of the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">California</ENAMEX> disaster on <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.K.</ENAMEX> equities, dealers said.
Dealers said the market still hasn't shaken off its nervousness after its bumpy ride of the past several sessions, caused by interest-rate increases last week and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Wall Street</ENAMEX>'s 6.9% plunge Friday. But technical factors, including modest gains in the value of the pound, helped draw buying back into the market and reverse losses posted a day earlier.
Among composite insurers, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">General Accident</ENAMEX> rose 10 pence to # 10.03 ($15.80) a share, Guardian Royal climbed 5 to 217 pence, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sun Alliance</ENAMEX> rose 3 to 290, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Royal Insurance</ENAMEX> jumped 12 to 450. Life insurers fared similarly, with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Legal & General</ENAMEX> advancing 3 to 344, although Prudential fell 2 to 184 1/2. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pearl Group</ENAMEX> rose 5 to 628, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sun</ENAMEX> Life finished unchanged at # 10.98.
Most banking issues retreated after a sector downgrade by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warburg Securities</ENAMEX>, although <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">National Westminister</ENAMEX> showed strength on positive comments from brokerage firms about its long-term prospects. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Natwest</ENAMEX>, the most actively traded of the banks, finished at 300, up 1.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">B.A.T Industries</ENAMEX> fell in early dealings but recovered to finish at 754, up 5. Dealers said the market was nervous ahead of a special <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">B.A.T</ENAMEX> holders' meeting today. The session is to consider a defensive plan to spin off assets to fend off Sir <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">James Goldsmith</ENAMEX>'s # 13.4 billion bid for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">B.A.T.</ENAMEX>
The recent stock market drop has shaken confidence in the plan, but dealers said the shares fell initially on questions about whether Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Goldsmith</ENAMEX>'s highly leveraged bid will come to fruition.
Trading was suspended in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">WCRS Group</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.K.</ENAMEX> advertising concern, pending an announcement that it is buying the remaining 50% of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">France</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Carat Holding</ENAMEX> for 2.02 billion French francs ($318.7 million) and expanding commercial and equity ties with advertising group <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Eurocom</ENAMEX>.
On Wednesday, shares were pushed up by index-related buying on the part of investment trusts as well as small orders from individuals and corporations, traders said.
Institutions, meanwhile, stepped back to the sidelines as the direction of U.S. interest rates remained unclear. The uncertainty was multiplied by the persistent strength of the dollar, traders said, and by the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> trade deficit, which widened by 31% in August from the previous month.
Some traders said the popularity of issues that gained yesterday won't last long, as investors will rotate their buying choices over the short term.
Interest rate-sensitive shares such as steel, construction and electric utility companies, which rose early in the week, saw their advance weaken yesterday.
Traders said these issues need large-volume buying to push up their prices, so substantial gains aren't likely unless institutional investors participate.
An outstanding issue in yesterday's session was <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mitsubishi Rayon</ENAMEX>, which surged 95 to 905 yen ($6.34) a share. Its popularity was due to speculation about the strong earnings potential of a new type of plastic wrap for household use, a trader at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">County Natwest Securities Japan</ENAMEX> said.
Some laggard food issues attracted bargain-hunters, traders said. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kirin Brewery</ENAMEX> was up 100 at 2,000, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ajinomoto</ENAMEX> gained 70 to 2,840. Pharmaceuticals were mostly higher, with SS Pharmaceutical gaining 140 to 1,980.
In <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Brussels</ENAMEX>, it was the first trading day for most major shares since stocks tumbled on Wall Street Friday. Trading had been impeded by a major computer failure that took place before the start of Monday's session.
