<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mcdonnell Douglas Corp.</ENAMEX> reported a 54% drop in third-quarter net income, but its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Douglas Aircraft Co.</ENAMEX> subsidiary appears to be fixing some of its problems.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Douglas Aircraft</ENAMEX> completed a restructuring in the third quarter but clearly is still adjusting to the jolt. The subsidiary posted a $3 million loss for the quarter, but that was after a one-time pretax gain of $25 million stemming from an insurance payment.
``They lost $28 million, but that is good news,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jack Modzelewski</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Painewebber Inc.</ENAMEX> analyst, who had expected <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Douglas</ENAMEX>'s loss to be as much as $50 million. In the second quarter, the subsidiary had a $158 million loss.
At least, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Modzelewski</ENAMEX> said, ``it's losing money at a decelerating rate.''
Indeed, while investors weren't exactly gleeful, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mcdonnell Douglas</ENAMEX> held steady on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX>, closing yesterday at $67.125 a share, unchanged.
Sales for the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">St. Louis</ENAMEX>-based aircraft and defense company rose 1.1% to $3.72 billion from $3.68 billion.
Besides the troubles at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Douglas</ENAMEX> -- which continued to be plagued by high development costs on the new MD-11 tri-jet and parts shortages -- <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mcdonnell Douglas</ENAMEX>'s combat aircraft segment also had its difficulties. Profits for the division tumbled to $67 million from $91 million, primarily because of reduced earnings for its <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">AH</ENAMEX>-64 Apache helicopter and write-downs on several other helicopter programs. These more than offset an improved financial performance by the F-15 fighter. Earnings were also off 33% in the missiles, space and electronic-systems segment, despite a 13% rise in revenue. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Modzelewski</ENAMEX>, while noting that times are tough for arms makers, said he expected <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mcdonnell Douglas</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pentagon</ENAMEX>-related projects to ``bounce back next quarter'' to some degree. A number of defense-oriented aerospace companies, including <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Northrop Corp.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">General Dynamics Corp.</ENAMEX>, have reported either flat or lower third-quarter earnings.
But the biggest question mark remains <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Douglas</ENAMEX>. Deliveries of its MD-80 jetliner, which competes primarily with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing Co.</ENAMEX>'s 737 series, jumped to 30 in the third quarter, from 24 in the second period and 28 a year earlier. Losses on the program narrowed to $1 million in the latest quarter from $34 million in the second period.
Company officials boast that <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Douglas</ENAMEX> could account for half of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mcdonnell Douglas</ENAMEX> revenues by 1992, compared with about a third now. Besides the MD-80 and MD-11 commercial jetliners, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Douglas</ENAMEX> is building the T-45 Navy trainer and C-17 military transport.
But whether things at the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Long Beach</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Calif.</ENAMEX>, subsidiary can really be turned around has yet to be seen. ``<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Douglas</ENAMEX> is improving,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Judith Comeau</ENAMEX>, analyst at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Goldman Sachs & Co.</ENAMEX>, ``but they're no where near where they need to be.
