Stock prices closed slightly higher in the first routine trading day since Friday's big plunge. Some issues were affected by Tuesday's devastating earthquake in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">San Francisco</ENAMEX> area.
Activity continued to slow from the hectic pace set during the market's plunge late Friday and its rebound Monday, as players began to set their sights on events coming later this week.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> Industrial Average drifted through the session within a trading range of about 30 points before closing with a gain of 4.92 at 2643.65.
Broader averages also posted modest gains. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Standard & Poor</ENAMEX>'s 500-Stock Index rose 0.60 to 341.76, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> Equity Market Index rose 0.71 to 320.54 and the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> Composite Index gained 0.43 to 189.32. Some 822 <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> issues advanced in price, while 668 declined.
But the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones Transportation Average</ENAMEX> went down for the seventh consecutive session, due largely to further selling in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX>. The average dropped 6.40 to 1247.87 and has now lost 21.7% of its value since the losing streak began Oct. 10.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX> volume dropped to 166,900,000 shares, in line with the level of trading over the past few weeks, from 224.1 million Tuesday. Traders cited anticipation of the consumer price report for September, due today, and tomorrow's expiration of October stock-index futures and options as major factors in the slowdown.
``I didn't expect it to be this quiet. I expected to see more volatility as some of the institutions who were spooked last Friday did some selling,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Raymond F. Devoe</ENAMEX>, a market strategist at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Legg Mason Wood Walker</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Baltimore</ENAMEX>.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Devoe</ENAMEX> said he expects prices to show some renewed instability over the next few sessions as institutions re-evaluate their stance toward the market in light of its decline. ``I would suspect that a lot of investment committees are looking into whether (they) want to be in stocks at all,'' he said.
Insurance stocks were sold at the opening amid concerns about the level of damage claims the companies would receive as a result of the earthquake. But those issues recovered quickly and turned higher because of expectations that the quake and the recent Hurricane Hugo would set the stage for an increase in premium rates.
Issues of insurance brokers were especially strong. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Marsh & Mclennan</ENAMEX> advanced 3 1/8 to 75 7/8, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Alexander & Alexander Services</ENAMEX> climbed 2 to 32 and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Corroon & Black</ENAMEX> firmed 1 7/8 to 37 1/2.
Elsewhere in the group, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">General Re</ENAMEX> rose 2 3/4 to 86 1/2, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American International Group</ENAMEX> gained 3 1/4 to 102 5/8, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Aetna Life & Casualty</ENAMEX> added 2 3/8 to 59 1/2 and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cigna</ENAMEX> advanced 7/8 to 62 1/2. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Loews</ENAMEX>, the parent of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CNA Financial</ENAMEX>, rose 1 3/8 to 123 1/8.
Among engineering firms, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">CRS Sirrine</ENAMEX> rose 5/8 to 34 1/4 on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX> and four others rallied on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Stock Exchange</ENAMEX>: <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jacobs Engineering Group</ENAMEX>, which gained 1 1/8 to 25 3/8, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Greiner Engineering</ENAMEX>, which rose 3 1/2 to 22 1/2; <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Michael Baker</ENAMEX>, which added 1 1/4 to 15 1/4, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Science & Engineering</ENAMEX>, up 1/2 to 8 1/2.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bankamerica</ENAMEX> eased 1/2 to 31 7/8 and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Wells Fargo</ENAMEX> lost 1/2 to 81 1/2; the two bank holding companies, based in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">San Francisco</ENAMEX>, were forced to curtail some operations due to the temblor. Among <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">California</ENAMEX> savings-and-loan stocks, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">H.F. Ahmanson</ENAMEX> eased 3/8 to 22 1/4, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Calfed</ENAMEX> slid 3/4 to 24 1/8, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Great Western Financial</ENAMEX> dropped 1/2 to 21 1/4 and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Golden West Financial</ENAMEX> fell 5/8 to 29 1/4.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX>, the parent company of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Airlines</ENAMEX>, swung within a 14-point range during the course of the session before closing at 191 3/4, down 6 1/4, on 2.3 million shares.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Airways</ENAMEX>, a member of the group that had offered $300 a share for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> in a leveraged buy-out, said it had yet to receive a revised proposal and it was ``in no way committed'' to the completion of a bid. Separately, investor <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Marvin Davis</ENAMEX> withdrew his backup $300-a-share takeover offer.
While <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> faltered, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AMR</ENAMEX>, the parent of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Airlines</ENAMEX>, pulled out of its recent nosedive by rising 3/4 to 74. The stock had been on the decline since the financing for the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> buy-out fell through on Friday and developer <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Donald Trump</ENAMEX> subsequently withdrew a takeover offer of $120 a share for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AMR</ENAMEX>. Also, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AMR</ENAMEX> was the most active <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX> issue; 2.8 million shares changed hands.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Colgate-Palmolive</ENAMEX> advanced 1 5/8 to 63 after saying it was comfortable with analysts' projections that third-quarter net income from continuing operations would be between 95 cents and $1.05 a share, up from 69 cents a year ago.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Springs Industries</ENAMEX> dropped 1 3/8 to 36. Analysts at several brokerage firms lowered their 1989 and 1990 earnings estimates on the company after its third-quarter results proved disappointing.
Trinova third-quarter loss after a charge for a planned restructuring, which will include the closing or downsizing of about 25% of its plants and a work force cut of about 1,500 over three years.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Carnival Cruise Lines</ENAMEX> Class A rose 1 1/4 to 22 3/8. The company, citing market conditions, postponed a $200 million debt offer.
