In the bidding war for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Public Service Co. of New Hampshire</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Illuminating Co.</ENAMEX> raised its proposed offer to one it valued at $2.29 billion from $2.19 billion, apparently topping all other bidders.
The new round of bidding would seem to complicate the decision making for Judge <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">James Yacos</ENAMEX>, the bankruptcy judge overseeing the case, because the company's stockholders, unsecured creditors and regulators each are currently backing different plans. In addition, some of the proposals are so close, that non-financial issues such as timing may play a more important role.
The unsecured creditors agreed in principle to support <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New Haven</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Conn.</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Illuminating</ENAMEX>'s new bid. They previously had backed an internal reorganization plan proposed by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">PS of New Hampshire</ENAMEX>.
All of the bidders contemplate full payment including interest to secured creditors. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Illuminating</ENAMEX>'s plan, however, offers more for unsecured creditors.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Geoffrey Kalmus</ENAMEX>, counsel to the official creditors committee, said that under the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Illuminating</ENAMEX> plan, unsecured creditors would be paid in full credits and interest of about $855 million, accrued before <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">PS of New Hampshire</ENAMEX>'s Jan. 1988 filing for bankruptcy court protection. In addition, they would receive some $200 million in payments for interest since then. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kalmus</ENAMEX> said that by next July they would have accrued unpaid interest equal to $350 million. Other plans generally wouldn't pay unsecured creditors' interest accrued since the filing.
Under <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Illuminating</ENAMEX>'s plan, a new holding company would be formed to own the two companies. It would be 72%-owned by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Illuminating</ENAMEX> holders and 28%-owned by current holders of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">PS of New Hampshire</ENAMEX> preferred and common stock. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">PS of New Hampshire</ENAMEX> preferred holders also would get certain debentures and preferred stock. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Illuminating</ENAMEX> said the preferred holders total package would equal about 60% of their claims. Common shareholders would end up owning about 6.4% of the combined company.
As previously reported, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Northeast Utilities</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hartford</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Conn.</ENAMEX>, Monday filed a bid it valued at $2.25 billion. That offer was endorsed by the shareholders committee.
The other bidders, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New England Electric System</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Westboro</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mass.</ENAMEX>, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">PS of New Hampshire</ENAMEX>, didn't change the value of their bids, although <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">PS of New Hampshire</ENAMEX> changed its rate proposal. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New England Electric</ENAMEX> values its offer at $2 billion and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">PS of New Hampshire</ENAMEX> values its reorganization plan at $2.2 billion.
The state has endorsed the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New England Electric</ENAMEX> plan, which promises to limit rate increases to 4.8% annually for seven years. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Northeast Utilities</ENAMEX>' plan proposes 5.5% annual increases.
In <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> trading, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">PS of New Hampshire</ENAMEX>'s 17 1/2 debenture due 2004 closed yesterday at $82.50, up $2. The utility's stock closed at $4 a share, up 37.5 cents, in composite trading on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX>.
