The sale, at a higher price than some analysts had expected, helps the food and tobacco giant raise funds to pay debt and boosts <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nestle</ENAMEX>'s 7% share of the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> candy market to about 12%.
The candy businesses had sales of about $154 million last year, which was roughly 12% of total revenue for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">RJR</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Planters Lifesavers</ENAMEX> unit, according to a memorandum distributed by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">RJR</ENAMEX>'s owner, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Kohlberg Kravis Roberts & Co.</ENAMEX>, to bankers last December.
The Nestle acquisition includes a candy plant in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Franklin Park</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ill.</ENAMEX>, which employs about 800 workers.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Louis Gerstner Jr.</ENAMEX>, chairman and chief executive officer of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">RJR</ENAMEX>, called the sale a ``significant step'' in the company's divestiture program, as well as a ``a strategic divestiture.'' Since <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">KKR</ENAMEX> bought <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">RJR</ENAMEX> in February for $25 billion of debt, it has agreed to sell nearly $5 billion of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">RJR</ENAMEX> assets. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">RJR</ENAMEX>'s executives have said they will dispense with certain brands, in particular, that aren't leaders in their markets. ``<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">RJR Nabisco and Planters Lifesavers</ENAMEX> will concentrate more on our own core businesses,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gerstner</ENAMEX> said Friday.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Baby Ruth</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Butterfinger</ENAMEX> are both among the top-selling 15 chocolate bars in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX>, but <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">RJR</ENAMEX>'s overall share of the roughly $5.1 billion market is less than 5%. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nestle</ENAMEX>'s share of 7% before Friday's purchases is far below the shares of market leaders <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hershey Foods Corp.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mars Inc.</ENAMEX>, which have about 40% and 36% of the market, respectively.
``This means Nestle is now in the candybar business in a big way,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lisbeth Echeandia</ENAMEX>, publisher of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Orlando</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Fla.</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Confectioner Magazine</ENAMEX>. ``For them, it makes all kinds of sense. They've been given a mandate from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Switzerland</ENAMEX>'' to expand their U.S. chocolate operations. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nestle S.A.</ENAMEX> is based in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Vevey</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Switzerland</ENAMEX>.
