<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Denis C. Smith</ENAMEX> was named to the new post of vice president of world-wide advanced materials operations for this chemicals concern. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Smith</ENAMEX>, 50 years old, was formerly responsible for advanced materials, which include plastic composites and alloys, in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">North America</ENAMEX> only. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Himont</ENAMEX> is 81%-owned by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Montedison S.p. A.</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Milan</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Italy</ENAMEX>.
