<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Color Systems Technology Inc.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Los Angeles</ENAMEX>, said its major creditor, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">General Electric Pension Trust</ENAMEX>, agreed to convert $11.8 million of debt owed into 25% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Color System</ENAMEX>'s fully diluted common stock.
The agreement also calls for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">General Electric Pension</ENAMEX>, a unit of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">General Electric Co.</ENAMEX>, to receive as much as 10% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Color Systems</ENAMEX>' fully diluted common stock, depending on the proceeds from the sale of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AEI Film Library</ENAMEX> and its receivables. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">General Electric Pension</ENAMEX> took control of the 85-title library last month after <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Color Systems</ENAMEX> defaulted on the loan.
