<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Computer Associates International Inc.</ENAMEX> reported earnings for the second quarter, ended Sept. 30, plummeted 66%, primarily because of the acquisition of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cullinet Software Inc.</ENAMEX>
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Anthony Wang</ENAMEX>, president, attributed the drop to the disruption of the company's business resulting from the prolonged process of acquiring <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cullinet</ENAMEX>. The acquisition was completed in September.
In August, the company warned investors that the acquisition was being delayed, and many customers were holding off on purchase decisions until the takeover was completed. The delays mainly affected sales of data base management products, a core area for both <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Computer Associates</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cullinet</ENAMEX>, as well as sales of other products as part of package sales.
