<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mitsubishi Estate Co.</ENAMEX>, a major developer and property owner in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX>, has agreed to pay $846 million to acquire a 51% stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rockefeller Group Inc.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rockefeller</ENAMEX> officials said.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rockefeller Group</ENAMEX> owns the 22-acre, 19-building Rockefeller Center in midtown <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Manhattan</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mitsubishi</ENAMEX> is a partner in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Citicorp</ENAMEX> Plaza in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Los Angeles</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pacwest Center</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Portland</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ore.</ENAMEX>, and owns most of the land beneath <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tokyo</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Marunouchi</ENAMEX> central business district, often referred to as the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rockefeller Center</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tokyo</ENAMEX>.
In 1985, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rockefeller Group</ENAMEX> sold a mortgage on the core of Rockefeller Center to the public in the form of a real estate investment trust. The trust has an option to convert its shares to a 71.5% equity stake in the center by the year 2000. Analysts say a sale of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rockefeller Group</ENAMEX> shares should not affect the trust's value.
If the trust exercises its option as expected, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mitsubishi</ENAMEX> will gain only a minority stake in the most prestigious section of the center, which was built during the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Great Depression</ENAMEX>. Among the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rockefeller Group</ENAMEX> holdings not encumbered by the trust are the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Time & Life</ENAMEX> building, a majority stake in the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mcgraw-Hill</ENAMEX> building, a prime development site on the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Manhattan</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">West Side</ENAMEX> and certain development rights.
Sources familiar with the transaction say officials at some <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rockefeller</ENAMEX> units are unhappy with the deal. Managers of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rockefeller</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cushman & Wakefield Inc.</ENAMEX>, a national real estate brokerage, have reportedly structured a company buy-out plan which was rejected by its parent. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cushman</ENAMEX> President <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Arthur J. Mirante II</ENAMEX> had no comment on reports of the buy-out effort or the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mitsubishi</ENAMEX> acquisition. But the sources say <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rockefeller</ENAMEX> was seeking at least $200 million for the real estate services firm, a price that would make a buy-out impractical for the managers. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cushman</ENAMEX>'s management is made up of top brokers who are considered the firm's major asset and whose cooperation is regarded as vital to its success. Sources estimate <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Cushman</ENAMEX> will have 1989 revenue of more than $275 million.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rockefeller Group</ENAMEX> said in September it would seek investors to purchase as much as 80% of the firm, a holding company for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rockefeller</ENAMEX> family interests. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mitsubishi</ENAMEX> has agreed to acquire 627,000 shares of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rockefeller</ENAMEX> common stock held by trusts established by <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John D. Rockefeller</ENAMEX> in 1934.
When people ``understand the resources of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mitsubishi</ENAMEX> they'll see it represents an exciting future for the company,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Richard A. Voell</ENAMEX>, president of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rockefeller Group</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">William G. Bowen</ENAMEX>, chairman of the committee that oversees the family trusts, said the deal meets the committee's objective of diversification of the family's assets.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">David Rockefeller</ENAMEX>, chairman of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rockefeller Group</ENAMEX>, said the company talked with many potential investors in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">United States</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Europe</ENAMEX>. But Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rockefeller</ENAMEX> said he has a 20-year association with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mitsubishi</ENAMEX> from his days as chairman of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chase Manhattan Corp.</ENAMEX>
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Koyata Hosokawa</ENAMEX>, executive vice president of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mitsubishi</ENAMEX>, said the company has spent years studying the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> real estate market.
Sources say <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rockefeller Group</ENAMEX> had distributed a ``fact book'' to international real estate investors including <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mitsui Real Estate Development Co.</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Canada</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Olympia & York Developments Ltd.</ENAMEX>
Before yesterday's announcement, many observers wondered whether a Japanese buyer would be willing to acquire a piece of such high-profile American real estate. It is understood that Japanese buyers shied from bidding on the 110-story <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sears</ENAMEX> Tower in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chicago</ENAMEX> because purchasing the world's tallest building might stir anti-Japanese sentiments in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX>
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rockefeller Group</ENAMEX>'s management unit will continue to manage <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Rockefeller Center</ENAMEX>, a stipulation insisted upon by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rockefeller Group</ENAMEX>.
