Wall Street securities giant <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Salomon Inc.</ENAMEX> posted a big, unexpected earnings gain in the third quarter, buoyed by its securities trading and investment banking activities.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Salomon</ENAMEX> said net income soared to $177 million, or $1.28 a share, from $65 million, or 38 cents a share, a year earlier. Revenue more than doubled to $2.62 billion from $1.29 billion. A <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Salomon</ENAMEX> spokesman said its stock, bond and foreign exchange trading, as well as its investment banking operations, were mostly responsible for the earnings jump.
``The earnings were fine and above expectations,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Michael W. Blumstein</ENAMEX>, an analyst at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Boston Corp.</ENAMEX> Nevertheless, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Salomon</ENAMEX>'s stock fell $1.125 yesterday to close at $23.25 a share in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> composite trading. ``I suspect October wasn't as good as the third quarter, and they'll have difficulty matching the third quarter in the fourth quarter,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Blumstein</ENAMEX> said.
But some analysts say <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Salomon</ENAMEX> has turned the corner. ``I upgraded the firm to my buy list because I certainly see signs of improvement,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lawrence Eckenfelder</ENAMEX>, an analyst at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Prudential-Bache Securities.</ENAMEX> ``The market has been overly harsh to them.''
Analysts say investors remain skittish toward <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Salomon</ENAMEX> because of its volatile earnings. In the first quarter, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Salomon</ENAMEX> had a record loss of $28 million on revenue of $1.54 billion. But in the second quarter, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Salomon</ENAMEX> posted a record $253 million net on revenue of $2.33 billion.
