<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chemical Waste Management</ENAMEX> has turned into one of the market's best-performing stocks by advancing 76% in the past year. Its reward: a swarm of short sellers.
Short sellers are backwards investors: They borrow stock and sell it, hoping the price will go down. Eventually the shorts must ``cover'' by purchasing shares to replace the borrowed ones. But if a stock declines enough in the meantime, they profit.
What with all the garbage-disposal problems clogging the headlines, it's easy to see why the shares of the nation's largest hazardous-waste concern have zoomed ahead to yesterday's close of a post-split 22 1/8. But the stock now trades at a dizzying 32 times the latest 12-month earnings for the company, more than double the multiple of the market as a whole.
That handsome multiple, a badge of success, is also a red flag for the shorts, who like to bet that a stock can't stay hot forever. Between Sept. 15 and Oct. 13, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> says, the total number of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chemical Waste Management</ENAMEX> shares sold short leaped to 5.3 million from 1.9 million -- the largest increase for any stock on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX>.
The company says it hasn't any idea who is doing the shorting or why. A spokesman said he can't comment further because a stock offering is in progress. The offering will increase the public's stake to 23% and decrease that of the parent company, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Waste Management</ENAMEX>, to 77% from 81%.
Money managers and analysts generally agree that the stock has had a huge run and is now expensive. Some go further and say that owning it could be... well, hazardous.
``We love the company, we expect to be owners again, but we think for the moment it's at least adequately priced,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gerald Levine</ENAMEX>, a partner at <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Weiss</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Peck & Greer</ENAMEX>. The firm sold much of its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chemical Waste</ENAMEX> holding earlier this year, government filings show.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Levine</ENAMEX> says he can understand short sellers' motivation. ``When they see a stock extend on the end of a long up move, that is often a sign the stock is going to roll over,'' he says.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Alliance Capital Management</ENAMEX>, a unit of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Equitable Life Assurance Society</ENAMEX>, has sold at least 927,000 shares this year. It won't comment on the sales.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kenneth Hackel</ENAMEX>, a money manager who runs <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cash Flow Investors</ENAMEX> in Fort <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lee</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.J.</ENAMEX>, says <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chemical Waste</ENAMEX> is ``not my cup of tea.'' It sells for 38 times operating cash flow, he says, while the typical industrial company sells for only 7.7 times that yardstick.
Pricey though it may be, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chemical Waste</ENAMEX> still is a risky short-sale candidate. It has a superb record of earnings growth and a strong balance sheet. Citing those attributes, several well-known short sellers say they aren't the ones doing the shorting.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Shorting</ENAMEX> because of a high stock price alone is ``a recipe for death,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Julian Robertson</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tiger Management</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chemical Waste Management</ENAMEX> is ``not our kind of short,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Joe Feshbach</ENAMEX>, one of the three brothers who run <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Feshbach Brothers</ENAMEX>, generally considered the nation's largest short-selling firm. The company, he said, is too well-capitalized to ``go away.''
But Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Feshbach</ENAMEX> thinks other hazardous-waste companies' stocks ``could be a fruitful area {for shorting} because a number of companies have reported disappointing earnings'' recently. He said his firm has shorted the shares of one small company, which he wouldn't name.
Analysts say hazardous-waste companies that have posted disappointing earnings include <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Canonie Environmental Services</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Environmental Systems</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Groundwater Technology</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Gundle Environmental Systems</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rollins Environmental Services</ENAMEX>.
But <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chemical Waste</ENAMEX>'s earnings for the third quarter were ``sparkling,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kay Hahn</ENAMEX>, an analyst with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chicago Corp.</ENAMEX> She recommends the stock, and says short sellers are ``taking their life in their hands.''
Also bullish is <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Remy Fisher</ENAMEX>, a vice president with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">J.W. Seligman & Co.</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> money-management firm that has been increasing its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chemical Waste shareholdings.</ENAMEX> ``It doesn't seem like anything could tarnish {<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chemical Waste</ENAMEX>'s} growth prospects,'' she says. She points out that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chemical Waste</ENAMEX> has about 40% of the hazardous-waste industry's revenue, and that it's hard for new firms to enter the field because of government regulations and neighborhood opposition to hazardous-waste treatment plants.
Nevertheless, some analysts expect <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chemical Waste</ENAMEX>'s torrid growth to slow a bit. Earnings for 1989 will be up about 30%, says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Deborah Thielsch</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Boston</ENAMEX>, compared with 34% growth in 1988. For 1990, she expects a 25% gain. That's still enviable growth, but Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Thielsch</ENAMEX> is neutral on the stock, citing its ``incredibly high'' price-earnings ratio.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chemical Waste Management</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NYSE</ENAMEX>; Symbol: <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">CHW</ENAMEX>)
Business: Hazardous waste management
Net income: $116.9 million; or 58 cents a share
Common shares outstanding: 200.6 million
Note: Figures adjusted to reflect 2-for-1 stock split paid in October 1989.
