Prince, the rock star, is indecent, according to the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal Communications Comission</ENAMEX>. At least before 8 p.m.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FCC</ENAMEX> proposed to fine KLUC-FM, in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Las Vegas</ENAMEX>, $2,000 for playing the Prince song ``<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Erotic City</ENAMEX>'' on May 16, 1988, at 7:53 p.m. because the song is allegedly indecent. By FCC standards, that means the song uses ``patently offensive'' terms to describe ``sexual or excretory activities or organs.''
``<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Erotic City</ENAMEX>,'' which was released as a single in 1984 and sold 250,000 copies, is certainly hot -- too hot for this newspaper to reproduce the lyrics. Suffice it to say, the song uses a short word for sexual congress, and congress is in session a lot during the song.
An agent for Prince didn't return a telephone call seeking comment. And <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">KLUC</ENAMEX>, a part of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nationwide Communications Inc.</ENAMEX>, couldn't be reached. The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Las Vegas</ENAMEX> telephone directory only lists <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">KLUC</ENAMEX>'s ``Concert <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hot Line</ENAMEX>'' -- and no one answered the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hot Line</ENAMEX> at midday yesterday.
But the proposed fine is bound to be controversial. For one thing, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FCC</ENAMEX> dismissed 51 complaints about indecency because the programs aired material after 8 p.m. -- only seven minutes after <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">KLUC</ENAMEX> played ``<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Erotic City</ENAMEX>.'' The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FCC</ENAMEX> now says 8 p.m. is the time that is all right to begin airing indecent material because children aren't likely listening in great numbers. Earlier, the agency set the decency line at midnight, but an appeals court rejected that time as too restrictive.
``You have to draw some lines,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Robert Pettit</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FCC</ENAMEX>'s general counsel.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Tom Chiusano</ENAMEX>, vice president and general manager of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">WXRK</ENAMEX>-<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FM</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>, said the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FCC</ENAMEX> decision singling out KLUC seemed unfair because he estimated probably 500 radio stations have played ``<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Erotic City</ENAMEX>.'' But Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Chiusano</ENAMEX> has his own problems. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FCC</ENAMEX> also sent WXRK a letter saying it believed one of its shows, the <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Howard Stern</ENAMEX> Show, contained indecent material.
The agency hasn't yet proposed a fine for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">WXRK</ENAMEX>. But two years ago, when the agency began its crackdown on indecency, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stern</ENAMEX>'s show, which features a lot of gross jokes, was one of the shows cited in the agency's first warning letters to broadcasters. ``<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Howard Stern</ENAMEX> doesn't broadcast indecent material,'' said Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Chiusano</ENAMEX>. ``He does four hours of contemporaneous humor.''
So far the indecency crackdown has managed to offend both civil libertarians, who say the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FCC</ENAMEX> has gone too far, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Congress</ENAMEX>, which says the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FCC</ENAMEX> hasn't gone far enough. Meanwhile the courts have rejected most of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FCC</ENAMEX>'s plans, and the agency has been subject to constant ridicule. One commissioner even proposed banning a reading of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">James Joyce</ENAMEX>'s ``<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ulysses</ENAMEX>'' until cooler heads prevailed.
But the agency hasn't given up. In addition to citing the stations in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Las Vegas</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FCC</ENAMEX> proposed fining radio stations in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Miami</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Los Angeles</ENAMEX> for airing allegedly indecent material before 8 p.m. In addition, the agency said it would begin a proceeding to see whether it was possible to find legal grounds for a ban on indecent programming around the clock.
