<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dunkin' Donuts Inc.</ENAMEX>, battling a takeover proposal by <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Canada</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">DD Acquisition Corp.</ENAMEX>, said that its directors will evaluate takeover offers submitted by Nov. 10.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dunkin' Donuts</ENAMEX>, based in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Randolph</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mass.</ENAMEX>, previously said it would explore ``alternatives,'' including a leveraged buy-out of the company, but hadn't set a date for submission of proposals.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dunkin' Donuts</ENAMEX>' announcement followed <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">DD Acquisition</ENAMEX>'s request to the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Delaware Court</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chancery</ENAMEX> Monday to set a trial date for its suit against the company. The trial had been postponed to allow <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dunkin' Donuts</ENAMEX> to seek alternatives to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">DD Acquisition</ENAMEX>'s offer.
