<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Arthur Price</ENAMEX> abruptly quit as president and chief executive officer of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MTM Entertainment Inc.</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Los Angeles</ENAMEX> production company that has fallen on hard times.
Industry analysts speculated that Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Price</ENAMEX>'s sudden departure may have stemmed from conflicts with Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gatward</ENAMEX>.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Price</ENAMEX> ``wanted to run the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MTM</ENAMEX> business'' and may have regretted selling the company to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">TVS</ENAMEX>, suggested <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Charles Denton</ENAMEX>, managing director of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Zenith Productions</ENAMEX>, a subsidiary of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Carlton Communications PLC</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX>.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gatward</ENAMEX> declined to comment, and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Price</ENAMEX> couldn't be reached on Friday. In the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">TVS</ENAMEX> statement, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Price</ENAMEX> said ``leaving <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MTM</ENAMEX> was a very difficult decision,'' but added that ``it is now time for a change....''
The $320 million purchase of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MTM</ENAMEX> represented an audacious international move for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">TVS</ENAMEX>, which then was about half the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> concern's size. At the time, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gatward</ENAMEX> said his friendship with Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Price</ENAMEX> had smoothed the way for its link with the small British company. But <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">TVS</ENAMEX> stunned industry analysts last month by disclosing that it expected MTM to post an operating loss for this year.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Price</ENAMEX> co-founded <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MTM</ENAMEX> in 1969 with U.S. actress <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mary Tyler Moore</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Grant Tinker</ENAMEX>, her then-husband. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Tinker</ENAMEX> later left to become chairman of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">National Broadcasting Co.</ENAMEX> The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">TVS</ENAMEX> spokesman said Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Price</ENAMEX> still holds about an 8% TVS stake, acquired as part of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MTM</ENAMEX> acquisition. In late trading on <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> Friday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">TVS</ENAMEX> shares rose four pence to 195 pence a share.
