<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bond Corp.</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Holdings Ltd.</ENAMEX>'s consolidated debt totals 6.9 billion Australian dollars (US$5.32 billion), including A$1.6 billion of bonds convertible into shares.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Alan Bond</ENAMEX>, chairman and controlling shareholder of the cash-strapped Australian media, brewing, resources and property concern, disclosed the debt figures yesterday.
The debt load would have been higher but for a reduction of A$5 billion over the past year from asset sales, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bond</ENAMEX> said at a business gathering.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bond</ENAMEX> indicated the consolidated debt figures, which include debt of units such as <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bell Group Ltd.</ENAMEX>, will be published soon in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bond Corp.</ENAMEX>'s 1989 annual accounts.
He predicted the debt will be reduced by another A$3.8 billion this fiscal year ending June 30, 1990, but didn't explain how this will be achieved.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bond</ENAMEX> blamed rising Australian interest rates and the acquisition of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bell Group</ENAMEX> ``with its very high levels of shortterm debt'' for producing a condition ``that was no longer sustainable.
``In order to restore confidence and ensure the support of our principal lenders,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bond</ENAMEX> said, ``we embarked on fundamantal changes in the structure and direction of the group.''
That reassessment resulted in continuing asset sales, as well as write-offs exceeding A$1.1 billion last fiscal year. ``In essence we have made a decision to clear the decks,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bond</ENAMEX> told the meeting.
While some assets have been written down, others are undervalued in the accounts, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bond</ENAMEX> maintained. Among these are the company's Australian brewing assets, in the books at A$950 million but actually worth A$2.5 billion, he said. An investment in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chile</ENAMEX>'s telephone company is carried at US$300 million but really worth US$500 million, and the company's property portfolio is undervalued by at least A$250 million, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bond</ENAMEX> said.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bond</ENAMEX> forecast that by next June, ``what will emerge will be a company with a honed sense of purpose... a stable balance sheet, with good-quality assets in brewing, telecommunications, media and property.''
He didn't name energy resources in that list, signaling that all the company's coal and oil interests might be for sale in total or in part. Some of the oil interests already have been sold.
