<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Delta Air Lines</ENAMEX> earnings soared 33% to a record in the fiscal first quarter, bucking the industry trend toward declining profits.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Atlanta</ENAMEX>-based airline, the third largest in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX>, attributed the increase to higher passenger traffic, new international routes and reduced service by rival <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Eastern Airlines</ENAMEX>, which is in bankruptcy proceedings in the wake of a strike that began last spring.
Revenue rose 15% to $2.17 billion from $1.89 billion. During the quarter, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Delta</ENAMEX> issued 2.5 million shares of common stock to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Swissair</ENAMEX>, and repurchased 1.1 million shares for use in a company employee stock ownership plan.
``The key to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Delta</ENAMEX>'s record earnings continued to be excellent passenger revenue growth,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Thomas Roeck</ENAMEX>, chief financial officer. Passenger traffic jumped 14% in the quarter, while profit per passenger grew 2%.
Separately, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">America West Airlines</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Phoenix</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ariz.</ENAMEX>, reported third-quarter profit jumped 45% to $5.8 million, or 28 cents a share, from $4 million, or 24 cents a share, a year earlier. The latest results include a $2.6 million one-time payment from a ``foreign entity.'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">America West</ENAMEX> wouldn't identify the entity, but said the payment was for the foreign company's use of certain tax benefits in connection with <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">America</ENAMEX> West plane purchases. Year-earlier results included an extraordinary gain of $1.6 million from a buy-back of convertible subordinated debentures.
