<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ashland Oil Inc.</ENAMEX> said it will take after-tax charges of $78 million, or $1.40 a share, in its fiscal fourth quarter, ended Sept. 30.
Because of the charge, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ashland</ENAMEX> expects to report a loss for the fourth quarter and ``significantly lower results'' for fiscal 1989.
The charges consist of: a $25 million after-tax charge to cover cost overruns in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ashland</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Riley Consolidated</ENAMEX> subsidiary; a previously announced $38 million after-tax charge resulting from a $325 million settlement with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">National Iranian Oil Co.</ENAMEX> and a $15 million after-tax charge from the previously announced sale of its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ashland Technology Corp.</ENAMEX> subsidiary. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ashland</ENAMEX> expects that sale to be complete next year.
The charge for the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Riley</ENAMEX> subsidiary is for expected costs to correct problems with certain bed boilers built for utilities. The charge will be added to $20 million in reserves established a year ago to cover the cost overruns.
