<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CONFRONTATIONS</ENAMEX> LOOM between <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bush</ENAMEX> and Democrats in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Congress</ENAMEX>.
The early bipartisanship dissipates as issues become more contentious and the Democrats find their voice. They begin to blame <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bush</ENAMEX>'s insistence on a capital-gains cut for the disarray in the budget process; one <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">White House</ENAMEX> aide sees a ``train wreck'' coming. The Democrats also increasingly lash <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bush</ENAMEX> for timidity on <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Eastern Europe</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">White House</ENAMEX> advisers formally threaten vetoes of the foreign-aid and child-care bills and informally discuss a possible veto of the defense bill. Child care could be an especially tough fight; after <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bush</ENAMEX>'s veto of abortion funding for rape and incest victims, anti-abortion lawmakers feel extra pressure to show attention to women's concerns.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bush</ENAMEX> still tries a personal touch; he golfs with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ways and Means</ENAMEX> Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rostenkowski</ENAMEX> and meets privately with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Senate</ENAMEX> Democrats.
A ``MUST-SIGN'' BILL becomes a magnet for controversial proposals.
To avoid missing Social Security payments, the government must get a raise in its borrowing limit by Nov. 8; the necessity of the measure attracts numerous attempts at adding unrelated measures to it. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Republicans</ENAMEX> will try to offer the capital-gains cut in the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Senate</ENAMEX>; the Democrats probably have the votes to block it, though some fear brinksmanship on the bill.
Other likely candidates for riders include revision of the Gramm-Rudman law, repeal of catastrophic-illness insurance, child care and other measures that were stripped off the recent budget-reconciliation bill. Democratic leaders will try to keep them off, fearing that allowing any of them would weaken their argument against capital gains.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">BUSH</ENAMEX> TURNS the failed Panama coup to his advantage, at least for now.
His complaints about secret restrictions on anti-Noriega plots put Congress on the defensive, even though the curbs didn't play a role in the coup's collapse. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Senate</ENAMEX> intelligence chiefs <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Boren</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Cohen</ENAMEX> agree with the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">White House</ENAMEX> to loosen the rules; <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CIA</ENAMEX> agents stand to gain broad leeway to work with rebels, even if a coup might endanger <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Noriega</ENAMEX>'s life.
The next step: a new covert plan for unseating the dictator. One possibility is more active American recruitment of rebels who would agree to hand Noriega to the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> and install the elected leaders he rebuffed. The last coup plotters refused to do either.
But <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bush</ENAMEX>'s handling of the previous attempt hobbles future efforts. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Noriega</ENAMEX> has purged potential enemies, and doubts grow about U.S. resolve.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">LAWMAKERS</ENAMEX>' PATIENCE wears thin over the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CFTC</ENAMEX>'s slow pace of reform after the ``sting'' operation that led to the spring indictments of 46 traders at two <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chicago</ENAMEX> exchanges. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Incredulous senators grill</ENAMEX> Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Wendy</ENAMEX> Gramm about the fact that 11 of the traders are still handling customer accounts. <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Nebraska</ENAMEX> Sen. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kerrey</ENAMEX> asks her: ``Do you work full-time at this job?''
THE <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">PENTAGON</ENAMEX> BALKS at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Darman</ENAMEX>'s budget strategy of threatening to make the automatic Gramm-Rudman cuts permanent. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pentagon</ENAMEX> brass worry it could mean sharp cutbacks in training, acquisition of spare parts and weapons development. ``The impact for us could be appreciably worse than <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">OMB</ENAMEX> has admitted in its maneuvering with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Congress</ENAMEX>,'' says a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pentagon</ENAMEX> budget aide.
NEW ALLY: Attorney General <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Thornburgh</ENAMEX>, back from the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.S.R.</ENAMEX>, reports that the Soviets are now providing assistance and intelligence to the U.S. on international drug trafficking. In exchange, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.S. Drug Enforcement Administration</ENAMEX> is training several Soviet agents in drug enforcement.
ORGAN-TRANSPLANT DOCTORS worry at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">HHS</ENAMEX> moves to assert control over the transplant system, currently overseen by a nonprofit group under federal contract. The department decides to impose a 10-step review on new transplant policies. Dr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Robert Corry</ENAMEX>, who heads the nonprofit group, says the move will ``stifle innovative changes'' and slow medical progress; he hopes to negotiate a compromise.
ABORTION POLITICS shape legal as well as electoral agendas.
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Illinois</ENAMEX> Attorney General <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Neil Hartigan</ENAMEX>, whose gubernatorial campaign is under pressure from pro-choice forces, pursues a settlement of the current <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Supreme Court</ENAMEX> case challenging the state's tough restrictions on abortion clinics. Agreement would sharply reduce the stakes in the court this term; the two remaining cases don't as directly challenge Roe vs. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Wade</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Pennsylvania</ENAMEX>'s new abortion law almost certainly will provide a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Supreme Court</ENAMEX> test, but probably not until next year. Abortion-rights activists plan a new series of major marches next month, but their biggest boost would come with a gubernatorial victory in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Virginia</ENAMEX>, where black nominee <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Wilder</ENAMEX> is riding the pro-choice issue hard.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">National Abortion</ENAMEX> Rights Action League, already running ads for Wilder, hits the airwaves today for <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New Jersey</ENAMEX> Democratic candidate <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Florio</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MINOR MEMOS</ENAMEX>: Among documents in the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">HUD</ENAMEX> scandal: a handwritten 1987 letter from presidential son Jeb <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bush</ENAMEX> to <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Deborah Dean</ENAMEX>, a central figure in the scandal, wishing her ``every success in trying to clean up the federal government's act.''... GOP Rep. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bentley</ENAMEX> writes business Pacs promising to ``lead the battle'' against President <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bush</ENAMEX>'s proposal to abolish them -- and asking for money for her 1990 campaign.... Sen. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mitchell</ENAMEX>'s advice to visiting <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Supreme Soviet</ENAMEX> members drawing up rules for their legislature: ``Don't copy ours.
