<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Trustcorp Inc.</ENAMEX> will become <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Society Bank & Trust</ENAMEX> when its merger is completed with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Society Corp.</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Cleveland</ENAMEX>, the bank said.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Society Corp.</ENAMEX>, which is also a bank, agreed in June to buy <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Trustcorp</ENAMEX> for 12.4 million shares of stock with a market value of about $450 million. The transaction is expected to close around year end.
