THE <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> ECONOMY GREW at a moderate 2.5% annual rate in the third quarter despite the worst trade performance in six years. The expansion, matching the second quarter's pace, was fueled by strong consumer spending, especially for autos. But analysts expect GNP growth to slow in the current quarter. An inflation gauge slowed to a 2.9% growth rate from 5% the previous quarter.
The Big Three car makers all posted quarterly losses in core North American auto operations for the first time since 1982. Expectations of slow sales and price wars are dimming the outlook for the current quarter.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX> is seeking to buy up to 15% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX>, marking its first salvo in a looming battle with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> for control of the British luxury car maker.
Stock prices tumbled amid growing concern about corporate earnings. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> industrials closed off 39.55 points, at 2613.73. Most bonds eased, but long-term <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Treasury</ENAMEX> issues edged up. The dollar also gained, especially against the British pound.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Painewebber Group</ENAMEX> ordered a major pullback from program trading amid mounting debate about the practice at Wall Street firms.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AT*/NNP&T</ENAMEX> was allowed by the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">FCC</ENAMEX> to continue offering discount phone services to big-business clients. The agency also plans to review its regulation of the long-distance market.
A capital-gains tax cut has stalled in the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Senate</ENAMEX>. Democratic leaders have bottled up the plan and may be able to prevent a vote indefinitely.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Treasury</ENAMEX> Secretary <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Brady</ENAMEX> said the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">SEC</ENAMEX> should be given the authority to close the stock markets in a crisis. Earlier, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">SEC</ENAMEX> Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Breeden</ENAMEX> said he doesn't want such power because it could end up disrupting the markets.
Regional thrift regulators claimed that phone calls were bugged during the examination of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lincoln S&L</ENAMEX> and that federal officials delayed <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Lincoln</ENAMEX>'s seizure until it had become the costliest thrift failure ever.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal Express</ENAMEX> pilots voted against joining a union, a major victory for Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Frederick Smith</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Intel</ENAMEX>'s most powerful chip has flaws that could delay several computer makers' marketing efforts. But the bugs aren't expected to hurt <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Intel</ENAMEX> and most computer manufacturers.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bethlehem Steel</ENAMEX> agreed to form a joint venture with the world's second-biggest steelmaker, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Usinor</ENAMEX>-<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sacilor</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">France</ENAMEX>, to modernize part of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bethlehem</ENAMEX>'s ailing <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bethforge</ENAMEX> division.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Treasury</ENAMEX> will hold an unscheduled auction of securities next week to raise $17 billion. The unusual move is intended to buy time for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Congress</ENAMEX> to debate a debt-limit increase.
Private-sector union contracts signed in the third quarter granted an average annual wage increase of 3%, slightly below the second-quarter rise but still above year-ago levels.
Quantum <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chemical</ENAMEX> suspended its cash dividend in favor of a stock payout. It also posted a quarterly loss.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navigation Mixte</ENAMEX> rejected as too low a $1.77 billion bid by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paribas</ENAMEX>, which is seeking to boost its stake in the French conglomerate to 66.7%.
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">France</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Banque Indosuez</ENAMEX> surprised <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX> markets by moving to become the dominant shareholder in merchant bank <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Morgan Grenfell.</ENAMEX>
Markets --
Dollar: 142.10 yen, up 0.58; 1.8400 marks, up 0.0047.
