Although the personal computer maker said it expects revenue to meet or exceed previous projections of $385 million for the year ending Jan. 28, 1990, earnings are expected to be 25 cents to 35 cents a share, down from previous estimates of 50 cents to 60 cents. Earnings for fiscal 1989 were $14.4 million, or 80 cents a share, on sales of $257.8 million.
Results for the third quarter ending Oct. 31, are expected to be released the third week of November, according to <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Michael Dell</ENAMEX>, chairman and chief executive officer. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dell</ENAMEX> said he doesn't expect a loss in either the third or fourth quarter, but said third-quarter earnings could be as low as four cents a share. In the third quarter last year, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dell</ENAMEX> had net income of $5 million, or 26 cents a share, on sales of $75.2 million.
``They've got a lot of different balls in the air at the same time,'' observes <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jim Poyner</ENAMEX>, a computer securities analyst with <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dallas</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">William K. Woodruff & Co.</ENAMEX> Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dell</ENAMEX>, meanwhile, concedes the company was ``definitely too optimistic'' in its expectations.
Analyst <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">James Weil</ENAMEX> of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Soundview Financial Group</ENAMEX> believes <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dell</ENAMEX>'s response has been to place increased emphasis on product quality, ``in an effort to rise above some of that price pressure.'' But that has been the key to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Compaq</ENAMEX>'s success, he adds, whereas <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dell</ENAMEX> carved out its market niche as a direct seller of low-cost but reliable computers -- and it might be too late in the game for a shift in strategy.
In national over-the-counter trading, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dell</ENAMEX> closed yesterday at $6 a share, down 87.5 cents.
