<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Tennessee National Corp.</ENAMEX> said it would take a $4 million charge in the fourth quarter, as a result of plans to expand its systems operation.
Further, under the agreement, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Tennesse</ENAMEX> would continue to develop the software that creates customer products and sevices.
``Because personal computers will soon be on the desks of all of our tellers, and customer service and loan representatives, information will be instantly available to help customers with product decisions and provide them with information about their accounts,'' according to <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John Kelley</ENAMEX>, executive vice president and corporate services group manager at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Tennessee.</ENAMEX>
