Costa <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rica</ENAMEX> is nearing an agreement with its creditors on a plan for restructuring $1.8 billion of its commercial debt, a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bank of America</ENAMEX> executive said.
Costa <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rica</ENAMEX> is one of several debtor countries trying to buy back some of their loans under a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> initiative named after <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Treasury</ENAMEX> Secretary <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Nicholas Brady</ENAMEX>.
Negotiations have been rushed in order to be completed in time for President <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bush</ENAMEX>'s trip to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Costa Rica</ENAMEX>, and the agreement is likely to be announced today. People involved in the negotiations said the accord will reduce <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Costa Rica</ENAMEX>'s foreign debt principal by more than 60%.
``We are reasonably close to an agreement on a <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Brady</ENAMEX>-type plan for Costa Rica,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peter Mcpherson</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bank of America</ENAMEX>'s executive vice president. His comments were the first signs of an imminent breakthrough in negotiations between <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Costa Rica</ENAMEX> and its commercial lenders.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bank of America</ENAMEX>, which chairs a committee representing Costa <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rica</ENAMEX>'s creditors, said the prospective plan would enable the country to buy back about $1 billion of debt at a ``substantial discount.'' The repurchase is to be financed by fresh credits from the International Monetary Fund, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">World Bank</ENAMEX> and donor governments.
Costa <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rica</ENAMEX> also would be able to pay overdue interest on its still-outstanding loans at ``more favorable terms'' than regular debtors, other U.S. bankers said.
