At a shareholders' meeting in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX>, the tobacco, financial-services and retailing giant said it received 99.9% approval from voting holders for plans to spin off about $6 billion in assets.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">B.A.T</ENAMEX> yesterday started its share buy-back. The company said it acquired 2.5 million shares for 785 pence ($12.48) each, or a total of # 19.6 million ($31.2 million), from its broker, Barclays <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">de Zoete Wedd</ENAMEX>. The share buy-back plan is likely to underpin <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">B.A.T</ENAMEX>'s share price.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">B.A.T</ENAMEX> said it may make more equity purchases until the close of business today, depending on market conditions, but will cease further purchases until Nov. 22, when it releases third-quarter results.
Shareholder approval sets the stage for a lengthy process of restructuring that might not be completed until next year's second half. Before the recent tumult in global financial markets, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">B.A.T</ENAMEX> officials, holders and analysts had expected a substantial part of the restructuring to be complete by the end of the first half.
``We are not in any hurry to sell'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Saks</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Marshall Field</ENAMEX> or <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">B.A.T</ENAMEX>'s other U.S. retail properties, said Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Patrick Sheehy</ENAMEX>. ``This isn't a distress sale. We are determined to get good prices.''
