<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Digital Equipment Corp.</ENAMEX> reported a 32% decline in net income on a modest revenue gain in its fiscal first quarter, causing some analysts to predict weaker results ahead than they had expected.
Although the second-largest computer maker had prepared Wall Street for a poor quarter, analysts said they were troubled by signs of flat U.S. orders and a slowdown in the rate of gain in foreign orders. The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Maynard</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mass.</ENAMEX>, company is in a transition in which it is trying to reduce its reliance on mid-range machines and establish a presence in workstations and mainframes.
Net for the quarter ended Sept. 30 fell to $150.8 million, or $1.20 a share, from $223 million, or $1.71 a share, a year ago. Revenue rose 6.4% to $3.13 billion from $2.94 billion.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Digital</ENAMEX> said a shift in its product mix toward low-end products and strong growth in workstation sales yielded lower gross margins. A spokesman also said margins for the company's service business narrowed somewhat because of heavy investments made in that sector.
The lack of a strong product at the high end of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Digital</ENAMEX>'s line was a significant drag on sales. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Digital</ENAMEX> hopes to address that with the debut of its first mainframe-class computers next Tuesday. The new line is aimed directly at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">International Business Machines Corp.</ENAMEX>
``Until the new mainframe products kick in, there won't be a lot of revenue contribution at the high end, and that's hurt us,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mark Steinkrauss</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Digital</ENAMEX>'s director of investor relations. He said unfavorable currency translations were also a factor in the quarter.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">DEC</ENAMEX> shares rose $1.375 to $89.75 apiece in consolidated <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> trading yesterday. But analysts said that against the backdrop of a nearly 40-point rise in the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> Industrial Average, that shouldn't necessarily be taken as a sign of great strength. Some cut their earnings estimates for the stock this year and predicted more efforts to control costs ahead.
``I think the next few quarters will be difficult,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steven Milunovich</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Boston.</ENAMEX> ``Margins will remain under pressure, and when the new mainframe does ship, I'm not sure it will be a big winner.'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Milunovich</ENAMEX> said he was revising his estimate for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">DEC</ENAMEX>'s current year from $8.20 a share to ``well below $8,'' although he hasn't settled on a final number.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Marc Schulman</ENAMEX>, with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UBS Securities</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>, dropped his estimate of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">DEC</ENAMEX>'s full-year net to $6.80 a share from $8. Although overall revenues were stronger, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Schulman</ENAMEX> said, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">DEC</ENAMEX> ``drew down its European backlog'' and had flat world-wide orders overall. ``The bottom line is that it's more hand to mouth than it has been before,'' he said.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Schulman</ENAMEX> said he believes that the roll-out of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">DEC</ENAMEX>'s new mainframe will ``occur somewhat more leisurely'' than many of his investment colleagues expect. He said current expectations are for an entry level machine to be shipped in December, with all of the more sophisticated versions out by June. For reasons he wouldn't elaborate on, he said he's sure that schedule won't be met, meaning less profit impact from the product for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">DEC</ENAMEX> in the next few quarters.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John R. Wilke</ENAMEX> contributed to this article.
