<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Transatlantic Holdings PLC</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">British</ENAMEX>-based, South African-controlled financial services investment group, and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">France</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Societe Centrale Union</ENAMEX> des <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Assurances</ENAMEX> de <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Paris</ENAMEX> reached an accord effectively reducing chances of an unfriendly takeover for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sun Life Assurance Society PLC</ENAMEX>.
In a joint statement, the two companies, whose combined holdings equal 52.7% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sun Life</ENAMEX>'s ordinary shares, said their agreement is aimed at reducing ``the uncertainty and instability for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sun</ENAMEX> Life that has resulted from two major shareholders owning'' a controlling interest in the company.
