<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mesa Airlines</ENAMEX> said the takeover offer it received earlier this week from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Stateswest Airlines</ENAMEX> is for a combination of cash and securities valued by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Stateswest</ENAMEX> at $10 a Mesa share. Both companies are regional carriers in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Southwest</ENAMEX>.
When it made the offer, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Stateswest</ENAMEX> declined to disclose details and asked Mesa to do the same. But <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Farmington</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.M.</ENAMEX>-based Mesa said the offer was for $7 in cash and unspecified Stateswest securities valued at $3 a share. Based on the number of Mesa shares outstanding not already owned by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Stateswest</ENAMEX>, the proposed takeover would have a value of about $15.3 million. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Stateswest</ENAMEX> owns 7.25% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mesa.</ENAMEX>
Last week, Mesa rejected a general proposal from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Stateswest</ENAMEX> that the two carriers combine. In response to the specific offer, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gary Risley</ENAMEX>, Mesa vice president, said management will ask directors to employ a financial consultant to advise them.
