The Finnish government and major creditors of bankrupt shipyard <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Waertsilae Marine Industries Oy</ENAMEX> agreed in principle to form a new company to complete most of the troubled shipyard's backlog of 15 ships.
The new company will attempt to limit the shipyard's losses, participants said. ``The situation is that the bankruptcy court will get out of the shipbuilding business. Everything will be taken over by the new company,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Christian Andersson</ENAMEX>, executive vice president of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Oy Waertsilae</ENAMEX>, former parent of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Waertsilae Marine</ENAMEX>.
Once its ownership is finalized, the new company will open talks with state-appointed receivers to buy or lease <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Waertsilae Marine</ENAMEX>'s shipyard facilities. Subcontractors will be offered a settlement and a swift transition to new management is expected to avert an exodus of skilled workers from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Waertsilae Marine</ENAMEX>'s two big shipyards, government officials said.
Under an accord signed yesterday, the government and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Union Bank</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Finland</ENAMEX> would become major shareholders in the new company, each injecting 100 million Finnish markkaa ($23.5 million). <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Oy Waertsilae</ENAMEX> is to contribute 200 million markkaa, most of it as subordinated debt, and take a minority stake in the new company.
Customers holding contracts for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Waertsilae Marine</ENAMEX>'s undelivered ships are expected to subscribe most of the remaining 170 million markkaa in share capital, government officials said.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Waertsilae Marine</ENAMEX>'s biggest creditor is <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Miami</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Carnival Cruise Lines Inc.</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Carnival</ENAMEX>, which has three ships on order from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Waertsilae Marine</ENAMEX>, presented claims for $1.5 billion damages in the bankruptcy court this week.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Waertsilae Marine</ENAMEX>'s bankruptcy proceedings began Tuesday in a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Helsinki</ENAMEX> court.
