The electronics maker and retailer previously estimated the sale price at between $100 million and $200 million for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Datatronic</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Victor microcomputer</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Micronic</ENAMEX> hand-held computer subsidiaries. In addition, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tandy</ENAMEX> will acquire rights to the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Victor and Micronic</ENAMEX> names for computers. During 1988, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Datatronic</ENAMEX> subsidiaries had combined sales in excess of $200 million.
Closing of the transaction is subject to certain conditions and regulatory approvals, the company said.
