<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bell Atlantic Corp.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Southern New England Telecommunications</ENAMEX> posted strong profit gains for the third quarter, while <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nynex Corp.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pacific Telesis Group</ENAMEX> and U <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">S West Inc.</ENAMEX> reported earnings declines for the period.
Rate settlements in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Minnesota</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Colorado</ENAMEX> depressed U <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">S West</ENAMEX>'s third-quarter profit. <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Denver</ENAMEX>-based U <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">S West</ENAMEX> said net income dropped 8.9%, noting that the year-ago quarter included the sale of a building by its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Betawest Properties</ENAMEX> unit.
Revenue dropped 4.3% to $2.3 billion from $2.4 billion, reflecting declines in its consumer-telephone sector, long-distance carrier business and diversified division. Revenue from business-telephone operations grew 3.3% to $618.9 million from $599.4 million a year ago.
``On a truly comparable basis, we've seen modest earnings growth this year from the operations of our company,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jack Macallister</ENAMEX>, chairman and chief executive officer. ``The major negative factor was the cumulative impact of regulatory activity over the past two years.''
He said the company expects to be ``on target'' with analysts' projections by year end but conceded that the fourth quarter represents ``a significant challenge.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Philadelphia</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bell Atlantic</ENAMEX> said net rose 6.5%, aided by strong growth in the network-services business and an increase in the number of new telephone lines.
Revenue jumped 5.6% to $2.9 billion from $2.8 billion in the year-ago quarter. Revenue from financial and real-estate services jumped 23% to $177.4 million from $144.1 million a year ago. Network-access revenue from long-distance telephone companies increased 6.4% to $618.6 million.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bell Atlantic</ENAMEX> added 148,000 new telephone lines in the quarter for a total of 16.9 million.
In composite trading on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bell Atlantic</ENAMEX> closed at $100.625, up $1.50 a share.
State and local taxes increased to $131.3 million from $99.1 million a year ago. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nynex</ENAMEX> said expenses rose 4.5% to $2.73 billion from $2.61 billion, a $119 million increase. Most of the higher costs were associated with acquisitions and growth in nonregulated business units, it added.
``Our net income isn't where we would want it to be at this point,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">William C. Ferguson</ENAMEX>, chairman and chief executive officer. ``This deviation from our past growth patterns is caused largely by lower earnings at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Telephone.</ENAMEX>''
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ferguson</ENAMEX> said a continued softness in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York City</ENAMEX> area's economy and increased competition, particularly in the private-line market, took a heavy toll on earnings.
The three-month-old strike at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nynex</ENAMEX> seriously hurt the installation of new telephone lines in the quarter. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nynex</ENAMEX> said access lines in service at the end of the quarter were off 18,000 from the previous quarter, which reported an increase of 160,000 new access lines.
Revenue rose to $3.31 billion from $3.18 billion, mostly from acquisition of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AGS Computers</ENAMEX> and robust non-regulated businesses.
In <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX> composite trading yesterday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nynex</ENAMEX> common closed at $81.125, up $1.625.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Southern New England Telecommunications</ENAMEX>, which bolstered its marketing efforts for telephone and non-telephone subsidiaries, reported that net increased 8.1 %.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Walter H. Monteith Jr.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">SNET</ENAMEX> chairman and chief executive officer, said: ``Innovative marketing of our products and services contributed to increase revenue.''
Revenue and sales increased 7.5% to $423.9 million from $394.4 million a year earlier. Yellow pages advertising sales rose 11.8% to $41.2 million.
Cost and expenses for the quarter, excluding interest, increased 6.1% to $333.3 million from $314 million the year before.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">SNET</ENAMEX> common rose $1.25 to $85.50 a share yesterday in composite trading on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">San Francisco</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pacific Telesis</ENAMEX> said net declined 12.6%, primarily because of regulatory action. Revenue was about flat at $2.4 billion.
``This is a good quarter for us in terms of our business fundamentals,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Sam Ginn</ENAMEX>, chairman and chief executive officer. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pacific Telesis</ENAMEX> said new telephone lines increased 4.5% for a total of about $13.5 million for the quarter; toll calls increased 9.6% to 807 million and minutes of telephone usage increased to 9.9 billion.
In <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX> composite trading yesterday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pacific Telesis</ENAMEX> common closed at $45.50, up 87.5 cents.
