ECONOMIC GROWTH APPEARS to be leveling off, latest reports suggest. Factory orders and construction outlays were largely flat in September, while purchasing agents said manufacturing shrank further in October. Still, many economists aren't predicting a recession anytime soon.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Fed</ENAMEX> is coming under pressure to cut short-term interest rates due to the apparent slowing of the economy. But it isn't clear yet whether the central bank will make such a move.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Campbell Soup</ENAMEX> forced out its president and chief executive, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">R. Gordon Mcgovern</ENAMEX>, the strongest indication yet that the Dorrance family plans to take charge of reshaping the troubled food company. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Campbell's</ENAMEX> stock rose $3.375, to $47.125, in reaction.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Georgia Gulf</ENAMEX> received a new takeover bid from investor <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Harold Simmons</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NL Industries</ENAMEX> of $50 a share, or about $1.1 billion. The offer, which follows a $55-a-share bid that was rejected in September, steps up pressure on the chemicals concern.
The minimum-wage bill worked out by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Congress</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bush</ENAMEX> won easy approval in the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">House</ENAMEX>. The compromise plan, which boosts the minimum wage for the first time since 1981, is expected to clear the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Senate</ENAMEX> soon.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steinberg</ENAMEX> sought clearance to buy more than 15% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Air</ENAMEX>'s parent, saying he may seek control. Takeover experts said they doubted the financier would make a bid by himself.
An airline buy-out bill was approved by the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">House</ENAMEX>. The measure would make it easier for the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Transportation Department</ENAMEX> to block leveraged buy-outs in the industry.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cray Research</ENAMEX> indicated that the survival of a spinoff company, which is developing a new supercomputer, depends heavily on its chairman and chief designer, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Seymour Cray</ENAMEX>.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Treasury</ENAMEX> plans to sell $30 billion in notes and bonds next week but will delay the auction unless <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Congress</ENAMEX> quickly raises the debt ceiling.
U.S. farmers' net income rose to a record $59.9 billion last year despite one of the worst droughts ever.
Dollar: 143.80 yen, up 0.95; 1.8500 marks, up 0.0085.
