<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Financial Corp.</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Santa Barbara</ENAMEX> said it rescheduled to Nov. 29 a special shareholder meeting to vote on a $75 million stock-for-debt exchange.
The meeting had been scheduled for Nov. 10 but the company delayed the meeting to allow time for the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Securities and Exchange Commission</ENAMEX> to review the proposal.
As part of a restructuring announced earlier this year, the company proposed in August to exchange 168 newly issued common shares for each $1,000 face value of debt. However, that figure could be revised, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Financial Corp.</ENAMEX> said. Currently, the company has about six million common shares outstanding. If all the debt was converted, about 13 million new shares would be issued.
In composite trading Wednesday on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Financial Corp.</ENAMEX> closed at $1.125, unchanged.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Financial Corp.</ENAMEX> also is proposing to exchange each of its 130,000 outstanding shares of cumulative convertible preferred series A stock for two shares of common.
