<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Western Digital Corp.</ENAMEX> reported a net loss of $2.7 million, or nine cents a share, for its first quarter ended Sept. 30, citing factors as varied as hurricane damage, an advance in graphics technology and the strengthening dollar.
In the year-ago period, the company earned $12.9 million, or 45 cents a share, on sales of $247 million. Sales for the just-ended period fell to about $225 million, the maker of computer parts said.
Nonetheless, Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Roger W. Johnson</ENAMEX> said he expects the company to be profitable in the current quarter. ``We are positioned to come through,'' he said, noting that the company's backlog was up from the previous quarter. In its second quarter last year, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Western Digital</ENAMEX> earned $12.7 million, or 44 cents a share, on sales of $258.4 million.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Johnson</ENAMEX> said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Western Digital</ENAMEX>'s plant in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Puerto Rico</ENAMEX> was affected by Hurricane Hugo, losing three days' production because of the storm, which wrecked much of the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Caribbean</ENAMEX> island's infrastructure. Although the plant itself wasn't damaged, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Johnson</ENAMEX> said millions of dollars in first-quarter revenue were lost. The revenue will be regained in the current period, he added.
There are no plans to initiate a common stock dividend, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Johnson</ENAMEX> said, explaining that the board continues to believe shareholders are best served  by reinvesting excess cash.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Johnson</ENAMEX> said the first-quarter loss also heavily reflected a rapid change in graphics technology that left reseller channels with too many of the old computer graphics boards and too few new monitors compatible with the new graphics boards. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Western Digital</ENAMEX> doesn't make the monitors.
An accelerating move by personal computer manufacturers' to include advanced graphics capabilities as standard equipment further dampened reseller purchases of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Western Digital</ENAMEX>'s equipment.
``The other areas of the business -- storage and microcomputers -- were very good,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Johnson</ENAMEX> said. He said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Western Digital</ENAMEX> has reacted swiftly to the movement to video graphics array, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">VGA</ENAMEX>, graphics technology from the old enhanced graphics adapter, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">EGA</ENAMEX>, which has a lower resolution standard, technology and now is one of the leading producers of these newer units. Other makers of video controller equipment also were caught in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">EGA</ENAMEX>-<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">VGA</ENAMEX> shift, he said, ``but we were able to respond much more quickly.''
Still, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Johnson</ENAMEX> said, ``our stock is grossly undervalued.'' He said the company has cut operating expenses by about 10% over the last few quarters, while maintaining research and development at about 8% to 9% of sales.
As part of its reorganization this week, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Western Digital</ENAMEX> has divided its business into two segments -- storage products, including controllers and disk drives; and microcomputer products, which include graphics, communications and peripheral control chips.
Computer parts are getting ever smaller, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Johnson</ENAMEX> said, a shrinking that has propelled laptops into position as the fastest-growing segment of the computer business. As smaller and more powerful computers continue to be the focus of the industry, he said, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Western Digital</ENAMEX> is strengthening development of laptop parts.
