Some important people plan to gather here soon to say nice things about <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Brian P. Monieson</ENAMEX>. The occasion isn't a tribute to the former <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chicago Mercantile Exchange</ENAMEX> chairman, however, but a hearing at which federal commodity regulators hope to ban him from the futures industry.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Commodity Futures Trading Commission</ENAMEX> alleges that Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Monieson</ENAMEX> was warned that some brokers at his <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GNP Commodities Inc.</ENAMEX> were bilking investors and that he failed to stop them promptly. One of the brokers in question was one of Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Monieson</ENAMEX>'s best friends.
The case has become the most closely watched civil commodity enforcement action in recent memory, with the futures industry's top officials rallying to Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Monieson</ENAMEX>'s defense. His scheduled character witnesses at the Nov. 6 hearing include: <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.S. Agriculture</ENAMEX> Secretary <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Clayton Yeutter</ENAMEX>, who was Merc president under Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Monieson</ENAMEX>; <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Leo Melamed</ENAMEX>, chairman of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merc</ENAMEX>'s executive committee, and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Robert K. Wilmouth</ENAMEX>, president of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">National Futures Association</ENAMEX>, an industry-funded regulatory group.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Monieson</ENAMEX>'s attorney in the matter is <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jerrold E. Salzman</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merc</ENAMEX>'s influential outside counsel.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GNP</ENAMEX> brokers allegedly ``allocated'' trades, meaning they initiated futures trades without the required customer account numbers and then kept the profitable ones for themselves and stuck customers with the losers.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Monieson</ENAMEX>, a childhood math whiz and self-described computer nerd, denies these charges and expects that he and GNP will be exonerated. Noting that GNP processed some nine million trades last year, he says, ``Who the (heck) would know what's going on with 50 trades out of nine million?'' If he loses at the hearing, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Monieson</ENAMEX> can appeal to the full panel of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CFTC</ENAMEX> commissioners and then to the federal courts.
Messrs. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Melamed</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Salzman</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Wilmouth</ENAMEX> came to their friend's aid despite the fact that the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merc</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">National Futures Association</ENAMEX> brought similar failure-to-supervise charges against <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GNP</ENAMEX>, though not against Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Monieson</ENAMEX> personally.
To some, the case shows the fallacy of self-regulation, a concept the futures industry cherishes. In theory, traders and brokers will police themselves because widespread fraud would discredit the industry and frighten away investors. This ``enlightened self-interest'' is supposed to overcome the built-in conflicts of interest.
``The problem with self-regulation is always that the regulators are tinged with self-interest,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">David Ruder</ENAMEX>, the just-departed chairman of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Securities and Exchange Commission</ENAMEX>.
In this case, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ruder</ENAMEX> says, ``it would seem they're acting in two capacities -- that people of that stature would testify in a disciplinary case. One would counsel the avoidance of an appearance of a conflict.'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ruder</ENAMEX> adds of Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Yeutter</ENAMEX>: ``It seems odd that people in high government positions would intervene to testify.''
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Salzman</ENAMEX> says the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merc</ENAMEX> gave him permission to represent Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Monieson</ENAMEX>, adding there's no conflict because he has recused himself from the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merc</ENAMEX>'s case. ``I've had a long personal relationship with <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Brian</ENAMEX>,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Salzman</ENAMEX> says. ``I couldn't say no.''
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Melamed</ENAMEX> and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Wilmouth</ENAMEX> both said they see no conflict because their organizations didn't charge Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Monieson</ENAMEX> personally, and they're only testifying to his character. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Yeutter</ENAMEX> couldn't be reached for comment.
In an interview in his corner office in the Merc tower, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Monieson</ENAMEX> contends he is a victim of his own celebrity. ``The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CFTC</ENAMEX> was looking for something high-profile,'' he says.
The investigation already has been costly to Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Monieson</ENAMEX>. In January 1987, he was two weeks away from the sale of his firm for as much as $40 million. But the deal hit a snag. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal Reserve Board</ENAMEX>, which had to approve <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GNP</ENAMEX>'s sale to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Banque Indosuez</ENAMEX>, a French bank, learned of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CFTC</ENAMEX> investigation.
A distressed Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Monieson</ENAMEX> called the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CFTC</ENAMEX>, and asked its two top lawyers no fewer than five times to divulge confidential details of its probe into <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">GNP</ENAMEX>. They refused, even after Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Monieson</ENAMEX> warned that the deal's collapse would become an ``international incident'' between the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">France</ENAMEX>, according to a memo one of the lawyers wrote. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Banque Indosuez</ENAMEX> deal fell through.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Monieson</ENAMEX>, 53 years old, wears the expensive clothes of a successful trader but his mannerisms are more those of a preoccupied math professor. His office is filled with toy pigs to remind him of the fortune he made trading pork bellies. And behind his desk hangs a more recent sign of success, a futures trader's Picasso: a <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Leroy Nieman</ENAMEX> painting, depicting a horse race.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Monieson</ENAMEX>'s defense at the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CFTC</ENAMEX> hearing will partly be that he is a busy man and wasn't personally involved in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">GNP</ENAMEX>'s retail brokerage business. During his years as Merc chairman, 1983 through 1985, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Monieson</ENAMEX> played host to prime ministers and crown princes; his attorneys have prepared charts showing the many Merc meetings he attended and the time he spent away on business. The lawyers probably won't mention his interest in horse racing, though Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Monieson</ENAMEX> says it remains a hobby. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Monieson</ENAMEX>, born on <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chicago</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">North Side</ENAMEX>, by age five was a faithful reader of the <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Racing Form</ENAMEX>, regularly joining his father at the track, he says. Later, he bet the ponies with a high school friend, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Myron Rosenthal</ENAMEX>, who would become his partner in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">GNP</ENAMEX> and other ventures.
In 1965, he and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rosenthal</ENAMEX> set up what would become <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Indecon Inc.</ENAMEX>, a computer processing firm. An early offshoot was their computerized tip sheet for harness racing -- cranked out using ``the same type of equipment used in important space research and big business,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Monieson</ENAMEX> told subscribers.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Programming</ENAMEX> unexpectedly led him into trading in the early 1970s when a customer, a pork processor, commissioned a computer program on the supply and demand of bacon, but never used the program. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Monieson</ENAMEX> and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rosenthal</ENAMEX> got together $50,000 and started trading pork belly futures at the Merc based on the program's predictions.
They formed <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GNP</ENAMEX> in 1973 not out of any desire to run a futures clearing firm, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Monieson</ENAMEX> says, but because they were tired of paying brokerage commissions.
A decade later, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GNP</ENAMEX> was trading all over the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merc</ENAMEX> floor, mostly in financial futures. Yet pork bellies still held a fascination for Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Monieson</ENAMEX>, and his trading in that pit would earn him a dubious distinction: the only Merc chairman to be found guilty of committing trading violations while running the exchange.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Monieson</ENAMEX> and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rosenthal</ENAMEX> were fined, $10,000 and $70,000 respectively, for taking speculative positions beyond the exchange's limits. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rosenthal</ENAMEX>'s fine was bigger because he allegedly had exceeded position limits before.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Monieson</ENAMEX>, likening the fine to ``a parking ticket,'' says he did violate the rules but contends the position limits are set too low for today's trading environment.
Three associates held pork belly positions nearly identical to those of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GNP</ENAMEX> owners and appeared to be acting at their direction, according to an internal Merc account of the case. A company controlled by Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Monieson</ENAMEX> and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rosenthal</ENAMEX> lent the other traders more than $6.5 million to help finance the trades.
One of the associates was <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Norman Furlett</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GNP</ENAMEX> salesman and one of Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Monieson</ENAMEX>'s closest friends. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Furlett</ENAMEX>'s job was to call up investors and get them to trade futures. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GNP</ENAMEX> got a commission.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ira P. Greenspon</ENAMEX> was in the same line of work, and in October 1985 joined <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GNP</ENAMEX>. What GNP didn't know was that Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Greenspon</ENAMEX> already was under investigation by the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CFTC</ENAMEX> for alleged trade allocating at his previous firm. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CFTC</ENAMEX> later concluded that Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Furlett</ENAMEX> had been allocating trades as well.
According to separate Merc charges against the two men and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GNP</ENAMEX>, which haven't been made public, during the first two months of 1986, accounts they maintained, including one named <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Horse Trading</ENAMEX>, had profits of $62,372.95. Four customer accounts the Merc reviewed had combined losses of $20.988.12 for those months. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Robert L. Sutermeister</ENAMEX>, a retired trucking company owner in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dayton</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ohio</ENAMEX>, says he lost nearly all of the $10,000 he sent the brokers. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Larry Margler</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mckinleyville</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ca.</ENAMEX>, engineer, says he lost about $3,000 of the $5,000 he turned over to Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Furlett</ENAMEX>.
Between June 1985 and May 1986, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CFTC</ENAMEX> alleges, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Monieson</ENAMEX> was warned by at least five GNP employees that Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Furlett</ENAMEX> and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Greenspon</ENAMEX> were defrauding customers. After the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Banque Indosuez</ENAMEX> deal collapsed in January 1987, the two salesmen left <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GNP</ENAMEX>. Their attorney, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">James Koch</ENAMEX>, says they deny any wrongdoing and that both men have agreed to leave the futures industry.
