<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">France</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Banque Indosuez</ENAMEX> shocked <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX> markets by moving to become the dominant shareholder in prestigious but troubled merchant bank <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Morgan Grenfell Group PLC</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Indosuez</ENAMEX> said it has agreed to purchase <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Willis Faber PLC</ENAMEX>'s 20.4% stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Morgan Grenfell</ENAMEX>, by far the largest single holding in the bank. That would bring <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Indosuez</ENAMEX>'s total stake to 24.8%, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Indosuez</ENAMEX> said.
While awaiting <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bank of England</ENAMEX> permission to pass the 15% mark, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Indosuez</ENAMEX> said, it has agreed to purchase immediately a 10.5% share in the bank for 410 pence ($6.62) a share, bringing its stake to 14.9%. It then intends to acquire the remaining <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Willis</ENAMEX> stake at 462 pence a share. The transaction still must be cleared by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Willis</ENAMEX> shareholders.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Morgan Grenfell</ENAMEX> shares jumped 38 pence to 400 pence on <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX>'s stock exchange.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Indosuez</ENAMEX> said it has agreed that, barring a major change in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Morgan Grenfell</ENAMEX>'s situation, it won't launch a full takeover bid for at least a year. But despite signs that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Morgan Grenfell</ENAMEX> staff was unhappy at the sudden investment, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Indosuez</ENAMEX> Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Antoine Jeancourt-Galignani</ENAMEX> said he will begin linking the two banks into ``an important merchant banking group in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Europe</ENAMEX>.''
In a telephone interview, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Morgan Grenfell</ENAMEX> Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John Craven</ENAMEX> said the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Indosuez</ENAMEX> holding ``wasn't one that was taken at our initiative,'' adding that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Morgan Grenfell</ENAMEX> ``remains perfectly confident in the future of our business as an independent entity.''
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Craven</ENAMEX> added he held ``important discussions'' yesterday with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Indosuez</ENAMEX> officials about the possible benefits of a combination, and that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Morgan Grenfell</ENAMEX>'s attitude ``is entirely objective.'' He added: ``My understanding of what I have heard is that their intentions are very long term. I guess if they get to 25%'' <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Morgan Grenfell</ENAMEX> would be a troublesome target for another counterbidder, he added.
In a statement, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Morgan Grenfell</ENAMEX> said it now seeks further clarification of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Indosuez</ENAMEX>'s intentions.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jeancourt-Galignani</ENAMEX> refused to say whether <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Indosuez</ENAMEX> will bid for all of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Morgan Grenfell</ENAMEX> when its year is up. If it does, the operation would be one of the largest foreign purchases of a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.K</ENAMEX> merchant bank. It would catapult Indosuez from the position of a marginal <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX> player, with strong Asian and Middle Eastern activities, to the upper levels of the U.K. merchant banking scene. It is part of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Indosuez</ENAMEX>'s overall plan of building its business across <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Europe</ENAMEX>, as the 1992 reduction of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">European Community</ENAMEX> market barriers looms.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jeancourt-Galignani</ENAMEX> said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Indosuez</ENAMEX> had to move fast because it feared that another investor -- widely rumored to be <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Deutsche Bank</ENAMEX> -- was buying shares heavily. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Indosuez</ENAMEX> said it believes <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Deutsche Bank</ENAMEX> currently has a 4.9% stake, but it refused to say who it believed was buying. It said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Deutsche Bank</ENAMEX> is the largest other holding it knows of.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Indosuez</ENAMEX> completed the purchase in just two weeks, and market sentiment is that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Indosuez</ENAMEX>'s rush led it to pay a high price, but French analysts tended to welcome the investment.
``The logic is that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Indosuez</ENAMEX> is a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">French</ENAMEX> investment bank with a lot of market activities, but not a lot of fund management,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Romain Burnand</ENAMEX>, a financial analyst at <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Paris</ENAMEX> brokerage <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cholet-Dupont & Cie</ENAMEX>.
He said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Morgan Grenfell</ENAMEX> manages about # 7 billion pounds ($11.3 billion) in investment funds. ``It is a force in the market and has a very good international image,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Burnand</ENAMEX> said. ``The problem is that executives are volatile. They can leave when they are unhappy.
