The bad news in the junk bond market yesterday was that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">TW Services</ENAMEX>, a group of restaurant chains, became the latest prospective issuer to get a cold shoulder from bond buyers.
The good news -- to fans of stable credit, at least -- is what the rejection says about the state of mind of junk buyers. Apparently they are learning to say no to excess risk.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coniston Partners</ENAMEX>, which with related entities controls 80% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">TW</ENAMEX>, had been planning to sell $1.15 billion of junk bonds, among other things to finance their acquisition of the remaining public shares.
Until recently, such buy-now, pray-for-growth-later deals were routine. ``But people don't buy anything on expectation anymore,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jack Utter</ENAMEX>, who manages the high-yield fund of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IDS Financial Services</ENAMEX>. ``Investors,'' he adds, ``are getting religion.'' The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">TW</ENAMEX> buy-out may yet be financed. ``There is nothing wrong with the company,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coniston</ENAMEX> principal <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Paul Tierney</ENAMEX>. The rub, he says, is that ``the junk market isn't as deep'' as before. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">TW</ENAMEX>'s stockholder meeting was postponed from tomorrow to Nov. 21. By then, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">DLJ</ENAMEX> hopes to be able to sell less-junky junk bonds.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Gollust, Tierney & Oliver</ENAMEX> is likely to contribute more than the $120 million in equity it had planned on. Banks may contribute more senior debt. And the total amount of junk financing will be reduced.
A <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">DLJ</ENAMEX> banker, putting a best possible face on it, asserts that ``very few people said they didn't like the credit quality. People said they didn't think a billion-dollar deal would trade.''
But trading risk stems from credit risk. And by adding equity, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">DLJ</ENAMEX> would seem to be acknowledging that credit risk was a concern. Indeed, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">DLJ</ENAMEX> banker says, in the reborn capital structure cash coverage of interest ``will meaningfully improve.'' As he sums it up: ``We are listening to the market.''
What is it, to borrow a term from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coniston</ENAMEX>, that so unsettled the market? Some of the same risks that were cited -- and seemingly ignored -- in dozens of previous junk offerings.
But such calculations ignore the noncash charge of depreciation, taken to allow for the gradual wearing out of french friers, deterioration of stores and the like. In fact, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">DLJ</ENAMEX> says, the company envisions capital expenses of about $180 million a year.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">TW</ENAMEX>'s pitch was that sales and earnings at its restaurants have risen steadily and that people won't stop eating during a downturn. But they won't necessarily eat at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Denny</ENAMEX>'s. The fast-food business is ``intensely competitive,'' notes <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Wertheim Schroder</ENAMEX> analyst <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John Rohs</ENAMEX>. Prospective bond buyers noted that TW historically has prospered because it has been willing to spend aggressively on remodeling restaurants and redoing menus.
The prospectus notes ``there can be no assurance'' that future growth will continue at past levels. In the recent past, bond buyers didn't seek such assurance. Now, apparently, they do.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">TW Services</ENAMEX>
(<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NYSE</ENAMEX>; Symbol: <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">TW</ENAMEX>)
Third quarter, Sept. 30, 1989:
