Hit by higher costs and lower sales, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Caterpillar Inc.</ENAMEX> said third-quarter earnings tumbled 43% and full-year earnings will trail last year's results.
In announcing a 1989 capital spending plan of $950 million early this year, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Caterpillar</ENAMEX> said full-year earnings would be flat compared with last year's $616 million, or $6.07 a share. But yesterday, the company said this year's profit will be lower. It didn't say by how much.
Suffering from a downturn in heavy truck production that cut orders for its engines, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Caterpillar</ENAMEX> also said it will indefinitely lay off about 325 workers in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Peoria</ENAMEX> area and temporarily shut its plant in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">York</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Pa.</ENAMEX>, for two weeks in both November and December.
