<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chambers Development Co.</ENAMEX> said its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Security Bureau Inc.</ENAMEX> unit purchased two security concerns in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Florida</ENAMEX> that will add $2.1 million of annual revenue.
Purchase of the businesses serving <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Miami</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Fort Lauderdale</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">West Palm Beach</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Fla.</ENAMEX>, is part of a plan by Chambers to expand in the growing security industry. Terms weren't disclosed.
