<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate Inc.</ENAMEX>, which has rejected an $18-a-share tender offer by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones & Co.</ENAMEX> for the 33% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX> that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> doesn't already own, said the two companies began talks yesterday to try to negotiate a friendly transaction.
However, the talks didn't produce any changes in the $576 million <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> offer, which a committee of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX>'s two independent directors has rejected as inadequate.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peter Skinner</ENAMEX>, vice president and corporate general counsel for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX>, said yesterday's talks took place both on the telephone and in person. ``We discussed the bid, but <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> and its board of directors believe the bid is full and fair,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Skinner</ENAMEX> said. He said no future talks are currently scheduled, but added that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> representatives will meet again with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX> officials if <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX> seeks a meeting.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX> disclosed the opening of negotiations in a filing with the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Securities and Exchange Commission</ENAMEX>, which said that ``there can be no assurance that such negotiations will continue or will result in revised terms that will be satisfactory to the special committee.''
The talks followed an effort by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX> to place a strongly worded advertisement attacking the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> offer in yesterday's editions of The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Wall Street Journal</ENAMEX>, according to two people familiar with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX>.
After <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX> submitted its ad to the Journal Wednesday, the people said, a lawyer for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> telephoned a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX> lawyer. Soon thereafter, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Warren H. Phillips</ENAMEX>, chairman of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX>, telephoned <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Neil S. Hirsch</ENAMEX>, chairman of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate.</ENAMEX> As a result of the conversations, the people said, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX> decided not to run the ad yesterday, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> agreed to meet with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX>.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Skinner</ENAMEX> said that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> executives had been told that the ad would be submitted by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX> and were advised of its content. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> executives indicated to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX> executives that such an ad would not be ``helpful,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Skinner</ENAMEX> said, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX> decided not to run the ad.
A spokesman for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX> declined to elaborate on <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX>'s filing with the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">SEC</ENAMEX>.
Many of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Wall Street</ENAMEX>'s takeover-stock speculators bought relatively large positions in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX> stock after <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> announced its tender offer on Sept. 21. The traders are betting <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> will increase its $18-a-share offer in order to acquire full ownership of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX>, an electronic distributor of financial-market information.
Several takeover stock traders said yesterday they expect <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> to offer at least $21. Some analysts, investment bankers and institutional investors who have studied <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX> have said they believe the company could fetch between $25 and $30 a share if it were put up for auction.
But the takeover stock traders, who declined to be identified, said they believe it is unrealistic to expect <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> will pay that much, considering it already owns about 67% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bruce Thorp</ENAMEX>, an analyst at <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Philadelphia</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Provident National Bank</ENAMEX>, said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX>'s tender offer reflects a typical premium for the purchase of a remaining minority stake. He thinks <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> will end up paying $20 or $21 a share for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX>.
``The offer will be sweetened, not because it has to be, but because it will make for a smoother transaction,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Thorp</ENAMEX> said. ``<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> could bludgeon its way through the process and get it for less, but they won't do that. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> is not going to squeeze as hard as it could.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> declined to comment on Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Thorp</ENAMEX>'s speculation.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX>'s proposed ad, headlined ``What Now, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX>?'' was in the form of a letter to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> directors. ``How can a company of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX>'s reputation persist in a coercive attempt to squeeze out the minority shareholders of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX> at a low-ball price of $18 a share?'' the ad asked. A copy of the ad was obtained from a person familiar with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX>.
``We are forced to consider <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX>'s actions as hostile -- to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX>'s shareholders, management, and employees,'' the ad said. It was signed by Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hirsch</ENAMEX>, three other <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX> directors who are employees of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX>, and two outside directors.
People familiar with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX> said the ad was intended to encourage <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> to begin negotiations and was submitted to the Journal for that reason. ``We could have run it in the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Times</ENAMEX>,'' one person familiar with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX> said.
As evidence of their contention that the current <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> offer is too low, takeover-stock speculators pointed to an <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">SEC</ENAMEX> filing by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> disclosing that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> managers had proposed offering $19 a share for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX>. However, that proposal was overruled by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX>'s board, which decided to offer $18 a share.
After the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX> special committee rejected the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> offer as inadequate, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Phillips</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> said, ``We are proceeding with our $18-a-share offer and continue to believe that the offer is fair to all <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX> stockholders.'' The offer is scheduled to expire Nov. 3.
Separately, a hearing is scheduled for Monday in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Delaware</ENAMEX> Chancery Court on a motion by certain <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX> shareholders seeking a court order to block the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> tender offer.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> paid between $10 and $15 a share for most of the 63.6 million <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX> shares it owns. The shares were purchased in various transactions, starting in August 1985. However, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> paid $28.75 a share for one block of about 10.5 million <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX> shares in September 1987. That price represented a premium of 16.8% above the then-market price of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX> shares.
