<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">National Medical Enterprises Inc.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Los Angeles</ENAMEX>, said the completion of the spinoff of its long-term care operations will be delayed until early next year because of regulatory complexities.
The health-care services concern announced the spinoff plan last January, then revised it in May and said it hoped to complete it by Nov. 30. But the process involves relicensing and other transfers for about 360 separate nursing-home facilities in more than 30 states, the company said, adding that it now plans for the transaction to be completed by Feb. 28.
The new company, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hillhaven Corp.</ENAMEX>, is expected to have about $150 million in equity, a 2-1 debt-to-equity ratio and to be 10%-owned by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NME</ENAMEX>.
