The authority will issue a total of $446.5 million of pollution-control revenue bonds. Proceeds of the sale will go to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Centerior</ENAMEX>'s operating subsidiaries to finance the projects, located at a nuclear unit located near <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Cleveland</ENAMEX>.
The bonds will be issued for a term of 34 years at an interest rate of 8%. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Goldman, Sachs & Co.</ENAMEX> is the underwriter.
