<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Stateswest Airlines</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Phoenix</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ariz.</ENAMEX>, said it sent a more detailed merger proposal to much-larger <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mesa Airlines</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Farmington</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.M.</ENAMEX>-based Mesa has consistently rejected <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Stateswest</ENAMEX>'s offers, and early this week said its board wouldn't give the proposal further consideration, calling it ``vague and ill-defined'' because it didn't describe the source of funds or the specific terms of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Stateswest</ENAMEX> securities which were part of the offer.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Stateswest</ENAMEX> asked Mesa to repond by Oct. 31. Mesa President <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Larry Risley</ENAMEX> said his board had received <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Stateswest</ENAMEX>'s most recent offer and was reviewing it.
