<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hercules Inc.</ENAMEX> put its ``nominally profitable'' <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Electronic & Printing Products</ENAMEX> subsidiary on the auction block, saying the unit doesn't fit in with the diversified chemical company's recent change in strategic goals.
Earlier this year, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hercules</ENAMEX> decided to sell its peripheral businesses and concentrate its resources on its core chemical businesses, including advanced materials and food ingredients. The electronic and printing unit, which has annual sales of about $80 million, is the first unit to be sold under the restructuring.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hercules</ENAMEX>, based in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Wilmington</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Del.</ENAMEX>, said it has received ``numerous unsolicited inquiries'' over the last 18 months about the unit's availability. It is seeking a buyer who will run the business under current management and ``whose strategy is to maintain strong growth.''
The subsidiary produces materials used in printing and in the fabrication of printed circuit boards.
