The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">White House</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Senate Intelligence Committee</ENAMEX> agreed on new rules for covert operations that will give President <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bush</ENAMEX> a freer hand to involve the U.S. in coup plots in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Panama</ENAMEX> and elsewhere.
Based on assurances from the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">White House</ENAMEX>, the committee agreed to rescind <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Reagan</ENAMEX>-era restrictions and give U.S. operatives wide latitude to participate in planning foreign coups, according to committee officials.
In particular, the Bush administration will no longer be bound by a controversial legal interpretation put in place last year that could have required notifying dictators in advance of coup plots that might endanger their lives. Instead, the officials said, an executive order barring assassinations would be considered satisfied as long as U.S. agents stay away from coup plots that have assassinations as their explicit goal.
``We start with a clean slate,'' said one official familiar with the pact.
The agreement was disclosed last night after the panel approved separate intelligence legislation and held a closed hearing regarding Panama with officials from the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Central Intelligence Agency</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">State Department</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pentagon</ENAMEX>.
The legislation also contains significant compromises that have the effect of giving Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bush</ENAMEX> more leeway in covert actions. The panel dropped a plan to require 48-hour notice of covert acts, and it voted to permit the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CIA</ENAMEX> to use a contingency fund to launch covert acts.
In return, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bush</ENAMEX> is sending Congress a letter pledging to notify the committee in advance of nearly all covert acts, but reserving the right to delay notification in some cases until a few days after the operations are launched, and in rare cases, to take longer.
In addition, the administration promised to put into writing all presidential intelligence decisions, called ``findings.'' And the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CIA</ENAMEX> reluctantly agreed to accept a more independent internal inspector's office than now exists.
