<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Banco Popular</ENAMEX> de <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Puerto Rico</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Banponce Corp.</ENAMEX> -- agreed to merge in a transaction valued at $324 million.
Under the agreement, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Banponce</ENAMEX> stockholders will be able to exchange each of their shares for either shares in the new entity or cash. In each case, the exchange is valued at $56.25 a share.
The two companies, both based in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">San Juan</ENAMEX>, will form a bank holding company with assets of just over $9 billion. The holding company will be called <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Banponce Corp.</ENAMEX> The primary subsidiary will be the combined banking operations of the two companies and will be known as <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Banco Popular</ENAMEX> de <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Puerto Rico</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rafael Carrion Jr.</ENAMEX>, chairman of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Banco Popular</ENAMEX>, will be the chairman of the holding company. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Alberto M. Paracchini</ENAMEX>, currently chairman of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Banponce</ENAMEX>, will serve as president of the bank holding company and chairman of the subsidiary.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Banco Popular</ENAMEX> originally proposed the merger in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">July</ENAMEX>, in a cash and stock transaction valued at $50 a share, or about $293 million. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Banponce</ENAMEX> reacted cooly at first, but appeared to be won over, analysts said, by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Banco Popular</ENAMEX>'s assurances that it wanted only a friendly transaction.
``Banco Popular just kept waiting,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Edward Thompson</ENAMEX>, a vice president and analyst at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Thomson Bankwatch Inc.</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>. ``They got a transaction that's good for both companies.''
The two banks appear to be a good fit. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Banponce</ENAMEX> caters to a more affluent customer, while <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Banco Popular</ENAMEX> has always had a large presence among middle-income and lower-income markets. The merger should also allow the companies to reduce costs by combining operations in many locations in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Puerto Rico</ENAMEX>. ``They're often right across the street from one another,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Thompson</ENAMEX> said.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Richard Carrion</ENAMEX>, who is currently president and chief executive officer of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Banco Popular</ENAMEX>, said the merger will result in a ``larger and stronger locally based bank.'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Carrion</ENAMEX>, who will now serve as president and chief executive officer of the subsidiary bank, added: ``We'll be able to better compete with large foreign banks. It makes sense from a strategic standpoint.''
The newly merged company will have 165 branches in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Puerto Rico</ENAMEX> and 27 branches outside of the island. The banks said they don't expect the merger to face any regulatory hurdles. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Carrion</ENAMEX> said the merger should be completed in six to nine months.
