<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Sebastian Guzman Cabrera</ENAMEX> took over the oil workers union, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mexico</ENAMEX>'s most powerful labor organization, only last January. But even in that short time Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guzman Cabrera</ENAMEX> has become as controversial in his own way as his deposed predecessor, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Joaquin Hernandez Galicia</ENAMEX>, known as <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">La Quina</ENAMEX>.
In recent contract negotiations with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pemex</ENAMEX> management, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guzman Cabrera</ENAMEX> accepted major concessions that greatly curtail the union's role in subcontracting, long a source of millions of dollars in illicit earnings. And with the quiet pragmatism of Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guzman Cabrera</ENAMEX> replacing the prickly populism of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">La Quina</ENAMEX>, government technocrats have been given a free hand to open the petrochemical sector to wider private and foreign investment.
The 61-year-old Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guzman Cabrera</ENAMEX> takes such criticisms in stride. ``This isn't a new kind of union leadership, it's a new <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mexico</ENAMEX>. We're no longer afraid of associating with private or foreign capital,'' he says.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pemex</ENAMEX>, which produces 40% of government revenue, desperately needs new investment. Since world oil prices collapsed in 1982, the government has siphoned <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pemex</ENAMEX>'s coffers to make payments on <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mexico</ENAMEX>'s $97 billion foreign debt. Little money has been returned to upgrade <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pemex</ENAMEX>'s aging facilities. While the government drains <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pemex</ENAMEX> from above, the union has drained it from below. A bloated payroll and pervasive graft caused <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pemex</ENAMEX>'s operating costs to balloon to 95 cents of each $1 in sales, far above the industry norm.
Though he also long benefited from the system built by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">La Quina</ENAMEX>, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guzman Cabrera</ENAMEX> says union perks had simply gotten out of hand. They are ``at the base of all of the problems of corruption,'' he says.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pemex</ENAMEX>'s customers also are pleased with the company's new spirit. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Grupo Desc</ENAMEX>, a big conglomerate, has long depended on <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pemex</ENAMEX> petrochemicals to produce plastic packing material. But when the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pemex</ENAMEX> plant shut down for an annual overhaul, it would never give notice to its customers. ``The capriciousness would completely disrupt our operations,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ernesto Vega Velasco</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Desc</ENAMEX>'s finance director. This year, for the first time, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Desc</ENAMEX> and other customers were consulted well in advance of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pemex</ENAMEX> plant's shutdown to ensure minimal inconvenience.
Taming the union complements previous moves by the government to attract private investment in petrochemicals, which <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mexico</ENAMEX> has been forced to import in large quantities in recent years. In May, the government unveiled new foreign investment regulations that create special trusts allowing foreigners, long limited to a 40% stake in secondary petrochemical companies, to own up to 100%. Later, the government reclassified several basic petrochemicals as secondary products.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guzman Cabrera</ENAMEX> and government officials insist that foreigners will be limited to investing in secondary petroleum products. But the new union leader makes no apologies for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pemex</ENAMEX>'s more outward-looking attitude. ``If we do not integrate into this new world of interdependence, sooner or later we're going to become victims of our own isolation,'' he says.
