<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MORGAN STANLEY</ENAMEX>, THE ONCE <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">STODGY</ENAMEX> investment house, in 1974 helped a corporate client complete a hostile takeover. It was the start of a boom in unfriendly, even ungentlemanly, mergers.
On July 18, 1974, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">International Nickle</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Canada</ENAMEX> -- advised by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Morgan</ENAMEX> -- offered $28 a share, equal to $157 million, for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ESB</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Philadelphia</ENAMEX> battery maker. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ESB</ENAMEX> said it was given only a three-hour advance warning on a ``take it or leave it'' basis from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Inco</ENAMEX>, as the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Toronto</ENAMEX> company is called.
``<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ESB</ENAMEX> is aware that a hostile tender offer is being made by a foreign company for all of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ESB</ENAMEX>'s shares,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">F.J. Port</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ESB</ENAMEX>'s president. ``Hostile'' thus entered the merger-acquisition lexicon. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Joseph Flom</ENAMEX>, of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Skadden</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Arps</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Slote</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Meagher & Flom</ENAMEX>, which became a leading legal firm in merger cases, said the case ``made takeovers respectable.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ESB</ENAMEX> spurned <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Inco</ENAMEX> and within five days <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ESB</ENAMEX> had a ``white knight'' as <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">United Aircraft</ENAMEX> -- headed by <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Harry Gray</ENAMEX>, a shrewdly friendly acquirer of companies -- offered $34 a share. Gray was advised by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Goldman Sachs</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merrill Lynch.</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ESB</ENAMEX> directors warmly accepted, but a whirlwind bidding match ensued. Within a few days in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">July</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Inco</ENAMEX> raised its bid to $36 and United matched it. On a single day Inco lifted its offer to $38 and then to $41, equal to $225.5 million. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United</ENAMEX> met the $38 but then withdrew.
ESB on July 29 accepted the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Inco</ENAMEX> offer and the brief battle -- unlike the intricate and lengthy big takeovers of 1984-1989 -- was over. The new gritty game became a money maker for <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Wall Street</ENAMEX>'s once austere old-name houses. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Inco</ENAMEX> paid <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Morgan</ENAMEX> an advisory fee of about $250,000, a paltry figure by today's measures. Early this year <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Morgan</ENAMEX> and three other investment houses each received $25 million in advisory fees from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Kohlberg Kravis & Roberts</ENAMEX> in its $25 billion friendly buy-out of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">RJR Nabisco.</ENAMEX>
