Nashua immediately responded by strengthening a poison-pill plan and saying it will buy back up to one million of its shares, or 10.4% of the 9.6 million outstanding.
Previously, an affiliate of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Unicorp Canada</ENAMEX> disclosed a stake of less than 5% in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Nashua</ENAMEX>, according to <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Daniel M. Junius</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Nashua</ENAMEX>'s treasurer.
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Nashua</ENAMEX>'s stock has fluctuated sharply on takeover speculation, rising to a high for the year of $42.875 a share in June from $29.75 in March. But the company has had weak results so far this year, with earnings declining 43% to $13.7 million, or $1.43 a share, on a 4% decline in revenue to $713.5 million through the first nine months of the year.
Its stock has slumped recently, closing unchanged Friday at $29 a share in composite trading on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX>; at that price, the company has a market value of about $278.4 million. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nashua</ENAMEX> announced the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Reiss</ENAMEX> request after the market closed.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Junius</ENAMEX> said <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Nashua</ENAMEX>'s ``intention is to remain an independent public company.'' The company said it amended its shareholder rights plan by reducing to 10% from 20% the level of ownership by an outsider that would trigger the issuance to other holders of rights to buy additional shares of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nashua</ENAMEX> common at half price.
In addition, the company's board authorized the purchase of up to an additional one million shares. Under a program approved by the company in 1987 that didn't specify a share amount, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Nashua</ENAMEX> had purchased 481,000 shares through Sept. 29.
