<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CMS Enhancements Inc.</ENAMEX> said it estimates that sales and earnings for the fiscal first quarter ended Sept. 30 fell somewhat from the year-earlier period.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jim Farooquee</ENAMEX>, chief executive officer of the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tustin</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Calif.</ENAMEX>, computer accessories supplier, said he was ``comfortable'' with analysts' expectations that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CMS</ENAMEX> would earn between six cents and eight cents a share on revenue of about $42 million.
A year earlier, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CMS</ENAMEX> posted profit of $1.1 million, or 13 cents a share, on sales of $48 million. This time, there are 30% more shares outstanding.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Farooquee</ENAMEX> attributed the decline to an industrywide softening of demand for computer enhancement products.
