With airline deals in a tailspin, legendary Wall Street trader <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Michael Steinhardt</ENAMEX> could have trouble parachuting out of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Usair Group</ENAMEX>, traders say.
Only a week ago, when airline buy-out fever was already winding down, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steinhardt</ENAMEX> was engaged in a duel with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Usair</ENAMEX>. He was threatening to take over the carrier, after spending an estimated $167 million to build an 8.4% Usair stake for his investment clients. The would-be raider even hired an investment banker to give teeth to his takeover threat, which was widely interpreted as an effort to flush out an acquirer for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Usair</ENAMEX>, or for his own stake.
In fighting <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Usair</ENAMEX>, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steinhardt</ENAMEX> was pitted against another investor, billionnaire <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Warren Buffett</ENAMEX>, who bought into Usair to help fend off Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steinhardt</ENAMEX>. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Buffett</ENAMEX>'s firm, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Berkshire Hathaway</ENAMEX>, holds a much bigger stake in the carrier than Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steinhardt</ENAMEX>'s firm, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Steinhardt Partners</ENAMEX>.
``It doesn't make sense to parachute out at this price,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steinhardt</ENAMEX> says, though he has stopped his takeover talk and now commends <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Usair</ENAMEX> managers' ``operating skills.''
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steinhardt</ENAMEX>, who runs about $1.7 billion for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Steinhardt Partners</ENAMEX>, made his name as a gunslinging trader, moving in and out of stocks with agility -- enriching himself and his investment clients. Meanwhile, his big losses, for instance in 1987's crash, generally have been trading losses.
``Long-term investing -- that's not <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steinhardt</ENAMEX>'s style,'' chuckles an investor who once worked at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Steinhardt Partners</ENAMEX>. ``He doesn't usually risk that much unless he thinks he has an ace in the hole,'' adds another <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Steinhardt Partners</ENAMEX> alumnus.
In recent days, traders say <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Usair</ENAMEX> has been buying its own shares, as part of a program to retire about eight million <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Usair</ENAMEX> shares, though the carrier won't discuss its buy-back program.
If <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Usair</ENAMEX> stepped up its share purchases, that might be a way for Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steinhardt</ENAMEX> to get out, says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Timothy Pettee</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merrill Lynch</ENAMEX> analyst. But <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Usair</ENAMEX> might not want to help Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steinhardt</ENAMEX>, he adds.
In 1987, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Usair</ENAMEX> Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Edwin Colodny</ENAMEX> stonewalled when <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Trans World Airlines</ENAMEX> Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Carl Icahn</ENAMEX> threatened to take over the carrier. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Icahn</ENAMEX>, a much more practiced raider than Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steinhardt</ENAMEX>, eventually sold a big <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Usair</ENAMEX> stake at a tiny profit through Bear, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Stearns.</ENAMEX> Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steinhardt</ENAMEX> also could take that route. He confers big trading commissions on Wall Street firms. However, with airline stocks cratering, he might not get a very good price for his shares, traders say.
Especially galling for Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steinhardt</ENAMEX>, say people close to him, is that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Usair</ENAMEX>'s Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Colodny</ENAMEX> won't even take his telephone calls. While <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Usair</ENAMEX> isn't considered absolutely takeover-proof, its defenses, including the sale in August of a 12% stake in the company to Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Buffett</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Berkshire Hathaway</ENAMEX>, are pretty strong.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Usair</ENAMEX>'s deal with Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Buffett</ENAMEX> ``wasn't exactly a shining example of shareholder democracy,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steinhardt</ENAMEX> says. Since last April, the investor has made seven so-called 13D filings in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Usair</ENAMEX>, as he bought and sold the company's stock. Such disclosures of big holdings often are used by raiders to try to scare a company's managers, and to stir interest in the stock. But of course it would be highly unusual for an investment fund such as <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Steinhardt Partners</ENAMEX> to take over a company.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Usair</ENAMEX> and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Buffett</ENAMEX> won't talk about Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steinhardt</ENAMEX> at all.
Analysts say <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Usair</ENAMEX> has great promise. By the second half of 1990, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Usair</ENAMEX> stock could hit 60, says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Helane Becker</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Shearson Lehman Hutton.</ENAMEX> She thinks traders should buy the stock if it tumbles to 35.
But meanwhile, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Usair</ENAMEX> is expected to show losses or lackluster profit for several quarters as it tries to digest <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Piedmont Airlines</ENAMEX>, which it acquired. Moreover, some investors think a recession or renewed airfare wars will pummel airline stocks in coming months.
However, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steinhardt</ENAMEX> says he's ``comfortable holding Usair as an investment.'' While he has bought and sold some <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Usair</ENAMEX> shares in recent days, he says that contrary to rumors, he hasn't tried to unload his holding. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steinhardt</ENAMEX> adds that he bought <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Usair</ENAMEX> stock earlier this year as ``part of a fundamental investment in the airline group.''
In 1989, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steinhardt</ENAMEX> says he made money trading in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Texas Air</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AMR</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX>. Overall, his investments so far this year are showing gains of about 20%, he adds.
Does Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steinhardt</ENAMEX> regret his incursion into the takeover-threat game? People close to the investor say that was an experiment he is unlikely to repeat. ``I don't think you'll find I'm making a radical change in my traditional investment style,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steinhardt</ENAMEX> says.
