The hottest rivalry in the computer industry intensified sharply yesterday as <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Digital Equipment Corp.</ENAMEX> announced its first line of mainframe computers, targeting <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">International Business Machines Corp.</ENAMEX>'s largest market.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IBM</ENAMEX> fired back with new mainframes of its own, extending the long-dominant 3090 line with a 7% to 14% power boost.
Up to now, the intense competition between <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IBM</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Digital</ENAMEX> has been confined largely to the broad midrange of the computer market, where <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Digital</ENAMEX> sought to exploit <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IBM</ENAMEX>'s weaknesses in networking. But <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Digital</ENAMEX>'s move into mainframes will target <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IBM</ENAMEX>'s home turf, where it has a commanding 70% share of the market.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Digital</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Maynard</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mass.</ENAMEX>, insisted yesterday that its marketing focus would differ sharply from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IBM</ENAMEX>'s. ``This is not your father's mainframe,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Allan Mcguire</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Digital</ENAMEX> spokesman. ``It's a whole new generation,'' he said.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IBM</ENAMEX> said the 16 new <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">J</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">JH</ENAMEX> models will generally be available immediately, though three won't ship until the third quarter of next year. Prices on the larger models, which range as high as $13 million, generally won't change. Small models, whose performance increased as much as 46%, will carry higher prices. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Upgrades</ENAMEX> to bigger models also will be costlier.
Analysts have predicted strong pent-up demand for the new line among <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Digital</ENAMEX>'s customers. Large Digital buyers say the new <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">VAX</ENAMEX> will let them stay with Digital when they need the power of a mainframe, instead of turning to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IBM</ENAMEX>. ``I'm convinced there's a huge market for this machine,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stephen Smith</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Painewebber Inc.</ENAMEX>
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Digital</ENAMEX> also plans to compete fiercely with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IBM</ENAMEX> when the giant's customers are computerizing new aspects of their businesses. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Digital</ENAMEX>, however, doesn't expect to displace <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IBM</ENAMEX> mainframes that are already installed at big companies.
In addition to commercial markets, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Digital</ENAMEX>'s new line targets the low end of the engineering and scientific supercomputer market, when it's packaged with an optional supercharger, known as a vector processor.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Digital</ENAMEX>'s push into mainframes comes at a time when its mainstay minicomputer line is under growing pressure from smaller personal computers and workstations that operate on standard operating systems rather than on the proprietary systems that older minicomputers use. Although <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Digital</ENAMEX> has staked out a major presence in the booming workstation market, profit margins in that market are much slimmer than for mainframes.
``Demand for these systems has been very, very strong,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bill Grabe</ENAMEX>, a senior <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IBM</ENAMEX> marketing executive. ``We have a good strong backlog for the fourth quarter even without'' the systems that were announced yesterday.
But the 3090 line is nearly five years old -- which is getting up there in mainframe years -- and its growth is expected to slow in 1990.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IBM</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Armonk</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.Y.</ENAMEX>, said it wanted to bring out the mainframes as soon as it could to spark as many sales as possible by the end of the year. The fourth quarter is always <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IBM</ENAMEX>'s biggest by far, with most sales coming in December as customers seek to use budgets before year end.
Still, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steve Cohen</ENAMEX>, an analyst at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Soundview Financial Group Inc.</ENAMEX>, said, ``I don't see that this will be sufficient to give <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IBM</ENAMEX> a significant kick in the fourth quarter.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IBM</ENAMEX> has already indicated it will have problems in the quarter, partly because of a delay in shipping a high-end disk drive and partly because the strong dollar will cut significantly the value of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IBM</ENAMEX>'s overseas earnings when translated into dollars. Some analysts have estimated <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IBM</ENAMEX>'s fourth-quarter per-share earnings will fall 10% to $3.57 a share from $3.97 a share a year earlier.
In addition to the new mainframe hardware and software, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IBM</ENAMEX> announced a magnetic-tape system for data storage that it said occupies half as much floor space as older systems but can store five times as much data on a single cartridge. That should help <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IBM</ENAMEX> address the damage that a resurgent <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Storage Technology Corp.</ENAMEX> has inflicted in that market.
