<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tokyo</ENAMEX> stocks closed easier for the second consecutive day, finishing at the intraday low on index-linked investment trust fund selling toward the end of the afternoon session. Stocks rose in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX>, but fell again in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Frankfurt</ENAMEX>.
On Wednesday, the market opened bullishly with high turnover, ignoring the volatility in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> stocks. But losers were spread in a broad range by the end of the session. A trader said that the more an issue gained recently, the sharper the loss sustained Wednesday.
A trader at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Yamaichi Securities</ENAMEX> said the market's mood was undercut by the continuing fall of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nippon Telegraph & Telephone</ENAMEX> shares, which declined to their lowest level since the begining of this year. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NTT</ENAMEX> lost 30,000 yen to 1,380,000 yen ($9,756).
Some traders noted individual investors dumped <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NTT</ENAMEX> shares amid growing expectation for a division of the company as suggested by a recent government-sponsored panel.
Dealers said they also took profits to reduce holdings in their own account at the end of the October transaction period.
Other losing issues included <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Showa Shell</ENAMEX>, which fell 40 to 1,520. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Toyota Motor</ENAMEX> fell 40 to 2,680.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sekisui House</ENAMEX>, which gained 150 Tuesday, lost 70 to 2640. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Daiwa House</ENAMEX> also ended easier, but Misawa Home was firmer.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pioneer Electronic</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony</ENAMEX>, both of which dominated buying earlier this month, continued to fall Wednesday. Pioneer was down 90 at 5,810, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony</ENAMEX> lost 40 to 8,550, down 10% from its record set Oct. 11.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Financial Times</ENAMEX> 100-share index finished at 2161.9, up 12.6 points. The 30-share index ended 12.6 points higher at 1751.9. Volume was thin at 374.6 million shares traded, down from 405.4 million Tuesday.
Dealers said the market gained some late steam on a flurry of buying by market-makers looking at blue-chip issues and stocks viewed as oversold during the market's recent downtrend.
Outside what essentially amounted to a bookkeeping exercise, dealers said <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX> dealings were largely dulled by the absence of active interest beyond the market-makers.
The late buying was drawn into the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX> market, dealers added, after Wall Street showed signs of stability following its rocky opening.
Stocks that suffered on the day were those with active U.S. operations, dealers noted. Among them were <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">B.A.T Industries</ENAMEX>, which settled 6 pence a share lower at 753 ($12.10). <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hanson</ENAMEX>, with 15 million shares traded, closed 2.5 lower at 212.5.
Dealers said the shares were hit by fears of a slowdown in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> economy.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> was boosted 21 to 715 on follow-through buying after <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford Motor</ENAMEX>'s announcement Tuesday that it might be prepared to mount a full bid for the U.K. luxury auto maker. It was further helped by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX>, which announced after <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX>'s close that it had raised its stake to 12% from just under 11% on Tuesday.
Frankfurt prices closed sharply lower in thin dealings, hurt by the roller-coaster session on Wall Street Tuesday and worries about wage demands by the largest West German trade union. The German stock index tumbled 26.29 to end at
``All the positive figures on the economy are out already, and people are focusing more on the dangers for next year, mostly the wage talks and the {parliamentary} elections,'' the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> trader said. The market also shrugged off positive factors, such as higher bond prices and a slowdown in monetary growth in September, traders said.
They said they expect the bearish mood to persist a while longer, as trading volume is falling toward the end of the year and the market is becoming more volatile.
In the auto sector, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bayerische Motoren Werke</ENAMEX> plunged 14.5 marks to 529 marks ($288), <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Daimler-Benz</ENAMEX> dropped 10.5 to 700, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Volkswagen</ENAMEX> slumped 9 to 435.5.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Continental</ENAMEX> gave up some of its recent gains, dropping 8 to 338, as rumors of an impending takeover attempt for the tiremaker faded, brokers said.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Deutsche Bank</ENAMEX> plummeted 12 to 645, hurt by the general mood. Other banks were slightly more resilient, with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dresdner Bank</ENAMEX> shedding 4.8 to 320, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Commerzbank</ENAMEX> slipping 2.5 to
Among Pacific markets, prices closed lower in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Sydney</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Seoul</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hong Kong</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Manila</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Singapore</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Wellington</ENAMEX>. Trading in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Taipei</ENAMEX> was suspended for a national holiday.
