<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Inland Steel Industries Inc.</ENAMEX>, battered by lower volume and higher costs, posted a 75% drop in third-quarter earnings.
The earnings also mark a significant drop from the second quarter's $45.3 million or $1.25 a share. Moreover, the earnings were well below analysts' expectations of about $1.16 a share.
The company attributed the earnings drop to lower volume related to seasonal demand and the soft consumer durable market, especially in the automotive sector. However, the company also lost orders because of prolonged labor talks in the second quarter. Third-quarter shipments slipped 7% from the year-ago period, and 17% from this year's second quarter.
Analysts noted that the disappointing results don't reflect lower prices for steel products. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Charles Bradford</ENAMEX>, an analyst with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merrill Lynch Capital Markets</ENAMEX>, said higher prices for galvanized and cold-rolled products offset lower  prices for bar, hot-rolled and structural steel. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Structural steel</ENAMEX>, which primarily serves the construction market, was especially hurt by a 15% price drop, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bradford</ENAMEX> said.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Inland</ENAMEX> Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Frank W. Luerssen</ENAMEX> said the company's short-term outlook is ``clouded by uncertainties in the economy and financial markets.'' However, he noted that steel mill bookings are up from early summer levels, and that he expects the company to improve its cost performance in the fourth quarter.
In the first nine months, profit was $113 million, or $3.04 a share, on sales of $3.19 billion, compared with $204.5 million, or $5.76 a share, on sales of $3.03 billion, a year earlier.
