<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Philip Morris Cos.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>, adopted a defense measure designed to make a hostile takeover prohibitively expensive.
The giant foods, tobacco and brewing company said it will issue common-share purchase rights to shareholders of record Nov. 8. Under certain circumstances, the rights would entitle <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Philip Morris</ENAMEX> holders to buy shares of either the company or its acquirer for half price.
The board isn't aware of any attempts to take over <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Philip Morris</ENAMEX>, the company said. As of Sept. 30, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Philip Morris</ENAMEX> had 926 million shares outstanding. In composite trading on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Philip Morris</ENAMEX> shares closed yesterday at $43.50 each, down $1.
