<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Toyota Motor Corp.</ENAMEX> predicted its annual imports will more than double by 1992, growing by 250% over the next three years to about 300 billion yen ($2.12 billion) as the company's overseas manufacturing operations reach full speed.
The projected imports comprise importation to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX> and other nations of vehicles produced at the company's major foreign manufacturing bases.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Toyota</ENAMEX> said its import program will specifically entail importing right-hand drive vehicles from its <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Georgetown</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ky.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> plant. ``An ultimate target of 40,000 units annually has been set for a still-to-be-named model,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Toyota</ENAMEX> said.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Toyota</ENAMEX> will also begin importing engines produced at the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Kentucky</ENAMEX> plant's new powertrain operation. Annual volume is expected to reach 100,000 units and will result in additional production and new employment opportunities, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Toyota</ENAMEX> said.
It added that exports of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX>-made Camrys to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Taiwan</ENAMEX> will rise to 10,000 a year by 1992 from a 1989 level of 4,000 units.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Toyota</ENAMEX> also announced a number of major overseas purchases. They include plans to buy 200 vehicles from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> and European auto makers for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Toyota</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rent-A-Lease</ENAMEX> division in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX> and plans to purchase a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cray Y</ENAMEX>-<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MP8</ENAMEX>-232 supercomputer.
