Health-care companies should get healthier in the third quarter.
Medical-supply houses are expected to report earnings increases of about 15% on average for the third quarter, despite sales increases of less than 10%, analysts say. To offset sluggish sales growth, companies have been cutting staff, mostly through attrition, and slowing the growth in research and development spending.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Baxter International Inc.</ENAMEX> yesterday reported net climbed 20% in the third period to $102 million, or 34 cents a share, from $85 million, or 28 cents a share, a year earlier. Sales for the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Deerfield</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ill.</ENAMEX>, company rose 5.8% to $1.81 billion from $1.71 billion.
But not every company expects to report increased earnings. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">C.R. Bard Inc.</ENAMEX> yesterday said third-quarter net plunged 51% to $9.9 million, or 18 cents a share, from $20 million, or 35 cents a share, a year earlier. Sales fell 1.2% to $190.1 million from $192.5 million. The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Murray Hill</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.J.</ENAMEX>, company said full-year earnings may be off 33 cents a share because the company removed a catheter from the market. In 1988, the company earned $1.38 a share.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Food and Drug Administration</ENAMEX> had raised questions about the device's design. Some analysts add that third-party pressures to reduce health costs will continue to bedevil companies' bottom lines. Takeover speculation, which has been buoying stocks of supply houses, may also ease, says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peter Sidoti</ENAMEX>, an analyst with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Drexel Burnham Lambert Inc.</ENAMEX> ``As that wanes, you're going to see the stocks probably wane as well,'' he says.
Bolstered by strong performances by its psychiatric hospitals, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">National Medical Enterprises Inc.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Los Angeles</ENAMEX>, reported net income of $50 million, or 65 cents a share, for the first quarter ended Aug. 31, up from $41 million, or 56 cents a share, a year earlier. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Humana Inc.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Louisville</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ky.</ENAMEX>, also reported favorable results, with net income of $66.7 million, or 66 cents, in the fourth quarter ended Aug. 31, up from $58.2 million, or 59 cents, a year earlier.
Analysts say the handful of hospital companies that are still publicly traded are benefiting from several trends. Most important, hospital admission rates are stabilizing after several years of decline. Moreover, companies have sold off many of their smaller, less-profitable hospitals and have completed painful restructurings. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Humana</ENAMEX>'s revenues, for example, are being boosted by large increases in enrollments in the company's health maintenance organizations.
Says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Todd Richter</ENAMEX>, an analyst with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dean Witter Reynolds</ENAMEX>: ``The shakeout in the publicly traded companies is over.
