<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Wang Laboratories Inc.</ENAMEX> has sold $25 million of assets and reached agreements in principle to sell an additional $187 million shortly, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Richard Miller</ENAMEX>, president, said at the annual meeting.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Miller</ENAMEX> said that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Wang</ENAMEX> has already sold some $12 million of miscellaneous assets and disclosed that it had received $13 million from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Compaq Computer Corp.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Houston</ENAMEX>, in the previously announced sale of its <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Stirling</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Scotland</ENAMEX>, plant.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Miller</ENAMEX> repeated that in the next six months he plans to sell another $200 million to $300 million of assets to repay debt and reduce interest costs at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Wang</ENAMEX>, a minincomputer maker in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Lowell</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mass.</ENAMEX>
