<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Petco Options</ENAMEX>, an options trading firm owned by the family of the deceased former <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chicago Board of Trade</ENAMEX> chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ralph Peters</ENAMEX>, is getting out of the trade clearing, or processing and guaranteeing, business after sustaining a multimillion dollar loss Friday, options industry officials said.
Over the weekend <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Fossett Corp.</ENAMEX>, another options trading firm, transferred the clearing accounts of about 160 traders to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Options of Chicago</ENAMEX>, a unit of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Continental Bank Corp.</ENAMEX>, because it couldn't meet regulatory capital requirements after Friday's market slide. The unprecedented transfer of accounts underscored the options industry's desire not to have its credibility tarnished by potentially widespread trading defaults on Monday. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CBOE</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Stock Exchange</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Options Clearing Corp.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stephen Fossett</ENAMEX>, owner of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Fossett</ENAMEX>, joined in putting up $50 million to guarantee the accounts at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Options.</ENAMEX>
The head of another small options clearing firm, who asked not to be identified, said that the heightened volatility in the financial markets in recent years makes it increasingly difficult for any but the largest financial trading firms to shoulder the risk inherent in the highly leveraged options and futures business.
Prior to the introduction of financial futures in the late 1970s, most trading firms clustered around the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Lasalle Street</ENAMEX> financial district here were family operations handed down from one generation to the next. Most also were relatively undercapitalized compared with the size of most Wall Street securities firms.
