If growth regains its glamour among investors, a sluggish segment of the Nasdaq over-the-counter market could show some flash.
Some stock pickers already are targeting the OTC market, where, they say, await plenty of small - and medium-sized growth stocks. Best of all, they add, these growth issues, unlike their big blue-chip cousins on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX>, are languishing at depressed prices.
``The market will have to look for a new theme now and that theme will be a return to growth,'' declares <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mary Farrell</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Painewebber</ENAMEX> analyst. Among her OTC picks are <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Oshkosh B'Gosh</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">A&W Brands</ENAMEX>. Like many OTC growth issues, they have market values -- as measured by stock price times shares outstanding -- of roughly $100 million to $500 million.
Some like to specialize in growth companies whose shares haven't traded publicly very long. These are sometimes dubbed ``emerging'' growth companies, though they also have expanding-profit track records.
``You can find some good, quality companies over the counter,'' but investors should be selective, says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John Palicka</ENAMEX>, chief portfolio manager at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Midco Investors</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Newark</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.J.</ENAMEX>, money management company with about $900 million invested in growth stocks of varying sizes. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Palicka</ENAMEX>'s picks from the OTC market include <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Legent</ENAMEX>, Mail Boxes <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Etc.</ENAMEX>, and Payco <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American.</ENAMEX>
The main argument for growth stocks is their usually superior performance in a slowing economy. ``If the market refocuses on earnings, we should get better valuations of growth stocks,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">L. Keith Mullins</ENAMEX>, a growth-stock analyst at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Morgan Stanley.</ENAMEX> Eventually, he believes, investors will be willing to pay higher prices for companies with proven track records of earnings growth. In anticipation of that shift, he and other analysts are encouraging their clients to buy such issues now.
In addition, earnings growth took a back seat to cash flow, restructuring and takeover potential, and breakup value as the preferred stock-picking standards for much of the year. Also, the smaller growth stocks aren't widely traded, and so are harder to buy and sell quickly than blue chips.
As a result, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Morgan Stanley's</ENAMEX> Index of 40 Emerging Growth Stocks -- most of which are in the OTC market -- is up only 13% for the year, while the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> Industrial Average has leaped 24% and the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">S&P</ENAMEX> 500 has grown 25%. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nasdaq</ENAMEX> Composite has gained 23% this year, but that's largely due to the 100 largest nonfinancial stocks, which have soared 30%.
Some investors are skeptical of growth stocks because investing in them means ignoring that maxim found in the fine print of some investment advertisements -- that past performance isn't indicative of future results. ``People are naturally suspicious of them,'' says Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mullins</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Morgan Stanley.</ENAMEX> Among his favorites in his firm's index are <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Legent</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Silicon Graphics</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Novell</ENAMEX>.
However, more money managers are reassured that profit is regaining importance. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mark Schoeppner</ENAMEX>, portfolio manager at <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Pittsburgh</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Quaker Capital Management</ENAMEX>, says that in reaction to nervousness about debt-laden buy-out transactions, analysts and investors now appear to be ``valuing stock based on future earnings as opposed to the amount of debt the company can support.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Barney Hallingby</ENAMEX>, managing director of research at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hambrecht & Quist</ENAMEX>, also believes earnings growth is beginning to play a greater part in investors' buying decisions. On Friday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hambrecht & Quist</ENAMEX> added <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">St. Jude Medical</ENAMEX> to the list of 20 stocks it strongly recommends. The opinion is largely based on the company's earnings momentum, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hallingby</ENAMEX> says.
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">St. Jude</ENAMEX>'s market value on Nasdaq exceeds $1 billion, so it isn't a small stock. The medical devices maker's earnings rose nearly 35% in 1987 from 1986, and 75% in 1988. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kurt Kruger</ENAMEX>, who follows the stock for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hambrecht & Quist</ENAMEX>, anticipates that the company's net income will grow 51% to $2.15 a share this year. <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">St. Jude</ENAMEX> finished up 1/4 to 44 1/2 on Friday.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nasdaq</ENAMEX> Composite Index eased 0.13 to 470.67. The composite finished up 0.7% from last Friday's close.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Eliot Savings Bank</ENAMEX> lost 7/8 to 1 5/8 after reporting that it had a $4.8 million loss in the latest third quarter mostly because of loan-loss provisions. In the 1988 quarter, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">bank</ENAMEX> earned $1.1 million.
One bank stock was a winner. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Banponce</ENAMEX> jumped 4 1/2 to 47 3/4 after agreeing to be acquired by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Banco Popular</ENAMEX> de <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Puerto Rico</ENAMEX> for $56.25 a share. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Banco Popular</ENAMEX>, meanwhile, dropped 1 1/4 to 21 1/2.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Sierra Tucson</ENAMEX>, an initial public offering, made the most active list. The company's shares began trading at 12 1/2, up from its initial offering price of 12, and closed at 13. Sierra <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tucson</ENAMEX> operates an addiction treatment center.
Among declining issues, a weak earnings outlook drove <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Groundwater Technology</ENAMEX> down 6 1/4 to 24. The company said results for its second quarter ended Oct. 28 could drop as much as 20% below the 30 cents a share reported in the year-earlier quarter.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Medstone International</ENAMEX> plummeted 3 1/4 to 7 1/4. A <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Food and Drug Administration</ENAMEX> advisory panel has asked that Medstone perform more studies on its device to treat gallstones.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Raymond Corp.</ENAMEX> lost 1 to 10 after it said late Thursday that it will take a $4.4 million charge in its third quarter for reserves to cover potential charges in connection with the closing and sale of a manufacturing plant. As a result, the company has suspended its quarterly dividend.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mccaw Cellular Communications</ENAMEX> and its target, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">LIN Broadcasting</ENAMEX>, were active. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">LIN</ENAMEX> added 5/8 to 110 5/8 and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mccaw</ENAMEX> lost 1/4 to 41. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mccaw</ENAMEX> said it has secured commitments from three banks to help finance its $125-a-share bid for 22 million of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lin</ENAMEX>'s shares. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mccaw</ENAMEX> has called for a ``fair auction'' of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">LIN</ENAMEX>, which earlier entered a stock-swap merger pact with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bellsouth</ENAMEX>.
Following the release of the company's fourth-quarter earnings, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Apple Computer</ENAMEX> dropped 3/4 to 48 on volume of more than 2.3 million shares. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Apple</ENAMEX> earned $161.1 million, or $1.24 a share, in the quarter, including $48 million from the sale of its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Adobe Systems</ENAMEX> stock.
