<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CMS ENERGY Corp.</ENAMEX> said management would recommend to its board today that its common stock dividend be reinstated at a ``modest level'' later this year. The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dearborn</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mich.</ENAMEX>, energy company stopped paying a dividend in the third quarter of 1984 because of troubles at its <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Midland</ENAMEX> nuclear plant. In addition, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CMS</ENAMEX> reported third-quarter net of $68.2 million, or 83 cents a share, up from $66.8 million, or 81 cents a share, a year ago.
