<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Polly Peck International Inc.</ENAMEX>'s agreement to acquire 51% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sansui Electric Co.</ENAMEX> proves that foreign companies can acquire Japanese companies -- if the alternative for the Japanese company is extinction.
``The myths that <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX> is not open to concerns from outside has, I think, been demolished at a stroke,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Nadir</ENAMEX> said.
But analysts say Sansui is a special case. It expects to post a loss of 6.4 billion yen for the year ending tomorrow and its liabilities currently exceed its assets by about 13.8 billion yen. ``If you find sound, healthy companies in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX>, they are not for sale,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">George Watanabe</ENAMEX>, a management-consultant at <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tokyo</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Asia Advisory Services Inc.</ENAMEX>
Nor do analysts expect the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sansui</ENAMEX> deal to touch off a fresh wave of foreign purchases. If the strong yen and the high stock prices of Japanese companies weren't deterrents enough, webs of cross-shareholdings between friendly Japanese companies and fiercely independent Japanese corporate attitudes repel most would-be acquirers.
Some of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sansui</ENAMEX>'s fellow audio-specialty companies, such as <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Aiwa Co.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pioneer Electric Corp.</ENAMEX>, responded to the challenge by quickly bringing out mini-component products of their own, by moving heavily into the booming compact disk businesses or by diversifying into other consumer-electronics fields, including laser disks or portable cassette players. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sansui</ENAMEX> was late into the mini-component business and failed to branch into other new businesses.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Yoshihisa Murasawa</ENAMEX>, a management consultant for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Booz-Allen & Hamilton (Japan) Inc.</ENAMEX>, said his firm will likely be recommending acquisitions of Japanese companies more often to foreign clients in the future. ``Attitudes {toward being acquired} are still negative, but they're becoming more positive,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Murasawa</ENAMEX> said. ``In some industries, like pharmaceuticals, acquisitions make sense.''
Whether <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Polly Peck</ENAMEX>'s acquisition makes sense remains to be seen, but at the news conference, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Nadir</ENAMEX> brimmed with self-confidence that he can turn Sansui around. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sansui</ENAMEX>, he said, is a perfect fit for <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Polly Peck</ENAMEX>'s electronics operations, which make televisions, videocassette recorders, microwaves and other products on an ``original equipment maker'' basis for sale under other companies' brand names.
He said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Polly Peck</ENAMEX> will greatly expand <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sansui</ENAMEX>'s product line, using <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Sansui</ENAMEX>'s engineers to design the new products, and will move <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Sansui</ENAMEX>'s production of most products other than sophisticated audio gear offshore into <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Polly Peck</ENAMEX>'s own factories.
``Whatever capital it (<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Sansui</ENAMEX>) needs so it can compete and become a totally global entity capable of competing with the best in the world, that capital will be injected,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Nadir</ENAMEX> said.
Last month, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Polly Peck</ENAMEX> posted a 38% jump in pretax profit for the first half to # 54.8 million from # 39.8 million on a 63% rise in sales.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Joann S. Lublin</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX> contributed to this article.
