<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Kellwood Co.</ENAMEX> said it completed a previously announced acquisition of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Crowntuft Manufacturing Corp.</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>-based maker of chenille robes and lounge wear.
The apparel maker wouldn't disclose terms of the agreement. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Kellwood</ENAMEX> said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gabriel Hakim Sr.</ENAMEX>, president of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Crowntuft</ENAMEX>, will continue to head <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Crowntuft</ENAMEX>'s management group.
