For bankers and regulators, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Arizona</ENAMEX> is looking more like <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Texas</ENAMEX> every day.
On <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Friday</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Los Angeles</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Interstate Bancorp</ENAMEX> said it expects a net loss of $16 million for the third quarter of 1989 because of hemorrhaging at its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Interstate Bank</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Arizona</ENAMEX> unit. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Interstate</ENAMEX> said the unit, bludgeoned by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Arizona</ENAMEX>'s worsening real-estate woes, will have a $174 million loss for the quarter. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Interstate</ENAMEX> took a huge $350 million provision for loan losses at the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Arizona</ENAMEX> bank. It charged off an estimated $200 million of Arizona loans, leaving the unit with a reserve for future losses of $255 million, about 61% of its $416 million of troubled loans and repossessed real estate.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Furthermore</ENAMEX>, the regulatory maneuvering behind <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Interstate</ENAMEX>'s loss suggests regulators have concluded that lenders' reserves are far too low to absorb their future Arizona losses and are forcing bankers to do something about it. Examiners from the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Office</ENAMEX> of the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Comptroller</ENAMEX> of the Currency had been combing through <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Interstate</ENAMEX>'s real-estate portfolio since last month; they first recommended that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Interstate</ENAMEX> take a provision that was less than the eventual $350 million third-quarter hit. When <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Interstate</ENAMEX> balked, arguing that the figure was too high, regulators responded by raising their recommendation to $350 million.
``At that point, {<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Interstate</ENAMEX>} decided it was the better part of valor not to negotiate further,'' said one industry official close to the talks. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Thomas P. Marrie</ENAMEX>, chief financial officer, wouldn't comment about the details of the negotiations. He said the provision ``wasn't forced upon us, but the regulators made it very clear what they thought was an appropriate number.''
The tough regulatory stance portends large future losses, especially at the state's thrifts. At least six of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Arizona</ENAMEX>'s 12 savings and loan institutions have either been taken over by the government's conservatorship program or are essentially insolvent; they are sitting on enormous unrecognized losses.
For example, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Western Savings & Loan Association</ENAMEX>, which is now in conservatorship, had tangible capital-assets minus liabilities -- of a negative $357.4 million at June 30. It had a $258.9 million loss in the second quarter. Yet it still held $916.3 million of repossessed real estate, for which it maintains no reserves whatsoever. It also had $479.7 million of past-due loans; its level of reserves against those wasn't immediately available, though it is believed to be small.
They have no reserves against the real estate, and their reserves against the loans are miniscule compared with the levels of reserves banks are moving to set up. The thrifts had a combined loss of $487.8 million in the second quarter. Other lenders have been recovering only 50 cents to 60 cents on the dollar on foreclosed Arizona property, if they can sell it at all.
``It's horrible to say, but it's unfortunate that earthquake wasn't in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Phoenix</ENAMEX> -- it might have knocked out some of our empty buildings,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">C.W. Jackson</ENAMEX>, a prominent <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Arizona</ENAMEX> businessman with interests in real estate, banking and many other businesses.
Many Arizona real-estate experts think the worst may be yet to come. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ralph Shattuck</ENAMEX>, publisher of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Foreclosure</ENAMEX> Update newsletter, said foreclosures have climbed to about 1,482 a month just in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Maricopa County</ENAMEX>, where <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Phoenix</ENAMEX> is located. That's up from about 687 a month in 1985, and it's accelerating: So far this month, foreclosures are averaging about 85 a day. ``It's frightening,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Shattuck</ENAMEX> said.
Moreover, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Shattuck</ENAMEX> and others said residential real estate, which had remained fairly strong through most of the downturn, is beginning to comprise more and more of the foreclosures. And the generally frail condition of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Arizona</ENAMEX>'s lenders means there is little capital available in the state to shore up the economy and slow down the slide.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Interstate</ENAMEX> had a $214.4 million loss in 1988's third quarter, mainly from writedowns and reserves connected with its <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Texas</ENAMEX> operations. For the six months ended June 30, it reported net income of $234.3 million, or $4.83 a share, including $46 million from tax credits and accounting changes.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">bank</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Arizona</ENAMEX> unit holds about $6 billion of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Interstate</ENAMEX>'s $50 billion of assets. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Marrie</ENAMEX> said the bank expects Arizona real-estate prices, which plummeted 40% over the last year, to fall another 20% before stabilizing. Some in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Arizona</ENAMEX> think that may be optimistic. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Interstate</ENAMEX> said its operations outside of Arizona ``achieved results as expected for the quarter,'' but didn't specify the results.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Interstate</ENAMEX> stock closed at $57.625, down 25 cents, in composite trading Friday on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX>. Since its unsuccessful bid for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bankamerica Corp.</ENAMEX> in 1986, the bank has undertaken a major restructuring in an effort to cut costs and boost performance, but many industry officials believe it may be ripe for a takeover bid, especially with interstate banking set to begin in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">California</ENAMEX> in 1991. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Marrie</ENAMEX> said the problems in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Arizona</ENAMEX> have only ``increased our resolve to continue to make our restructuring even more effective.''
Separately, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Standard & Poor's Corp.</ENAMEX> lowered its ratings on <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Valley National Corp.</ENAMEX>'s senior debt to double-B from double-B-plus, affecting about $300 million of long-term debt. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">S&P</ENAMEX> also lowered ratings on unsecured deposits and issues backed by a letter of credit from the bank holding company's principal unit, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Valley National Bank</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Arizona</ENAMEX>. The ratings service said the downgrades reflect the continued slide in the company's financial condition.
A spokesman for <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Phoenix</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ariz.</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Valley National</ENAMEX>, said the concern will be able to withstand the current downturn in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Arizona</ENAMEX> real estate. Commercial paper holders have reinvested their funds, he said, and consumer deposits have been up in the last few days.
