An <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Eastern</ENAMEX> spokesman said he doesn't expect that the arbitrator's ruling ``will have any overall material effect on the company's strategic plan.''
Bankruptcy experts said the law isn't clear on how such an arbitration ruling can affect a company's case. Like any other creditor, the pilots will have to apply to the court for payment of their claim.
That may leave a lot of leeway for U.S. Bankruptcy Judge <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Burton R. Lifland</ENAMEX> to decide what, if anything, the pilots actually collect. In August, he issued the ruling that let the pilots pursue their back-pay grievance before the arbitrator. The pilots' contract with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Eastern</ENAMEX> calls for a mutually acceptable private arbitrator to resolve such grievances.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Eastern</ENAMEX>'s creditors committee, along with the company, has consistently opposed the pilots' claim, which if paid would have to come out of money both hope to use to pay off other bankruptcy claims.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Eastern</ENAMEX> and its creditors are in the final, delicate stages of negotiating a second reorganization plan to pay off the airline's debts. An earlier plan, which had received the creditors' approval in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">July</ENAMEX>, fell apart when <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Eastern</ENAMEX> changed its business plan. It isn't known whether the pilot claim was figured into either plan.
The dispute between <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Eastern</ENAMEX> and its pilots is over a ``pay parity'' clause in the pilots' contract. The clause was part of an agreement in which pilots accepted a substantial pay cut as long as no other labor group got a raise.
Ironically, many of the pilots involved have left <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Eastern</ENAMEX> or are still striking the carrier, which filed for bankruptcy protection March 9. About 800 have crossed the picket lines and returned to work.
