<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ciba-Geigy Ltd.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chiron Corp.</ENAMEX> said they extended their offer for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Connaught Biosciences Inc.</ENAMEX>, valued at 866 million Canadian dollars (US$736 million) to Oct. 27.
The companies earlier said they didn't want to raise their offer to match a rival bid by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Institut Merieux S.A.</ENAMEX> of C$37/NNP a share, or C$942 million. But they said the C$30-a-share bid, which was due to expire Monday, may still be extended or varied.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Institut Merieux</ENAMEX>'s bid for <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Toronto</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Connaught</ENAMEX> has run into problems with the Canadian government, which told <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merieux</ENAMEX> last week that it wasn't convinced that the proposed acquisition would be of ``net benefit'' to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Canada</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merieux</ENAMEX> officials are expected to meet with federal officials in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ottawa</ENAMEX> today to discuss the decision.
