<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UNITED AIR</ENAMEX>'S PARENT quashed any prospects for an immediate revival of the labor-management buy-out, saying <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> should remain independent for now. Also, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stephen Wolf</ENAMEX> pulled out of the buy-out effort to focus on running the company. The two developments leave the airline with several problems, including an unsettled labor situation.
Stock prices fell and bonds rose as worries mounted about the economy and the junk bond market. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> industrials sank 26.23 points, to 2662.91. The dollar also declined.
The turmoil in junk bonds may last for years, investors and traders say. Even <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Drexel</ENAMEX> is pulling back.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Santa Fe Pacific</ENAMEX> plans to sell 20% of its large real estate unit to a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">California</ENAMEX> pension fund for $400 million and spin the rest off to shareholders. The proposal values the company's real estate operation at $2 billion.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Time Warner</ENAMEX> reported a $176 million loss for the third quarter, reflecting the cost of the recent merger and a method of accounting for the deal.
Thrifts continued to shed assets in August, mainly to comply with stiffer capital rules under the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">S&L</ENAMEX> bailout law. Also, withdrawals exceeded deposits by $5.1 billion in the month.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Exxon</ENAMEX>'s profit fell 9% in the third quarter, hurt by sagging results at two of its three main businesses. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Phillips</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Arco</ENAMEX> posted declines. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ashland</ENAMEX> had a loss. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Amerada Hess</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Occidental Petroleum</ENAMEX> had gains.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ogilvy</ENAMEX>'s chairman, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kenneth Roman</ENAMEX>, is leaving to take a top post at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Express</ENAMEX>. His resignation follows a hostile takeover of the ad agency in May by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">WPP</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Shearson</ENAMEX> was sued by money manager <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">George Soros</ENAMEX>, who claimed one of his funds was defrauded out of $60 million during stock-index futures trading just after the 1987 crash.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Drexel</ENAMEX>'s efforts to settle its legal troubles are being resisted by at least 10 states. Some may try to revoke the firm's license to sell securities.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Union Carbide</ENAMEX>'s earnings plunged 35% in the third quarter, reflecting weakness in the company's core chemicals and plastics businesses.
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Daiwa Securities</ENAMEX> named Masahiro Dozen president. The rapid advance of the 52-year-old executive surprised many at the company.
Markets --
Dollar: 141.90 yen, off 0.53; 1.8470 marks, off 0.0108.
