<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Canadian Pacific Ltd.</ENAMEX> said it proposed acquiring the 44% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Soo Line Corp.</ENAMEX> it doesn't already own for $19.50 a share, or about $81.9 million, after failing to find a buyer for its majority stake earlier this year.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Soo Line</ENAMEX> said its board appointed a special committee of independent directors to study the proposal. The troubled <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Minneapolis</ENAMEX>-based railroad concern said the committee has the authority to hire financial and legal advisers to assist it. The proposed acquisition will be subject to approval by the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Interstate Commerce Commission</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Soo Line</ENAMEX> said.
In <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> composite trading yesterday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Soo Line</ENAMEX> shares jumped well above the proposed price, closing at $20.25, up $2.75.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Canadian Pacific</ENAMEX> put its 56% stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Soo Line</ENAMEX> up for sale last year but couldn't find any takers. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Canadian Pacific</ENAMEX>, which has interests in transportation, telecommunications, forest products, energy and real estate, finally took its majority block off the market this spring. ``It turned out we couldn't sell it,'' a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Canadian Pacific</ENAMEX> official said, adding that acquiring the remainder of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Soo Line</ENAMEX> is now ``the best way to rationalize operations.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Canadian Pacific</ENAMEX> is <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Soo Line</ENAMEX>'s biggest customer and has owned a majority stake in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> railroad since 1947. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Canadian Pacific</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Soo Line</ENAMEX> tracks connect at two points in the West on the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Canada</ENAMEX>-<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> border and the two companies operate a very successful <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chicago</ENAMEX>-<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Montreal</ENAMEX> rail service.
