<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Diversified Investment Group Inc.</ENAMEX> said it agreed to be acquired by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Star States Corp.</ENAMEX> for stock valued at $13.75 a share, or about $24.4 million.
The acquisition would give <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Wilmington</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Del.</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Star States</ENAMEX> access to the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Pennsylvania</ENAMEX> market.
The agreement is subject to regulatory approval and resolution of lawsuits brought by certain Diversified holders in connection with the proposed merger.
