The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.S. Export-Import Bank</ENAMEX> cleared a $25 million loan to a telephone company in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chile</ENAMEX> for the purchase of satellite telecommunications network equipment from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> suppliers.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Export-Import Bank</ENAMEX> said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cia.</ENAMEX> de <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telefonos</ENAMEX> de <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chile</ENAMEX> is buying equipment and project management services from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Scientific-Atlanta Inc.</ENAMEX>, of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Norcross</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ga.</ENAMEX>, to extend telephone and data-transmission services between <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Santiago</ENAMEX> and other Chilean cities. The bank said several other U.S. companies also will supply electronic equipment for this project.
The loan, which carries a 9.65% annual interest rate, was approved after <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Scientific-Atlanta</ENAMEX> won a $29.4 million contract to supply equipment and services for the project in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chile</ENAMEX>. According to Export-<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Import Bank</ENAMEX> officials, Japanese and French companies also bid for the business.
