<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Norwood Partners Limited Partnership of Boston</ENAMEX> said it may make a tender offer for some or all of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Phoenix Technologies Ltd.</ENAMEX>'s common shares.
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Norwood</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mass.</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Phoenix</ENAMEX>, a once-high-flying maker of software for personal computers, has had substantial losses in the past two quarters. Its stock, which was as high as $18.75 a share, has been trading under $4 a share recently. Yesterday it closed at $4.375 a share, up $1.125, in national over-the-counter trading.
In a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Securities and Exchange Commission</ENAMEX> filing, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Norwood</ENAMEX> said it's part of a group that holds 525,546 <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Phoenix Technologies</ENAMEX> common shares, or a 5.3% stake.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Norwood</ENAMEX> has made ``no detailed plans,'' but it has engaged in talks with other shareholders, the filing said. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Phoenix</ENAMEX> declined to comment.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Norwood</ENAMEX> is controlled by <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Daniel L. Barnett</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Paul A. Reese</ENAMEX>, both officers of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Boston</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Oasis Capital Management Inc.</ENAMEX>, a small <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Boston</ENAMEX> money management firm. Also involved in the group is <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Robert F. Angelo</ENAMEX>, formerly <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Phoenix</ENAMEX>'s senior vice president, field operations, who left <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Phoenix</ENAMEX> at the beginning of October. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Angelo</ENAMEX> was described in the filing as a consultant to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Oasis</ENAMEX>.
