<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pittston Co.</ENAMEX>'s third-quarter net income plunged 79%, reflecting the impact of a prolonged and bitter labor strike at its coal operations.
Net sank to $3.1 million, or eight cents a share, including $789,000, or two cents a share, reflecting a tax-loss carry-forward. In the year-ago quarter, net totaled $14.7 million, or 38 cents a share, including $4 million, or 10 cents a share, reflecting a tax-loss carry-forward. Revenue slipped 0.7% to $395.3 million from $398.3 million.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pittston</ENAMEX> also owns <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Brink's Inc.</ENAMEX>, the security service, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Burlington Air Express</ENAMEX>, the air-freight concern.
In addition to expected losses tied to the labor strike, the coal group has spent almost $20 million since the strike began for security, the company said. As a result, the group's third-quarter loss widened to $9.8 million from the second quarter's $3.6 million. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pittston</ENAMEX> continues to hire replacement workers, the company said.
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Burlington</ENAMEX>'s operating profit grew to $9.2 million from $3.8 million a year earlier, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pittston</ENAMEX> said. While ``the tone'' of domestic and international air-freight markets remains sound, seasonal factors are likely to hinder <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Burlington Air</ENAMEX> from matching third-quarter results in the fourth quarter, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pittston</ENAMEX> said.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Brink</ENAMEX>'s operating profit was about flat with the year-earlier period, reflecting continued pricing and cost pressures.
In <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> composite trading Friday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pittston</ENAMEX> closed at $18.50 a share, down 12.5 cents.
