Billions of investors' dollars are pouring out of the nation's junk-bond mutual funds, undermining a pillar of support in the already reeling junk market.
Last week alone, an eye-popping $1.6 billion flowed out of the junk funds, or nearly 5% of their total assets, according to estimates by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dalbar Financial Services Inc.</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Boston</ENAMEX> research firm.
Interviews with three major fund groups -- <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Fidelity Investments</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Vanguard Group Inc.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">T. Rowe Price Associates Inc.</ENAMEX> -- confirm the trend. Their junk funds combined have had net outflows totaling nearly $500 million, or about 13% of their junk fund assets, in the past two months.
Some fund managers say negative publicity has exacerbated investors' concern about recent declines in junk-bond prices. ``People have been seeing headline after headline after headline and saying: `I can't take it anymore -- I'm getting out,''' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kurt Brouwer</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Brouwer & Janachowski</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">San Francisco</ENAMEX> investment adviser.
The withdrawals could spell trouble for the $200 billion junk market. If the heavy outflows continue, fund managers will face increasing pressure to sell off some of their junk to pay departing investors in the weeks ahead. Such selling could erode prices of high-yield junk bonds, already weakened by a rash of corporate credit problems.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mutual</ENAMEX> fund groups haven't lost control of much of the outgoing money, says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Louis Harvey</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dalbar</ENAMEX>'s president. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mutual fund</ENAMEX> officials say that investors have transferred most of it into their money market accounts, and to a lesser extent, government-bond funds. So the impact on the $950 billion mutual fund industry as a whole probably will be slight.
The $1.5 billion <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Fidelity High Income Fund</ENAMEX> has had a net outflow of about $150 million in the past two months. About $60 million streamed out last week alone, double the level of the week following last month's <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Campeau Corp.</ENAMEX> credit squeeze. About 98% of the outflow was transferred to other <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Fidelity</ENAMEX> funds, says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Neal Litvack</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Fidelity</ENAMEX> vice president, marketing, with most going into money market funds.
At the $932 million <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">T. Rowe Price High Yield Fund</ENAMEX>, investors yanked out about $182 million in the past two months. Those withdrawals, most of which were transferred to other <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">T. Rowe Price</ENAMEX> funds, followed little change in the fund's sales picture this year through August. ``The last two months have been the whole ball game,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steven Norwitz</ENAMEX>, a vice president.
Junk-fund holders have barely broken even this year, as fat interest payments barely managed to offset declining prices. Through Oct. 19, high-yield funds had an average 0.85% total return (the price change plus dividends on fund shares), according to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lipper Analytical Services Inc.</ENAMEX> That's even less than the 4.35% total return of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merrill Lynch High-Yield Index</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Fidelity</ENAMEX>'s junk fund has fallen 2.08% this year through Oct. 19, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lipper</ENAMEX> says; the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Vanguard</ENAMEX> fund rose 1.84%; and the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">T. Rowe Price</ENAMEX> fund edged up 0.66%.
Says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Michael Hirsch</ENAMEX>, chief investment officer of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Republic National Bank</ENAMEX> and manager of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Fundtrust Group</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>: ``It's a time bomb just waiting to go off.
