<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Reebok International Ltd.</ENAMEX> posted a 35% increase in third-quarter net income despite a slight decline in sales.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Paul Fireman</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Reebok</ENAMEX> chairman and chief executive officer, said, ``Our gains in earnings provide further evidence that the controls we have put in place and our sales mix are continuing to improve the company's overall profit performance.''
The company said it expects sales to improve due to a number of new products, including a ``pump'' basketball shoe that can be inflated to better fit the foot.
In the first nine months, net was $140 million, or $1.23 a share, on sales of $1.44 billion.
Separately, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Reebok</ENAMEX> completed the acquisition of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CML Group Inc.</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boston Whaler</ENAMEX> unit, a builder of power boats.
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">CML</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Acton</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mass.</ENAMEX>, had agreed to sell the unit to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Reebok</ENAMEX> for about $42 million. The agreement also called for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Reebok</ENAMEX> to receive warrants to purchase 400,000 shares of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CML</ENAMEX> common at $31.25 a share, exercisable at any time before July 1,
An outside spokesman for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CML</ENAMEX> said the terms were changed to a minor extent but wouldn't disclose what those changes were.
