<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">TW Services Inc.</ENAMEX> posted a $3.3 million third-quarter net loss, compared with a $24.9 million profit, reflecting $60 million of expenses related to its much-publicized proposed takeover by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coniston Partners</ENAMEX>.
The per-share loss for the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Paramus</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.J.</ENAMEX>, food-services concern totaled seven cents, compared with earnings of 51 cents a share a year earlier. Revenue rose 5% to $981.7 million from $934.7 million.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coniston</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> investment partnership, awaits a vote by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">TW</ENAMEX>'s shareholders, scheduled for Friday, on <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coniston</ENAMEX>'s $34-a-share, or $1.66 billion, offer for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">TW</ENAMEX>.
