Yesterday, in composite trading on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Stock Exchange</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Vermont American</ENAMEX> common closed at $39.75, off 25 cents.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FTC</ENAMEX>'s request was ``not unusual'' and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Emerson</ENAMEX> will make a ``full and prompt'' response, according to a spokesman. Spokesmen for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Emerson</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Vermont American</ENAMEX>, which has agreed to be acquired, said they don't anticipate ``any problems'' with the completion of the transaction.
An <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FTC</ENAMEX> spokesman said the matter is ``in a non-public posture at this time'' and declined to comment further.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Emerson</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bosch</ENAMEX>, through their joint acquisition arm, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Maple Acquisition</ENAMEX>, have begun a cash tender offer for all of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Vermont's</ENAMEX> common shares outstanding. The offer, set to expire Nov. 1, may be extended pending the timing and resolution of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FTC</ENAMEX> request, the companies said.
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">St. Louis</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Emerson</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Stuttgart</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bosch</ENAMEX> make electrical and electronic products, including power tools. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Vermont American</ENAMEX> acquisition is designed to enhance their position in the accessories portion of the power-tool industry.
