Domestic lending for real estate and property development was the source of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bank Bumiputra Malaysia Bhd.</ENAMEX>'s most recent spate of financial troubles, the institution's executive chairman, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mohamed Basir Ismail</ENAMEX>, said.
He said the bank couldn't wait any longer for prices to recover and for borrowers to service their loans. So the bank's board decided to make 1.23 billion Malaysian dollars (US$457 million) in provisions for interest payments from loans previously recorded as revenue but never actually received by the bank, and to submit a bailout package to replenish the bank's paid-up capital.
Tan Sri <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Basir</ENAMEX> said the capital restructuring plan has been approved by <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Malaysia</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Capital Issues Committee</ENAMEX> and central bank. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Malaysia's High Court</ENAMEX> is expected to approve the plan.
Once the plan is approved, Tan Sri <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Basir</ENAMEX> said, most of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bank Bumiputra</ENAMEX>'s nonperforming loans will have been fully provided for and the bank will be on track to report a pretax profit of between M$160 million and M$170 million for the fiscal year ending March 31. For the previous financial year, the bank would have reported a pretax profit of M$168 million if it hadn't made provisions for the nonperforming loans, he said.
``We lent a lot of money all over the place,'' said Tan Sri <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Basir</ENAMEX>, who refused to discuss the bank's outstanding loans to
As well as the M$1.23 billion in provisions announced on Oct. 6, the restructuring package covers an additional M$450 million in provisions made in earlier years but never reflected in a reduction of the bank's paid-up capital. At the end of the exercise, the cash injection from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Petronas</ENAMEX> will increase the bank's paid-up capital to M$1.15 billion after virtually being wiped out by the new provisions.
