<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Apogee Enterprises Inc.</ENAMEX> said profit for the third quarter ending Dec. 2 will fall below the year-earlier results because of an after-tax charge of $1.9 million related to a project that was guaranteed by the company.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Apogee</ENAMEX> said the charge stems from a building supply contract in which the company guaranteed a contractor's performance. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Apogee</ENAMEX> said a subcontractor had severe cost overruns and was unable to fulfill the contract terms on its own, making it necessary for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Apogee</ENAMEX> to advance cash to ensure completion of the project.
The company said its core businesses have performed well and it expects them to continue to do so in the remainder of the fiscal year.
