In an official release, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">BP</ENAMEX> said initial production from the field was 11,000 barrels a day, and that it expects peak output from the field of 15,000 barrels a day to be reached in 1990.
