<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">National Intergroup Inc.</ENAMEX> said it expects to report a charge of $5.3 million related to the sale of its aluminum unit's extrusion division for the third quarter.
The company said it has agreed to sell the extrusion division for $15 million to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">R.D. Werner Co.</ENAMEX>, a closely held firm based in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Greenville</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Pa.</ENAMEX>
The charge is offset by an after-tax gain of about $30 million in the quarter from the previously announced pact to sell <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">National Aluminum</ENAMEX>'s rolling division.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">National Intergroup</ENAMEX> in the year-ago third quarter earned $22.5 million, or 97 cents a share, including a gain of $18 million from the sale of a steel tube company. Revenue was $778.6 million.
The sale of the extrusion division is subject to audit adjustments for working capital changes through the closing.
The extrusion unit produces bare and painted custom extrusions for building products and construction industries. In fiscal 1989, it had sales of about $40 million and an operating loss of $1.5 million.
