<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Time Warner Inc.</ENAMEX> reported a third-quarter net loss of $176 million, or $2.88 cents a share, reflecting acquisition costs for a 59.3% stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner Communications Inc.</ENAMEX> and the purchase method of accounting for the transaction.
Separately, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> reported a net loss of $106 million, or 56 cents a share, including merger expenses of $100 million and $120 million in charges associated with stock-appreciation-based compensation plans.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Time Warner</ENAMEX> is in the process of completing its acquisition of the remaining <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> shares. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Time Warner</ENAMEX> emphasized in a news release that it should be evaluated based on its cash flow, which the company defined as earnings before interest, taxes, depreciation and amortization. On a pro-forma basis, assuming the merger was effective Jan 1, 1988, including the results from both <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Time Inc.</ENAMEX> and all of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX>, that cash flow figure would be $526 million for the latest quarter, more than double the comparable figure a year ago, or $242 million, according to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Time Warner</ENAMEX>.
Some analysts at least are buying that argument, and weren't alarmed by the losses. ``What really matters is the operating income of the divisions: I look at these numbers and I say, these businesses are doing well,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mark Manson</ENAMEX>, a vice president of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Donaldson, Lufkin & Jenrette Securities Corp.</ENAMEX> ``For example, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> made more than $100 million from filmed entertainment in three months. That's a big number. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> also had a gain of more than 13% from records and music publishing, even though the domestic record business was sluggish this summer.''
In the year-ago third quarter, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Time</ENAMEX> on its own reported net income of $81 million, or $1.42 a share. Combined revenue for the latest quarter of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Time Warner</ENAMEX> was $2.2 billion, compared with the year-ago Time revenue of $1.1 billion.
On a pro forma basis, including all of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX>'s earnings, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Time Warner</ENAMEX> had a third-quarter loss of $217 million, compared with a $342 million loss a year earlier. On the same basis, revenue rose to $2.7 billion from $2.2 billion.
For the third quarter, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX>'s $106 million loss compared with a year-ago loss of $113 million, or 90 cents a share. Revenue rose to $1.5 billion from $1.1 billion. The 1988 figures were restated to include the results of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lorimar Telepictures Corp.</ENAMEX>, which <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> acquired in January.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Time Warner</ENAMEX>'s operating earnings got a boost from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX>'s record box-office results. ``Batman'' alone has racked up more than $247 million in box-office receipts to date, making it <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner Bros.</ENAMEX>' largest grossing film ever. ``Lethal <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Weapon II</ENAMEX>'' was also a big hit. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> also contributed record results from its music business, where unit sales of compact discs rose more than 50% from a year ago, the company said, helped by <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Prince</ENAMEX>'s ``Batman'' soundtrack.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Time Warner</ENAMEX> said its cable division turned in a 77% increase in operating cash flow, to $166 million from $94 million, reflecting higher per-subscriber revenue. In addition, the 1988 results included a $20 million charge reflecting a reserve for relocation related expenses at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Television & Communications Corp.</ENAMEX>
On the other hand, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Time Warner</ENAMEX> said its operating cash flow declined in the quarter for its magazine division, its books division and the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Home Box Office</ENAMEX> programming division. In magazines, higher advertising revenues at Sports Illustrated and Fortune were offset by lower ad revenue for other major magazines. The programming division saw a decline in operating cash flow because the year-ago quarter included a $12 million dividend from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Turner Broadcasting System</ENAMEX> and because the quarter includes expenses associated with the Nov. 15 launch of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">HBO</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Comedy Channel</ENAMEX>.
In <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> composite trading, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Time Warner</ENAMEX> closed at $138.625 a share, up $1.875, while <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> closed at $63.875 a share, up 12.5 cents.
