<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hale Milgrim</ENAMEX>, 41 years old, senior vice president, marketing at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Elecktra Entertainment Inc.</ENAMEX>, was named president of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Capitol Records Inc.</ENAMEX>, a unit of this entertainment concern. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Milgrim</ENAMEX> succeeds <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">David Berman</ENAMEX>, who resigned last month.
