<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">General Motors Corp.</ENAMEX>'s big defense and automotive electronics unit, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM Hughes Electronics</ENAMEX>, said net income fell 22% in the third quarter, reflecting declining military spending and slumping <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX> vehicle production.
Meanwhile, net at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX>'s finance arm, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">General Motors Acceptance Corp.</ENAMEX>, fell 3.1%. By contrast, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Electronic Data Systems Corp.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX>'s data processing subsidiary, boosted net 16%.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX> closed down $1.875 at $44.875 in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> trading yesterday. Earnings for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX> common stock, reflecting the performance of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX>'s core automotive operations, will be disclosed this morning. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM Class H</ENAMEX>, which represents a dividend interest in Hughes earnings, closed at $29, up 25 cents in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX> composite trading. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM Class E</ENAMEX>, which represents a dividend interest in EDS profit, fell 75 cents to $52.25 on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX>.
The earnings drop at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM Hughes Electronics</ENAMEX> is a sign of tough times at both the defense operations of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hughes Aircraft Co.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX>'s North American automotive operations, which are a primary customer for the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Delco Electronics Corp.</ENAMEX> side of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX> Hughes unit.
Profit at the unit fell to $110.6 million, or 37 cents a share, from $142.4 million, or 45 cents a share, largely because of a $24 million one-time charge associated with <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hughes</ENAMEX>'s previously  announced plan to reduce employment by at least 6,000 people by year end. Even excluding the charge, however, net fell 5%.
In addition, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX>'s North American vehicle production fell 8.4% from a year ago, which hurt <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Delco Electronic</ENAMEX>'s earnings, a company spokesman said. That decline was reflected in revenue for the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX> Hughes unit, which edged down to $2.58 billion from $2.63 billion.
At <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GMAC</ENAMEX>, net dropped 3.1% to $234.5 million from $241.9 million. The finance unit attributed the decline to higher borrowing costs compared with a year earlier. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GMAC</ENAMEX> said its automotive financing and leasing business rose 35% in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX>, largely because of dealer and customer incentives used to boost sales. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GMAC</ENAMEX> profits are combined with earnings from the rest of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX>'s operations and attributed to the company's traditional common stock.
In the first nine months, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GMAC</ENAMEX>'s earnings fell 8% to $859.5 million from $930.2 million.
In the nine months, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">EDS</ENAMEX> earned $315.8 million, or $2.62 a share, up 13% from $280.7 million, or $2.30 a share. Revenue rose 14% to $4.03 billion from $3.54 billion. Revenue from non-<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX> accounts was 45% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">EDS</ENAMEX>'s total business in the latest nine months, compared with 40% a year earlier. The company has said it wants to boost non-<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX> revenue to at least 50% of its total business by the end of 1990.
