<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Gillette Co.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Boston</ENAMEX>, said it is planning to restructure its South African subsidiary. Under the plan, Gillette <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">South Africa</ENAMEX> will sell manufacturing facilities in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Springs</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">South Africa</ENAMEX>, and its business in toiletries and plastic bags to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Twins Pharmaceuticals Ltd.</ENAMEX>, an affiliate of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Anglo American Corp.</ENAMEX>, a South African company.
Terms were not disclosed. A final agreement has not been signed, and the moves will not have a material effect on the company, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Gillette</ENAMEX> said. The company said it is part of a continuing world-wide restructuring in which it has downsized or sold operations in several countries. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Gillette</ENAMEX> said its continued presence in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">South Africa</ENAMEX> ``enables it to make meaningful contributions to South African society, to the lives of its employees and to the communities in which it operates.'' Gillette <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">South Africa</ENAMEX> employs about 250 people. About 60% of the work force will continue with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Gillette</ENAMEX> or transfer to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Twins Pharmaceuticals</ENAMEX>, the company said.
