<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Schlumberger Ltd.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>, reported third-quarter net income edged up as growth in its oil-field services sector offset a decline in interest income.
The lower interest income occurred because <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Schlumberger</ENAMEX> spent $1.2 billion buying back its stock last year.
Revenue declined 6.3% to $1.11 billion from $1.18 billion. But excluding businesses acquired or sold, revenue was flat at about $1.24 billion.
This year's nine-month results include gains of $13 million, or five cents a share, from the sale of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Schlumberger</ENAMEX>'s defense systems business, and $22 million, or nine cents a share, from an award by the Iranu.s. Claims Tribunal. The year-earlier nine months include a gain of $35 million, or 13 cents a share, from sale of the company's <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Electricity Control & Transformers</ENAMEX> division.
