<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cipher Data</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">San Diego</ENAMEX> maker of magnetic tape peripherals and optical disc drives, said the loss included reserves of $3.8 million related to a corporate restructuring.
The restructuring calls for a 24% reduction in its work force over the next two months, affecting about 525 jobs, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cipher Data</ENAMEX> said. It is eliminating the positions of president and chief operating officer, formerly held by <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Edward L. Marinaro</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cipher Data</ENAMEX> said Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Marinaro</ENAMEX> consequently has resigned from those posts and from the company's board. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Marinaro</ENAMEX> couldn't immediately be reached for comment.
