East <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rock Partners Limited Partnership</ENAMEX> said it proposed to acquire <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">A.P. Green Industries Inc.</ENAMEX> for $40 a share.
In an Oct. 19 letter to <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">A.P. Green</ENAMEX>'s board, East Rock said the offer is subject to the signing of a merger agreement by no later than Oct. 31.
An <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">A.P. Green</ENAMEX> official declined to comment on the filing. The $40-a-share proposal values the company at about $106.6 million. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">A.P. Green</ENAMEX> currently has 2,664,098 shares outstanding. Its stock closed at $38, up $1.875, in national over-the-counter trading. The company is a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mexico</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mo.</ENAMEX>, maker of refractory products.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">East Rock</ENAMEX> also said in the filing that it boosted its stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">A.P. Green</ENAMEX> to 8.7%. It now holds 233,000 A.P. Green common shares, including 30,000 shares bought last Thursday for $35.50 to $36.50 a share.
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John Kuhns</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Robert Macdonald</ENAMEX> control East <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rock Partners Inc.</ENAMEX>, the sole general partner of East <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rock Partners</ENAMEX> L.P. The sole limited partner of the partnership is Westwood Brick <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lime Inc.</ENAMEX>, an indirect subsidiary of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Westwood Group Inc.</ENAMEX> Both <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Westwood Brick</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Westwood Group</ENAMEX> are based in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Boston</ENAMEX>.
