<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Harken</ENAMEX>, which made its offer in August, said it still is awaiting a response to its offer from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tesoro</ENAMEX>'s board.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Harken</ENAMEX> also said that its financing from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bankers Trust Co.</ENAMEX> has been extended until Dec. 15 to give <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Tesoro</ENAMEX>'s board time to consider the offer at a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tesoro</ENAMEX> board meeting scheduled for mid-November.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Harken</ENAMEX>, which owns about 800 retail gas stations, has said it is particularly interested in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tesoro</ENAMEX>'s refinery because it would fill a gap in its business. However, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tesoro</ENAMEX>, based in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Houston</ENAMEX>, already has rejected a suitor in the past year.
