<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">PPG Industries Inc.</ENAMEX>, hurt by softness in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> automotive and construction industries, said third-quarter net income fell 5.5% to $106.7 million, or 97 cents a share, from $112.9 million, or $1.03 a share, a year ago.
Sales were nearly identical to the year-earlier $1.36 billion.
The drop in earnings didn't surprise analysts who said the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Pittsburgh</ENAMEX> glass, coatings and chemical concern had been predicting a slow quarter because of the sluggish construction industry, a major market for the company's flat glass.
In <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> composite trading, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">PPG</ENAMEX> closed at $41 a share, down 37.5 cents.
