A round of futures-related program selling near the close sent the stock market lower in otherwise directionless trading.
Nervousness that the market hasn't seen the last of its recent volatility kept trading at a moderate pace, as did anticipation of a report on the economy's third-quarter performance.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> Industrial Average, which plunged more than 80 points in early trading Tuesday and then recovered nearly all of its losses by the close, fell 5.94 to 2653.28 in the latest session.
The average drifted in a trading range of about 30 points throughout the day. The lower boundary was established just after the opening in a brief round of selling; the upper boundary was set at midday as scattered bargain-hunting pushed prices higher.
Buying interest in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Du Pont</ENAMEX>, which declared a stock split and a dividend boost, and certain other blue-chip issues gave the industrial average a better performance than broader indexes.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Standard & Poor</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">500-Stock Index</ENAMEX> dropped 1.20 to 342.50; the decline was the equivalent of a nine-point setback in the 30-stock average. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> Equity Market Index fell 1.16 to 320.94 and the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> Composite Index slid 0.53 to 189.52.
But advancing issues topped decliners by 784 to 700 on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX> despite the late sell programs, resulting from stock-index arbitrage. The programs occurred against the backdrop of a late pullback in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX>, which had held at slightly lower levels through most of the session amid optimism that another bidder might surface.
``People are sort of nervous to do anything in the market now. Our phones are quiet around here,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Don R. Hays</ENAMEX>, director of investment strategy at Wheat <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Butcher & Singer Inc.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Richmond</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Va.</ENAMEX>
The gross national product report, due to be released before today's opening, is expected to show that the economy continued to expand in the third quarter at a moderate pace. The consensus of economists polled by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> Capital Markets Report calls for a 2.5% annual growth rate for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GNP</ENAMEX> during the quarter.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Du Pont</ENAMEX>, which announced plans for a 3-for-1 stock split and raised its quarterly dividend by 14%, jumped 2 1/2 to 117 3/8. The company also posted third-quarter earnings that were in line with analysts' forecasts.
Blue-chip consumer stocks also provided a lift to the industrial average.
But <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">General Motors</ENAMEX> dropped 1 7/8 to 44 7/8. Its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM Hughes Electronics</ENAMEX> and financial-services units both reported that third-quarter earnings were down from a year earlier.
Anheuser-Busch plunged 4 3/8 to 38 1/2 on 3.5 million shares. Its third-quarter earnings were lower than analysts had forecast, and the company said it had lowered its projections for earnings growth through the end of 1990 because of planned price cuts.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Xerox</ENAMEX> fell 3 1/8 to 59 5/8. Disappointment with the company's earnings for the quarter led <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Prudential-Bache Securities</ENAMEX> to reduce its 1989 and 1990 earnings estimates, according to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> Professional Investor Report.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Computer Associates International</ENAMEX>, the most active <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX> issue, was another victim of an earnings-related sell-off. The stock fell 3/4 to 12 7/8 as 3.6 million shares were traded in the wake of its report that fiscal second-quarter net income fell 66% from a year ago.
Insurance stocks moved higher in the wake of a strong third-quarter earnings report from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chubb</ENAMEX>, coming on the heels of speculation that last week's devastating earthquake in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">San Francisco</ENAMEX> area would lead to higher premium rates.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Comprehensive Care</ENAMEX> plunged 4 3/4 to 3 5/8 on 1.2 million shares. The company reported a third-quarter loss and said it is holding talks with its bank lenders for an extension on some overdue debt payments.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">TW Services</ENAMEX> dropped 1 1/4 to 31 1/4 following the postponement of a $1.4 billion junk-bond offering that would have permitted <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coniston Partners</ENAMEX> to complete its takeover of the company. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coniston</ENAMEX> said it would pursue ``various financing alternatives.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> stock declined by 9 to 161 after nobody surfaced to claim credit for aggressive buying Tuesday by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bear Stearns</ENAMEX> that sent <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> stock up 35 points in a matter of hours. Tuesday's rumored buyer, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coniston Partners</ENAMEX>, wouldn't comment on speculation that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coniston</ENAMEX>, which battled the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> board in 1987, might challenge the board's decision Monday to remain independent.
Stocks that reportedly benefited Tuesday from a Japanese buy program handled by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Painewebber</ENAMEX> gave back some of their gains. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Procter & Gamble</ENAMEX> went down 3 1/2 to 130, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> fell 3 1/2 to 37 1/2 and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rockwell International</ENAMEX> dropped 2 1/8 to 25. However, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Atlantic Richfield</ENAMEX> preserved its twopoint advance in the previous session and added 1/8 to 103 7/8.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">General Mills</ENAMEX> gained 2 1/4 to 72 7/8. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Goldman Sachs</ENAMEX> placed the stock back on its list of recommended issues, raised its 1990 earnings estimate and recommended that its clients shift funds from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Kellogg</ENAMEX> to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">General Mills</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Kellogg</ENAMEX> dropped 1 3/4 to 73 1/4.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Manville</ENAMEX> advanced 3/4 to 10. The company offered to purchase $500 million of convertible preferred stock from the trust that handles its payments to asbestos victims.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Di Giorgio</ENAMEX> gained 1 to 30 3/4 after the company said it is starting negotiations with unidentified parties interested in acquiring its units. Investor <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Arthur Goldberg</ENAMEX> is pursuing a $32-a-share takeover offer.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Esselte Business Systems</ENAMEX> rose 1 to 43 1/2. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Esselte AB</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Sweden</ENAMEX> offered $43.50 a share for the 22% of the company it doesn't already own.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Public Service of New Hampshire</ENAMEX> went up 3/8 to 4. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Northeast Utilities</ENAMEX> boosted its offer to acquire the company by $400 million, to $2.25 billion.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Newell</ENAMEX>, which declared a 2-for-1 stock split and boosted its quarterly dividend by 14%, added 7/8 to 49 3/8. Also, the company posted improved third-quarter earnings.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mission Resource Partners</ENAMEX> lost 5 1/4 to 14 1/8. The partnership, which had solicited takeover offers, said it failed to receive any adequate bids for all of its operations but is reviewing offers for individual properties.
