A study of patients in eight <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Public Health Service</ENAMEX> hospitals found that cancer-related deaths among seamen were significantly higher than among other patients.
The research, recently presented at a scientific conference in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Italy</ENAMEX>, was conducted by the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.S. Public Health Service Hospital</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Staten Island</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.Y.</ENAMEX> The study was prompted by a previous finding of a similar mortality pattern among American merchant seamen who died in that hospital in 1975 and 1976.
The latest report, the first of several planned, didn't draw any direct link between the cancer death rate among seamen and asbestos used in ships as fire retardants and insulation. But <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Leonard Jaques</ENAMEX>, an admiralty attorney who handles asbestos-related cases for seamen and who provided his clients' records for the research, said ``the connection was a natural presumption.''
The researchers compared deaths between 1973 and 1978 at the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Staten Island</ENAMEX> hospital with that of the eight public health hospitals for the same period. The group found that at the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Staten Island</ENAMEX> facility, cancer was the cause of death in 55% of the seamen, compared with 28% among non-seamen; respiratory cancer accounted for one in five deaths among seamen, compared with one in 12 among non-seamen.
The data collected from the eight other hospitals showed that cancer was responsible for 46% of seamen deaths, compared with 37% among non-seamen. Respiratory cancer accounted for one in five seamen deaths versus one in eleven for non-seamen.
``The cancer mortality `excess,' particularly respiratory cancer, is not specific to the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Staten Island</ENAMEX> facility, but is characteristic of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Public Health Service Hospital System</ENAMEX> as a whole,'' the report concluded. The research group was headed by Dr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Howard R. Kelman</ENAMEX>, chief of health services research at the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Staten Island</ENAMEX> hospital.
