The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Los Angeles</ENAMEX> media concern said that the year-ago period included a $26.5 million gain from the sale of assets, primarily timberlands.
Revenue was $873.9 million, up 7.3% from $814.8 million.
Stronger results from the company's broadcast and cable television units and professional and textbook publishing divisions, plus increased advertising at the company's largest newspaper, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Los Angeles Times</ENAMEX>, offset advertising declines in the company's newspapers in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Eastern U.S.</ENAMEX>, the company said.
