<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Arnold C. Pohs</ENAMEX> was officially named president and chief executive officer of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cellular Inc.</ENAMEX>, a provider of management, financing and operating services to cellular-telephone systems.
Cellular said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Robert J. Lunday Jr.</ENAMEX>, its chairman and another founder, resigned from the company's board to pursue the sale of his telephone company, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Sandy Telecommunications Inc.</ENAMEX> A new director hasn't been named to fill that seat, which expires in 1992. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Pohs</ENAMEX> said the board probaby will elect a new chairman at its meeting Nov.
In addition, the company said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Monroe M. Rifkin</ENAMEX>, a cable television investor and consultant, was elected a director, filling a vacant seat that will expire in 1991. The board currently has six members, but is expanding to nine, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Pohs</ENAMEX> said.
