<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Georgia Gulf Corp.</ENAMEX>, hurt by declining sales and falling chemical prices, said third-quarter earnings fell 13% to $46.1 million from $53.1 million in the year-earlier  period.
Sales declined 10% to $251.2 million from $278.7 million.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Atlanta</ENAMEX>-based chemical manufacturer said lower prices hurt margins for most products. ``We did see some relief in raw material costs, but it wasn't sufficient to offset the drop in sales prices,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">James R. Kuse</ENAMEX>, the company's chairman and chief executive officer said in a statement.
In composite <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> trading, stock in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Georgia Gulf</ENAMEX>, which has been mentioned as a takeover candidate, rose $2.125 a share to close at $46.125.
