<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coda Energy Inc.</ENAMEX> said it arranged a $50 million credit facility with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NCNB Texas National Bank</ENAMEX>, a unit of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NCNB Corp.</ENAMEX>, of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Charlotte</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.C.</ENAMEX>
The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dallas</ENAMEX> oil and gas concern said that $10 million of the facility would be used to consolidate the company's $8.1 million of existing bank debt, to repurchase 4 million of its 4.9 million shares outstanding of Series D convertible preferred stock, and to purchase a 10% net-profits interest in certain oil and gas properties from one of its existing lenders, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">National Canada Corp.</ENAMEX> The remaining $40 million can be used over three years for oil and gas acquisitions, the company said.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ted Eubank</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Coda</ENAMEX>'s president, said the loan carries an interest rate of prime plus one percentage point, with 85% of the company's net oil and gas revenue each month dedicated to repayment. The company put up ``virtually all'' of its oil and gas properties as collateral, he said.
