<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tandy Corp.</ENAMEX>, citing sluggish sales of consumer-electronics goods, said net income dropped 3.3% for the first quarter ended Sept. 30.
The results, which represented the fifth consecutive quarter of flat-to-lower earnings for the big electronics retailer, disappointed analysts and traders. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tandy</ENAMEX>'s stock fell $1.375 a share to close at $44 in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> composite trading.
Net for the quarter was $62.8 million, or 73 cents a share, down from $64.9 million, or 72 cents a share, a year earlier. The company said earnings would have increased if it hadn't been actively repurchasing its shares, thus increasing its interest expense and reducing its interest income. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tandy</ENAMEX> had 86.3 million shares outstanding at Sept. 30, down from 90 million a year earlier.
Revenue rose 5% to $986 million from $937 million.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tandy</ENAMEX> said consumer electronics sales at its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Radio Shack</ENAMEX> stores have been slow, partly because of a lack of hot, new products.
``Radio Shack continues to be lackluster,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dennis Telzrow</ENAMEX>, analyst with <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Eppler</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Guerin & Turner</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dallas</ENAMEX>. He said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tandy</ENAMEX> ``has done a decent job'' increasing sales by manufacturing computers for others and expanding sales of its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Grid Systems Corp.</ENAMEX> subsidiary, which sells computers to bigger businesses, but ``it's not enough to offset the problems at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Radio Shack.</ENAMEX>'' Sales at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Radio Shack</ENAMEX> stores open more than a year grew only 2% in the quarter from a year earlier, he said.
As a result, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Telzrow</ENAMEX> said he cut his fiscal 1990 per-share earnings estimate for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tandy</ENAMEX> to $4.05 from $4.20. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tandy</ENAMEX> earned $88.8 million, or $3.64 a share, in the year ended June 30.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Barry Bryant</ENAMEX>, an analyst with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Drexel Burnham Lambert Inc.</ENAMEX>, said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tandy</ENAMEX> also has suffered from lethargic sales of its computers aimed at the home and small-office market, which are less-advanced and cheaper than computers aimed at the corporate market.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tandy</ENAMEX> has added several new products to that line, including a laptop computer priced around $1,000, and is focusing its advertising on the easy-to-use software that is packaged with its machines. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bryant</ENAMEX> and other analysts hope all those moves will combine to help <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tandy</ENAMEX>'s results improve in the important Christmas quarter.
``They've been promising 13% to 15% growth based on the strategic moves they've made,'' he said. ``If the earnings acceleration is to take place, that should be the quarter.
