<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Esselte AB</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Stockholm</ENAMEX> office supplies company, as expected, proposed to acquire the 22% it doesn't own of its U.S. unit, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Esselte Business Systems Inc.</ENAMEX>
The price in the proposal is $43.50 for each of the 4.9 million shares the parent doesn't own, or $213.2 million.
In <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> composite trading, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Esselte</ENAMEX> closed yesterday at $43.50 a share, up $1.
A committee of outside directors for the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Garden City</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.Y.</ENAMEX>, unit is evaluating the proposal; the parent asked it to respond by Oct. 31. The unit said it can provide no assurance a transaction will occur.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Esselte AB</ENAMEX> sold the minority stake five years ago in a $40 million international share offering. The unit, which is the holding company for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Esselte</ENAMEX>'s non-Swedish units, accounted for 58% of sales and 71% of operating profit last year.
