<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Braniff Inc.</ENAMEX> said it has retained <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merrill Lynch</ENAMEX> Capital Markets to advise it on alternatives -- including a possible sale -- as the cash-strapped airline maneuvers through bankruptcy-law court proceedings.
The carrier, a unit of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">BIA</ENAMEX>-<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">COR Holding Inc.</ENAMEX>, sought Chapter 11 protection Sept. 28, a day after it abruptly canceled flights and laid off 2,800 employees. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Braniff</ENAMEX>, which had launched ambitious expansion plans over the past year, blamed its difficulties on the collapse of expected financing.
It was <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Braniff</ENAMEX>'s second bankruptcy-law filing in a decade. The carrier sought Chapter 11 protection in 1982, emerging with new owners -- the <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Pritzker</ENAMEX> family -- who sold it in 1988 to a group of real estate investors.
A bankruptcy court in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Orlando</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Fla.</ENAMEX>, where the case is being heard, approved <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Braniff</ENAMEX>'s request to retain <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merrill Lynch</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Braniff</ENAMEX> currently operates 46 daily flights to 11 cities. Before the filing, it flew to more than 40 cities.
