<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Di Giorgio Corp.</ENAMEX> said it's continuing talks with potential buyers of certain units, but has reached no agreement on any deals.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Di Giorgio</ENAMEX>, a food wholesaler and building products maker, is seeking alternatives to an unsolicited $32-a-share tender offer of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">DIG Acquisition Corp.</ENAMEX>, a unit of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rose Partners Limited Partnership</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">DIG</ENAMEX> is the vehicle being used to pursue to acquisition.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Robert Mellor</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Di Giorgio</ENAMEX>'s executive vice president, said the company stands to reap more money through the sale of individual units to others than by accepting <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">DIG</ENAMEX>'s offer.
