<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Capital Cities/ABC Inc.</ENAMEX>'s net income rose 29% on a modest 9% increase in revenue in the third quarter, mainly on strong advertising demand at its <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">ABC</ENAMEX> television network operation.
Demand for ads also rose at the eight TV stations <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Capital Cities</ENAMEX> owns and at its 80%-owned <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ESPN</ENAMEX> sports cable channel.
The broadcast and publishing company reported net climbed to $80.8 million, or $4.56 a share, from $62.6 million, or $3.55 a share, in the year-earlier period. Revenue reached $1.1 billion from $1.01 billion.
In <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> composite trading yesterday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Capital Cities</ENAMEX> closed at $558.50, down $5.
The broadcasting unit reported operating profit of $134.9 million, up 18% from the year-earlier $114.3 million. Publishing reported operating profit was $33.3 million, nearly flat with the year-before $33 million.
Revenue at the broadcasting unit, consisting of the network and stations, advanced 11%, to $838 million from $752.9 million. The publishing unit reported revenue edged up 2.6% to $263.2 million from $256.6 million. Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Thomas S. Murphy</ENAMEX> cited <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Capital Cities</ENAMEX>' nine daily newspapers in explaining most of the gain. The parent also publishes weeklies, shopping guides and specialty magazines.
