<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">A.H. Belo Corp.</ENAMEX> said it asked the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal Communications Commission</ENAMEX> to dismiss a request by the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dallas</ENAMEX> Times <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Herald</ENAMEX> calling for the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FCC</ENAMEX> to revoke <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Belo</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dallas</ENAMEX> television license.
In a response to the commission, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Belo</ENAMEX>, owner of the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dallas</ENAMEX> Morning <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">News</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">WFAA</ENAMEX>-TV in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dallas</ENAMEX> and other TV stations, said that the Times <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Herald</ENAMEX>'s complaint is ``without merit'' and is an effort to gain leverage in a legal battle.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dallas</ENAMEX> Times <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Herald</ENAMEX> filed the request with the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FCC</ENAMEX> earlier this month, charging that an agreement between <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Belo</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Universal Press Syndicate</ENAMEX> is intended to eliminate newspaper competition in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dallas</ENAMEX>. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Belo</ENAMEX>-Universal agreement calls for the two companies to study developing television programs based on <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Universal</ENAMEX>'s features. As part of the agreement, Universal moved 26 features, including ``Doonesbury,'' ``The Far Side'' and Dear <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Abby</ENAMEX>, to the Morning News from the Times <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Herald</ENAMEX>.
A lawsuit filed by the Times <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Herald</ENAMEX> against <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Belo</ENAMEX> charging antitrust law violations and interference with a contract is pending in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Houston</ENAMEX> state court.
