PROGRAM TRADING is being curbed by more securities firms, but big institutional investors are expected to continue the practice, further roiling the stock market. Bowing to criticism, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bear Stearns</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Morgan Stanley</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Oppenheimer</ENAMEX> joined <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Painewebber</ENAMEX> in suspending stock-index arbitrage trading for their own accounts. Still, stock-index funds are expected to continue launching big programs through the market.
Several <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX> firms are organizing to complain about program trading and the exchange's role in it. The effort is being led by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Contel</ENAMEX>.
Personal spending rose 0.2% in September, the smallest gain in a year. The slowdown raises questions about the economy's strength because spending fueled much of the third-quarter GNP growth. Meanwhile, personal income edged up 0.3%.
Factory owners are buying new machinery at a healthy rate this fall, machine-tool makers say. But weak car sales raise questions about future demand from the auto sector.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">LIN Broadcasting</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bellsouth</ENAMEX> sweetened their plan to merge cellular phone operations, offering LIN holders a special $42-a-share payout. But the new pact will force huge debt on the new firm and could still fail to thwart rival suitor <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mccaw Cellular.</ENAMEX>
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Unisys</ENAMEX> posted a $648.2 million loss for the third quarter as it moved quickly to take write-offs for various problems and prepare for a turnaround. But some analysts wonder how strong the recovery will be.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">RJR Nabisco</ENAMEX> agreed to sell three candy businesses to Nestle for $370 million. The accord helps RJR pay off debt and boosts <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nestle</ENAMEX>'s 7% share of the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> candy market to 12%.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> are expected to go head to head in the markets to buy up rival 15% stakes in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX> confirmed it received U.S. antitrust clearance to boost its holding.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sansui Electric</ENAMEX> agreed to sell a 51% stake to <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Polly Peck</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> for $110 million. Still, analysts said the accord doesn't suggest <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX> is opening up to more foreign takeovers.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Insurers</ENAMEX> could see claims totaling nearly $1 billion from the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">San Francisco</ENAMEX> earthquake, far less than the $4 billion from Hurricane Hugo.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mobil</ENAMEX> is cutting back its <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> oil and gas exploration and production group by up to 15% as part of a restructuring of the business.
Markets --
Dollar: 141.65 yen, off 0.45; 1.8300 marks, off 0.0100.
