<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rorer Group Inc.</ENAMEX> will report that third-quarter profit rose more than 15% from a year earlier, though the gain is wholly due to asset sales, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Robert Cawthorn</ENAMEX>, chairman, president and chief executive officer, said.
Growth of 10% would make sales for the latest quarter $269 million, compared with $244.6 million a year ago.
As the gain from the sales indicates, operating profit was ``significantly'' below the year-earlier level, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Cawthorn</ENAMEX> said. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rorer</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">July</ENAMEX> had projected lower third-quarter operating profit but higher profit for all of 1989. He said the company is still looking for ``a strong fourth quarter in all areas -- sales, operating income and net income.''
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Cawthorn</ENAMEX> attributed the decline in third-quarter operating profit to the stronger dollar, which reduces the value of overseas profit when it is translated into dollars; to accelerated buying of Rorer products in the second quarter because of a then-pending July 1 price increase, and to higher marketing expenses for <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Rorer</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Maalox antacid</ENAMEX>, whose sales and market share in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> had slipped in the first half of 1989. He said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rorer</ENAMEX> opted to sell <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Asilone</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Thrombinar</ENAMEX> to raise revenue that would ``kick start'' its increased marketing efforts behind Maalox, still its top-selling product with about $215 million in world-wide sales in 1988. ``We had underfunded Maalox for a year,'' he said, because the company was concentrating on research and development and promoting other drugs.
