Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jones</ENAMEX> takes heart. There in the center of the pack is quarterback <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Troy Aikman</ENAMEX>, the key to the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cowboys</ENAMEX>' comeback strategy. So key, in fact, that Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jones</ENAMEX> signed him in April for $11.4 million over the next six years -- a record for a rookie. ``He's a genuine Wheaties-box athlete,'' gushes Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jones</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ah</ENAMEX>, the glamour of professional sports. For Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jones</ENAMEX>, losing his quarterback temporarily was just the latest in a string of setbacks that has beset the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dallas</ENAMEX> Cowboys -- and, this year, much of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">National Football League</ENAMEX>. Once fat and happy, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cowboys</ENAMEX> now are losing games, fans and money. Last year, the team ended up $2 million in the red on $30 million in revenue. It has some of the highest costs in the league. Its attendance is off 23% from six years ago.
At the very least, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jones</ENAMEX>, who cultivates the society circuit as eagerly as his bench, can take comfort in one fact: These days, he isn't alone. Nearly half the owners of the 28 <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">National Football</ENAMEX> League teams are losing money, the result of flat attendance, aging stadiums and -- more than anything -- skyrocketing salaries for star players like Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Aikman</ENAMEX>.
Last year, the top 12 players on each <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NFL</ENAMEX> team took home an average $536,000, a figure comparable to baseball and higher than in basketball. First-round draft picks have done even better: Average salaries and bonuses for them rose to $685,000 this year, up 44% from 1987. ``It's a vicious circle,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Art Modell</ENAMEX>, owner of the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Cleveland</ENAMEX> Browns. ``One team pays so much and the other pays more. We just don't have that kind of income stream.''
All this is causing convulsions in professional football. Owners, largely complacent in the past, are now almost desperately looking for ways to lower costs and raise revenue -- embracing some revolutionary ideas in the process. Though not intentionally, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cowboys</ENAMEX>' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jones</ENAMEX> has come to represent this new breed of owner.
For Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jones</ENAMEX>, it was just the beginning. He quickly cut the team's bloated administrative staff by half, shut down a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cowboys</ENAMEX>-owned dance academy and, in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">July</ENAMEX>, announced plans to sell Valley Ranch, the team's 30-acre practice camp and the most lavish training facility in the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NFL</ENAMEX>. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jones</ENAMEX> calls the ranch ``the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pentagon</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Sportdom.</ENAMEX>'' It is a maze of halls that connects film rooms, elaborate spas and weight-training centers that testify to a richer, more free-spending era. He likes to tell the yarn of how he got lost on the expansive ranch during an early visit, took refuge in an office and called the front desk for help. ``I said, `Somebody come get me. I'm at extension 29.'''
And as for <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Tom Landry</ENAMEX>, well, in Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jones</ENAMEX>'s mind, he had played out his winning years. After posting losing seasons in each of the last three years, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cowboys</ENAMEX> needed a change, he says.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Football</ENAMEX> has long been Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jones</ENAMEX>'s passion, both on and off the field. An <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Arkansas</ENAMEX> native, he started at guard on the undefeated 1964 <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">University of Arkansas</ENAMEX> team that won a national championship. After college, he worked at his father's insurance company in Little Rock, and in 1966 led an aborted attempt to buy the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">San Diego Chargers</ENAMEX>. Years later, with cash from the sale of the insurance company, he founded <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Arkoma Production Corp.</ENAMEX>, an oil and gas exploration company based in Little Rock.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jones</ENAMEX> is attacking the problem on several fronts. He continues to reshuffle the team, trading famed running back <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Herschel Walker</ENAMEX> to the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Minnesota</ENAMEX> Vikings this month for a slew of players and future draft picks. To try to draw more fans, he has dropped end-zone ticket prices from $25 to $19. But the general trend, given rising costs in the league, has been to raise prices, and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jones</ENAMEX> is expected to eventually follow suit. ``It's simple,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lamar Hunt</ENAMEX>, who owns the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Kansas City</ENAMEX> Chiefs and last year raised ticket prices by $2.40 to an average $17. ``If we didn't increase prices, we'd be in the red.''
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jones</ENAMEX> has also beefed up his marketing staff to sell the 118 luxury suites topping <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Texas</ENAMEX> Stadium (his deal with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bum</ENAMEX> Bright included operating rights for the stadium). The suites are air-conditioned, have wet bars and plush seating, and offer a clear view of the field -- all for a sale price of $475,000 to $1 million, depending on their size and location. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jones</ENAMEX> has been taking prospective suite owners onto the field during practice to let them rub elbows with players, and promises those who actually buy one of the rooms an insider's look at the team's strategy before game time. The sales job seems to be paying off: When he bought the team, only six of the suites had been sold. Today, 30 have.
This wage inflation is bleeding the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NFL</ENAMEX> dry, the owners contend. Soon, only large corporations will be able to afford to buy and run football teams, predicts <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John J. Veatch Jr.</ENAMEX>, an investment banker with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Salomon Brothers</ENAMEX> who handled the Cowboys sale. To tackle the problem, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NFL</ENAMEX> owners have proposed setting a rookie wage scale to try to rein in salaries. Details of the plan, which would go into effect in 1993, are sketchy, but each player would apparently be paid a base salary keyed to his position and ability. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bonuses</ENAMEX> would be paid based on playing time and performance.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NFL Players Association</ENAMEX>, meanwhile, contends that athletes are paid a wage commensurate with their ability to draw fans, and that some owners are in financial trouble because of poor business management, not players' salaries.
The owners are trying to boost profit in other ways, too. Many have launched promotions to attract new fans and are renegotiating dated stadium contracts. Most of the owners must pay up to 10% of gross ticket sales for leases on stadiums they say are either too small or too old. In <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chicago</ENAMEX>, for example, size is the issue.
``We have the worst lease in the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NFL</ENAMEX>,'' contends <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Michael B. Mccaskey</ENAMEX>, the president of the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chicago</ENAMEX> Bears and a grandson of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">George Halas</ENAMEX>, who founded the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NFL</ENAMEX>'s predecessor organization. ``We're in a metro area with millions of Bear fans, and only a small number can be accommodated.'' When the lease expires in 1999, he says, ``It's got to be changed.''
This year, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NFL</ENAMEX> also imposed an 80-player limit on teams going into training camp, down from 120, in a move meant to trim payroll costs. And the league is trying to get more for its three-year national network contract, which expires after this season. The current contract pays the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NFL</ENAMEX> $1.4 billion. Owners say they expect the league to demand a 50% increase, despite the fact that televised football games have had lackluster ratings. An <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NFL</ENAMEX> spokesman also says the league will probably expand its offerings to cable TV companies like <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ESPN</ENAMEX>.
Besides, to a large extent, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jones</ENAMEX> may already be getting what he wants out of the team, even though it keeps losing. Owning the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cowboys</ENAMEX> has bought him entree to a glitzy life that drilling for oil in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Arkansas</ENAMEX> just didn't provide. There is the new private jet, the platoon of assistants, invitations to the best parties, and television appearances on shows such as ``Prime <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Time Live.</ENAMEX>'' A few weeks ago, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jones</ENAMEX> even entertained <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Elizabeth Taylor</ENAMEX> in his private suite at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Texas Stadium.</ENAMEX>
``You're in the catbird seat every day in this job,'' he says.
