Market makers in Nasdaq over-the-counter stocks are adding their voices to the swelling chorus of complaints about program trading.
Some of these problems are neither new nor unique to the OTC market. But the big, often tumultuous slide in stock prices this month has turned some of those who have been profiting from the practice against it.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peter Dapuzzo</ENAMEX>, head of retail equity trading at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Shearson Lehman Hutton</ENAMEX>, acknowledges that he wasn't troubled by program trading when it began in the pre-crash bull market because it added liquidity and people were pleased to see stock prices rising.
``We weren't as concerned until they became sell programs,'' says Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dapuzzo</ENAMEX>, who now thinks it adds unnecessary volatility. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Shearson Lehman</ENAMEX>, however, executes program trades for clients.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merrill Lynch</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Goldman Sachs</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Kidder Peabody</ENAMEX>, in addition to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Shearson</ENAMEX>, do program-trade OTC stocks. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Shearson</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merrill Lynch</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Goldman Sachs</ENAMEX> say they do so only for customers, however. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Kidder Peabody</ENAMEX> does program trading for its own as well as clients' accounts.
Of course, there were sell programs in past years, too, but they seem to hurt market makers more painfully these days. That's largely because of defensive measures they adopted after the 1987 crash, when individual investors fled the market and trading activity dwindled. Market makers, to cut costs, slashed inventories of stocks they keep on hand to sell investors when other holders aren't selling.
And to protect their reduced capital investment from eroding further, market makers became quicker to lower price quotes when sell programs are in progress. On days when prices are tumbling, they must be willing to buy shares from sellers when no one else will. In such an environment, market makers can suffer huge losses both on trades made that day at steadily dropping prices and in the value of their inventories of shares.
``It makes no sense for us to put money at risk when you know you're going to lose,'' says Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Antolini</ENAMEX>, of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Donaldson Lufkin.</ENAMEX>
But this skittishness, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Antolini</ENAMEX> says, is creating liquidity problems in certain OTC stocks. ``It's harder to sell stocks when the sell programs come in because some market makers don't want to {take the orders}. No one has big positions and no one wants to take big risks.''
The OTC stocks in the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">S&P</ENAMEX> 500 include <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nasdaq</ENAMEX>'s biggest, such as <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Apple Computer</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MCI Communications</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tele-Communications</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Liz Claiborne</ENAMEX>. These big stocks greatly influence the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nasdaq</ENAMEX> Composite Index. When the computers say ``sell,'' the composite tumbles as well as the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> Industrial Average.
The problem, market makers say, is that while the industrial average and the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">S&P</ENAMEX> 500 usually recover as buy programs kick in, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nasdaq</ENAMEX> Composite frequently is left behind.
Eight trading days after Oct. 12, the day before the stock market plunge, for instance, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nasdaq</ENAMEX> Composite had fallen 4.3%, compared with 3.3% for the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">S&P</ENAMEX> 500, 3.5% for the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> Composite Index and 3.6% for the industrial average. This gap eventually closes, but slowly. Three days later, as of Friday's close, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nasdaq</ENAMEX> Composite was down 6%, compared with 5.9% for the industrial average, 5.7% for the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">S&P</ENAMEX> 500 and 5.8% for the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX> Composite.
The main reason for this lag is that individual investors own 65% of the OTC market's capitalization, according to Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hardiman</ENAMEX>, much more than on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX>. Such investors tend to be more cautious than institutional investors are about re-entering the market after massive selloffs, market makers say.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nasdaq</ENAMEX> Composite Index tumbled 5.39, or 1.2% to 452.76 on Friday. For the week, the index dropped 3.8%.
Weakness in big technology stocks hurt the composite as well as the Nasdaq 100 Index, which fell 1.4%, or 6.43, on Friday, to 437.68. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nasdaq Financial Index</ENAMEX> lost about 1%, or 3.95, to 448.80.
The revised <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">LIN</ENAMEX>-<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bellsouth</ENAMEX> agreement boosts the dollar amount of the special dividend LIN promises to pay shareholders. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">LIN</ENAMEX> now plans to dole out $42 a share in cash, up from the earlier $20 amount.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Kirschner</ENAMEX> Medical fell 4 to 15. The company said its third-quarter earnings will probably be lower than the 16 cents a share it reported last year, despite a rise in the company's revenue. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Kirschner</ENAMEX> earned $376,000 on revenue of $14.5 million in the 1988 quarter. The company blamed a number of factors for the earnings decline, including softer sales of joint-implants.
