<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX>'s stock regained most of an early loss amid speculation one or more investors may challenge the airline's decision to stay independent. The stock closed down $8.375, at $170, after plunging $33, to $145.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> may seek all of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX>, setting the stage for a possible bidding war with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> has been discussing an alliance with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX>, but <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX>'s move may derail the talks.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Norfolk Southern</ENAMEX>'s board approved a buy-back of up to 45 million shares, valued at over $1.7 billion. The repurchase, coupled with an earlier buyback, will reduce the firm's shares outstanding by over 26%.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">PS New Hampshire</ENAMEX> received a sweetened $2.25 billion offer from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Northeast Utilities</ENAMEX>, likely spurring a new round of bidding for the utility.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GE</ENAMEX> executives were accused by U.S. prosecutors of providing ``misleading and false'' data to the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pentagon</ENAMEX> in 1985 to cover up ``longstanding fraudulent'' billing practices.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Texaco</ENAMEX> said profit rose 11% in the quarter, partly due to a massive restructuring. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sun</ENAMEX> posted a gain. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mobil</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Shell</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chevron</ENAMEX> had declines.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sears</ENAMEX> posted a 16% drop in third-quarter profit as U.S. retail operations recorded the first loss in over five years. The results show <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sears</ENAMEX> is struggling to attract shoppers.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cray Research</ENAMEX> expects supercomputer sales to be flat next year, the latest in a series of negative announcements by the company.
Short interest increased 6% in the Nasdaq over-the-counter market for the month ended Oct. 13.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Salomon</ENAMEX> posted an unexpectedly big gain in quarterly earnings, aided by its securities trading and investment banking activities.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Procter & Gamble</ENAMEX>'s profit surged 38% in its latest fiscal quarter, aided by a gain from a legal settlement and continued growth overseas.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Goodyear</ENAMEX>'s profit rose 11% in the quarter, buoyed by improved operating  results in its tire business.
Markets --
Dollar: 141.45 yen, off 0.45; 1.8355 marks, off 0.0115.
