<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ocean Drilling & Exploration Co.</ENAMEX> will sell its contract-drilling business, and took a $50.9 million loss from discontinued operations in the third quarter because of the planned sale.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New Orleans</ENAMEX> oil and gas exploration and diving operations company added that it doesn't expect any further adverse financial impact from the restructuring.
In the third quarter, the company, which is 61%-owned by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Murphy Oil Corp.</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Arkansas</ENAMEX>, had a net loss of $46.9 million, or 91 cents a share, compared with a restated loss of $9 million, or 18 cents a share, a year ago. The latest period had profit from continuing operations of $4 million. Revenue gained 13% to $77.3 million from $68.5 million.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ocean Drilling</ENAMEX> said it will offer 15% to 20% of the contract-drilling business through an initial public offering in the near future. It has long been rumored that Ocean Drilling would sell the unit to concentrate on its core oil and gas business.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ocean Drilling</ENAMEX> said it won't hold any shares of the new company after the restructuring.
