<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">General Motors Corp.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford Motor Co.</ENAMEX> are now going head to head in the markets for shares of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar PLC</ENAMEX>, as <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX> got early clearance from the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal Trade Commission</ENAMEX> to boost its stake in the British luxury car maker.
A spokesman for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX>, the No. 1 auto maker, declined to say how many <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> shares that company owns. In late trading Friday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> shares bucked the downward tide in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX>'s stock market and rose five pence to 725 pence ($11.44). Trading volume was a moderately heavy 3.1 million shares. In the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX>'s American depositary receipts were among the most active issues Friday in national over-the-counter trading where they closed at $11.625 each, up 62.5 cents.
Analysts expect that the two U.S. auto giants will move quickly to buy up 15% stakes in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX>, setting up a potential bidding war for the prestigious <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> brand.
British government restrictions prevent any single shareholder from going beyond 15% before the end of 1990 without government permission. The British government, which owned <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> until 1984, still holds [a] controlling ``golden share'' in the company.
With the golden share as protection, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> officials have rebuffed <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX>'s overtures, and moved instead to forge an alliance with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> officials have indicated they are close to wrapping up a friendly alliance with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX> that would preserve <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX>'s independence, but no deal has been announced. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX>, on the other hand, has said it's willing to bid for all of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX>, despite the objections of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> chairman Sir <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John Egan</ENAMEX>. Analysts continued to speculate late last week that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> may try to force the issue by calling for a special shareholder's meeting and urging that the government and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> holders remove the barriers to a full bidding contest before December 1990. But a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> spokeswoman in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dearborn</ENAMEX> said Friday the company hasn't requested such a meeting yet.
Individuals close to the situation believe <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> officials will seek a meeting this week with Sir <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John</ENAMEX> to outline their proposal for a full bid. Any discussions with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> could postpone the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX>-<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX> deal, headed for completion within the next two weeks. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX> agreement is expected to retain <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX>'s independence by involving an eventual 30% stake for the U.S. auto giant as well as joint manufacturing and marketing ventures.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX> hope to win <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> shareholders approval for the accord partly by structuring it in a way that wouldn't preclude a full <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> bid once the golden share expires. ``There's either a minority {stake} package capable of getting <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> shareholder approval or there isn't,'' said one knowledgeable individual. ``If there isn't, {the deal} won't be put forward'' to shareholders.
Union sentiment also could influence shareholder reaction to a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX>-<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX> accord. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX>'s U.K. unit holds crucial talks today with union officials about its consideration of an Ellesmere Port site for its first major engine plant in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX>. One auto-industry union leader said, ``If they try to build it somewhere else {in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Europe</ENAMEX>} besides the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.K.</ENAMEX>, they are going to be in big trouble'' with unionists over any <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> deal.
