<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Consolidated Rail Corp.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>, reported that third-quarter net income climbed 4.8% to $87 million, or $1.27 a share, exceeding analysts' expectations.
In the year-earlier quarter, the freight railroad earned $83 million, or $1.21 a share. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">James A. Hagen</ENAMEX>, chairman and chief executive officer, noted that earnings advanced ``in the face of a drop in business, brought on by the general economic slowdown.'' Revenue slipped 4.6% to $835 million from $876 million.
For the rest of 1989, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hagen</ENAMEX> said, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Conrail</ENAMEX>'s traffic and revenue ``will reflect the sluggish economy, but Conrail will continue to take steps to control and reduce costs.''
