<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Merchants & Manufacturers Inc.</ENAMEX> said its president, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Uzi Ruskin</ENAMEX>, withdrew his proposal to acquire control of the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> textile and clothing company.
Last month, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ruskin</ENAMEX> proposed, among other things, to buy 3.5 million shares, or 38%, for $4 apiece. Coupled with his current 1.2 million shares and 4% held by an associate, the stake would have given him control of 55% of the concern.
A special committee of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Merchants</ENAMEX> directors said that in view of uncertainties regarding various legal and financial considerations, it couldn't recommend the plan to the full board.
The company is exploring, with a major financial institution, the development of a plan to boost the value of the company for its holders, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ruskin</ENAMEX> said.
In a separate <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">SEC</ENAMEX> filing, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Albert Safer</ENAMEX>, who holds 6.46% of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">United Merchants</ENAMEX>, said he retained investment bank <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lazard Freres & Co.</ENAMEX> for advice as he evaluates the possibility of making a bid for the textile maker. On Friday, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Safer</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Newark</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.J.</ENAMEX>, textile businessman, signed a confidentiality agreement under which <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Merchants</ENAMEX> would provide him with nonpublic information.
