The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nuclear Regulatory Commission</ENAMEX> ruled unanimously that the financial troubles facing the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Seabrook</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.H.</ENAMEX>, nuclear-power plant have no impact on whether the plant receives a full-power license.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NRC</ENAMEX> rejected Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Shannon</ENAMEX>'s argument that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Public Service Co. of New Hampshire</ENAMEX>, which owns the largest share of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Seabrook</ENAMEX>, and 11 other owners are financially unable to guarantee the plant's safe operation. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Shannon</ENAMEX> was seeking a waiver of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NRC</ENAMEX> policy that ignores financial considerations in making licensing decisions.
``The commissioners found the circumstances of the case didn't undercut the assurance from government rate setters of available funds adequate for safe operation,'' said a commission spokesman.
