<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Times Co.</ENAMEX> said net income rose in the third quarter because of a one-time gain on the sale of the company's cable-TV system.
Exclusive of the gain, operating profit declined 35% to $16.4 million, or 21 cents a share, from $25.2 million, or 31 cents a share. The decline primarily reflected the dilution from acquiring <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mccall</ENAMEX>'s, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Golf World</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX>) and Sailing World magazines; lower equity earnings from the forest-products group because of price discounting and an unfavorable exchange rate, and an 8.7% decline in advertising linage at the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Times</ENAMEX>, the company's flagship newspaper. Advertising volume at the company's 35 regional newspapers decreased 1.1%. The company said the negative factors are expected to continue into next year.
Revenue rose 6.4% to $415.3 million from $390.5 million.
