<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mccaw Cellular Communications Inc.</ENAMEX> said it sent a letter to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">LIN Broadcasting Corp.</ENAMEX> clarifying its revised tender offer for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">LIN</ENAMEX> and asking LIN to conduct ``a fair auction.''
The letter apparently came in response to a request for clarification by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">LIN</ENAMEX> earlier this week. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">LIN</ENAMEX>, which has agreed with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bellsouth Corp.</ENAMEX> to merge their cellular-telephone businesses, said then that it wouldn't take a position on <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mccaw</ENAMEX>'s revised tender offer.
The letter outlines broad powers for an independent group of directors provided for in the revised offer. In a statement, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Craig O. Mccaw</ENAMEX>, chairman and chief executive officer of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mccaw</ENAMEX>, said: ``We trust <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">LIN</ENAMEX> will take no further actions that favor <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bellsouth</ENAMEX>.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mccaw</ENAMEX> said the three independent directors provided for in the offer would be designated by the current board. The successors would be nominated by the independent directors.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">LIN</ENAMEX> would have a priority right to pursue all opportunities to acquire <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> cellular interests in markets other than those in which <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mccaw</ENAMEX> holds an interest, or which are contiguous to those markets, unless <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">LIN</ENAMEX> has an interest there or contiguous to it. Independent directors would have veto rights to any acquisition if they unanimously decide it isn't in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">LIN</ENAMEX>'s best interest.
Independent directors would be able to block transactions they unanimously deem would be likely to depress the private market value of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">LIN</ENAMEX> at the time it is to be sold in five years.
If <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">LIN</ENAMEX> is put up for sale rather than purchased by <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mccaw</ENAMEX> in five years, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mccaw</ENAMEX> won't submit a bid unless the independent directors request it, and the independent directors will run the bidding. The directors would be able to sell particular assets to enable such buyers as the regional Bell operating companies to purchase the company's interests.
