<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">International Proteins Corp.</ENAMEX> definitively agreed to pay $49 million and 2,850,000 of its shares for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hanson PLC</ENAMEX>'s Ground Round restaurant subsidiary.
Shareholders of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">International Proteins</ENAMEX>, a food and agriproducts company, will vote on the transaction at a meeting late next month. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hanson</ENAMEX> is a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX> producer of consumer and other goods.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">International Proteins</ENAMEX> shares didn't trade yesterday on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Stock Exchange</ENAMEX>. They closed Tuesday in composite trading at $13.625, down 37.5 cents, giving the stock portion of the transaction an indicated value of $38.8 million.
