<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ekco Group Inc.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Nashua</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.H.</ENAMEX>, expects to report that net income in the third quarter, ended Oct. 1, fell 50% to 60% from $2.1 million, or 11 cents a share, a year earlier.
But Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stein</ENAMEX> said he is ``reasonably confident'' that earnings for the full year will exceed the $3.1 million, or 17 cents a share, in 1988. That would require fourth-quarter net of more than about 22 cents to 24 cents a share, assuming that Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stein</ENAMEX>'s third-quarter estimate proves accurate. In the year-earlier fourth quarter, the company had profit of $2.7 million, or 15 cents a share.
Third-quarter revenue is expected to be $40 million to $45 million, up from $38.2 million a year earlier, according to <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Neil Gordon</ENAMEX>, treasurer. The year-earlier periods don't reflect results of the company's <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Woodstream Corp.</ENAMEX> unit, acquired last January, but include some Canadian operations that were sold at the end of 1988.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stein</ENAMEX> said tighter operating controls have enabled Ekco to reduce inventory levels 25% to 30%; improve on-time delivery of orders to about 95% from around 70%; and to lower the number of labor hours required to produce a unit. By moving the design of new products in-house -- instead of contracting out the work -- the company also has been able to come up with designs that can be manufactured more efficiently, he said.
In addition to those measures, the company spent heavily earlier this year to install displays at its customers' retail outlets -- a strategy that Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stein</ENAMEX> said has helped bolster awareness of the company's brands.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ekco</ENAMEX>'s housewares operation makes kitchen tools and gadgets, as well as bakeware, at factories in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Canada</ENAMEX>. The main issue in the strike at the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ohio</ENAMEX> facility was health-care benefits, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stein</ENAMEX> said. The strike ended Oct.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ekco</ENAMEX> continues to seek further acquisitions in the consumer-products industry, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stein</ENAMEX> said. He indicated that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ekco</ENAMEX> may be interested in acquiring another company with revenue in the range of $75 million to $100 million, partly because mass merchandisers increasingly want to rely on larger, and fewer, suppliers.
