<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Scimed Life Systems Inc.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Minneapolis</ENAMEX>, said a federal appeals court vacated an earlier summary judgment in its favor.
A lower court in St. Paul had ruled in September 1988 that a heart catheter <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Scimed</ENAMEX> manufactures doesn't infringe on a patent owned by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Advanced Cardiovascular Systems</ENAMEX>, a unit of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Eli Lilly & Co.</ENAMEX>
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Scimed</ENAMEX> said the appeals court remanded the case back to the district court for further proceedings. In national over-the-counter trading Friday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Scimed</ENAMEX> shares tumbled $2.75 to $43.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Scimed</ENAMEX> said it ``remains committed'' both to the ``vigorous defense'' of its position that the catheter doesn't infringe the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lilly</ENAMEX> unit's patent, and to the pursuit of its own counterclaims, which allege <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lilly</ENAMEX> engaged in antitrust violations and other wrongful acts.
