(See: ``Pro-Choice Power: Abortion Issue Erodes Conservative Loyalty to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New Jersey GOP</ENAMEX> -- The Right's Social Agenda Is a Liability as Republican <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lags</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Governer</ENAMEX>'s Race -- Also Unpopular: <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Toxic Waste'' -- WSJ</ENAMEX> Oct. 20, 1989
