<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Daniel J. Terra</ENAMEX>, a director of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Illinois Corp.</ENAMEX>, said that in August he reduced his stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Illinois</ENAMEX> to 26.48% of the common shares outstanding.
In a filing with the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Securities and Exchange Commission</ENAMEX>, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Terra</ENAMEX> said he sold 263,684 <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Illinois</ENAMEX> common shares from Aug. 9 to Aug. 28 for $9.9375 to $10.5625 a share. As a result of the sales he holds 6,727,042 shares.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Terra</ENAMEX> said in the filing that he sold the stock to decrease his position in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Evanston</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ill.</ENAMEX>, banking concern. He may sell more shares in the open market or in private transactions, but wouldn't rule out changing his intentions and buying shares, the filing said.
