<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Johnson & Johnson</ENAMEX> reported a 10% rise in third-quarter net income on a 12% sales increase-results that were driven particularly by new products including pharmaceuticals and the company's professional operations.
In a statement, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ralph S. Larsen</ENAMEX>, chairman and chief executive officer, said the company was pleased with its third-quarter sales performance, ``especially in light of the extremely competitive environment in domestic consumer markets and the negative impact of unfavorable exchange rates this quarter.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">David J. Lothson</ENAMEX>, an industry analyst for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Painewebber Group Inc.</ENAMEX>, said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Johnson & Johnson</ENAMEX>'s results slightly exceeded his expectations for the third quarter.
In <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> composite trading yesterday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Johnson & Johnson</ENAMEX> shares fell 37.5 cents to $54.625.
Despite health-care cost controls and programs to hold down inventory, the professional division, which makes products including sutures and surgical stapling equipment, ``achieved solid growth,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Johnson & Johnson</ENAMEX> said.
But domestic consumer sales slipped 1.2% for the quarter, to $490 million from $496 million. The company cited softness in the retail health and beauty aids category, ``as well as the intense competition in the company's sanitary protection product line.'' Overseas sales were stronger, principally because of a rebound in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Brazil</ENAMEX>, where economic turmoil had hurt year-earlier results, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Johnson & Johnson</ENAMEX> said.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lothson</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Painewebber</ENAMEX> said the company's sales pace has been picking up largely because the effect of unfavorable exchange rates has been easing -- a pattern continuing this quarter. He cautioned, however, that a ``tough tax-rate comparison'' may slow the company's earnings growth for the current quarter. For last year's fourth quarter, the company's tax rate was less than 20%, he said.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Columbia Gas System Inc.</ENAMEX>, shelf offering of up to $200 million of debentures.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Televideo Systems Inc.</ENAMEX>, proposed offering of 1,853,735 common shares, to be sold by holders.
