<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Microsoft</ENAMEX> and other software stocks surged, leading the Nasdaq composite index of over-the-counter stocks to its biggest advance of the year on breathtaking volume.
The Nasdaq composite leaped 7.52 points, or 1.6%, to 470.80. Its largest previous rise this year came Aug. 7, when it gained 4.31.
Of the 4,346 issues that changed hands, 1,435 rose and 629 fell. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jeremiah Mullins</ENAMEX>, head of OTC trading at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dean Witter Reynolds</ENAMEX>, said both institutional and retail investors were buying. But there was a dearth of sellers, traders said, so buyers had to bid prices up to entice them.
``There's no pressure on OTC stocks at this point,'' said Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mullins</ENAMEX>, who said some buyers are beginning to shop among smaller OTC issues.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Microsoft</ENAMEX>'s surge followed a report this week of substantially improved earnings for its first quarter, ended Sept. 30. The stock was trading at 69 just two weeks ago.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rick Sherlund</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Goldman Sachs</ENAMEX> analyst, has raised his earnings estimates for the company twice in the past two weeks, citing improved margins. After the earnings were announced, he raised his fiscal 1990 estimate to between $3.80 and $4 a share. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Microsoft</ENAMEX> earned $3.03 a share in fiscal 1989.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Caere</ENAMEX>, a new software issue, surged from its offering price of 12 to close at 16 1/8. The company also makes optical character recognition equipment. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Caere</ENAMEX> was underwritten by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Alex.</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Brown & Sons.</ENAMEX>
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Valley National</ENAMEX>'s slide of 5 3/4 points to 18 1/2 on 4.2 million shares followed its report late Wednesday of a $72.2 million third-quarter loss. In the 1988 quarter, the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Phoenix</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ariz.</ENAMEX>, commercial banking concern earned $18.7 million.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Valley National</ENAMEX> said its $110 million provision for credit losses and $11 million provision for other real estate owned is related to weakness in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Arizona</ENAMEX> real estate market. Additionally, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Moody's Investors Service</ENAMEX> said it downgraded <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Valley National</ENAMEX>'s senior debt and confirmed the company's commercial paper rating of ``not prime.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dell Computer</ENAMEX> dropped 7/8 to 6. The company said earnings for the year ending Jan. 28, 1990, are expected to be 25 to 35 cents a share, compared with a previous estimate of 50 to 60 cents a share.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">A.P. Green Industries</ENAMEX> advanced 1 5/8 to 36 1/8. East <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rock Partners</ENAMEX>, which has indicated it might make a bid for the company, said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">A.P. Green</ENAMEX>, a refractory products maker, told the partnership it isn't for sale.
