<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mutual</ENAMEX>-fund czar <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John M. Templeton</ENAMEX> has put his money where his moniker is, pouring $1.4 million into one of his own funds, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Templeton Value Fund</ENAMEX>.
Why did he add the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Value Fund</ENAMEX> to the list? Because he's very bullish on the emerging growth stocks that make up the fund's portfolio, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Templeton</ENAMEX> said from his Bahamas hideaway.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Templeton</ENAMEX>'s 147,300-share purchase in the closed-end fund came before the U.S. stock market's plunge last Friday, but still proved slightly profitable.
In addition, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Templeton</ENAMEX> received a dividend of 22 cents a share Oct. 5.
RIVER RUN: A senior vice president and a vice president at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">James River Corp.</ENAMEX> sold the majority of their shares in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Richmond</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Va.</ENAMEX>, paper-products concern in late August and early September, reports filed with the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">SEC</ENAMEX> show.
The executives, who got $30.88 a share for the stock, showed good timing. In <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX> trading yesterday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">James River</ENAMEX> shares closed at $28.375, down 12.5 cents.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">James A. Toney</ENAMEX>, a vice president, sold 1,500 shares Aug. 28. He still has 1,143 shares, according to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">SEC</ENAMEX> files. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Toney</ENAMEX> also declined to comment.
INTEREST-RATE PLAYER: <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cincinnati Gas & Electric Co.</ENAMEX> tops the companies portion of the accompanying Insider Trading table this week. Three of the utility's directors have at least doubled their holdings in the company since July.
The largest purchase was by <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dudley Taft</ENAMEX>, who bought 4,400 shares for $125,075. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Taft</ENAMEX>, who is also president of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Taft Broadcasting Co.</ENAMEX>, said he bought the shares because he keeps a utility account at the brokerage firm of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Salomon Brothers Inc.</ENAMEX>, which had recommended the stock as a good buy. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Salomon Brothers</ENAMEX> confirmed that it has had a buy recommendation on the stock for about two years.
``<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cincinnati Gas & Electric</ENAMEX> is in good shape,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Taft</ENAMEX> said, and utilities are ``a good investment because interest rates are going down.''
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Taft</ENAMEX> paid an average of $28.43 for each share. The stock closed yesterday on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX> at $28.75, down 12.5 cents.
The two other directors bought 1,000 and 1,900 shares, respectively, at prices between $28.15 a share and $28.75 a share, filings with the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">SEC</ENAMEX> show. The two couldn't be reached for comment. A company spokesman said he couldn't explain their sudden bullishness. ``I don't know of any news or anything unusual happening here,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bruce Stoecklin</ENAMEX>, director of media services.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peter Pae</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Pittsburgh</ENAMEX> contributed to this article.
