<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Meson Investment Ltd.</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Vancouver</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">B.C.</ENAMEX>-based investment firm, said it raised its stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Verit Industries</ENAMEX> to 8.9% of the common shares outstanding.
In a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Securities and Exchange Commission</ENAMEX> filing, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Meson</ENAMEX> said it holds 67,400 Verit common shares, including net purchases of 8,100 shares bought from Oct. 10, 1988, to Oct. 11, 1989, for $3.875 to $7 each.
Officials for <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Sun Valley</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Calif.</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Verit</ENAMEX> couldn't be reached for comment.
In composite trading on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Stock Exchange</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Verit</ENAMEX> closed unchanged yesterday at $3.875 a share.
