The bleak automotive results were offset by strong earnings from some non-automotive operations. Still, the combined profit of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chrysler Corp.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">General Motors Corp.</ENAMEX> fell 44% to $1.02 billion from $1.83 billion a year earlier, excluding a one-time gain of $309 million at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chrysler</ENAMEX> from the sale of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mitsubishi Motors Corp.</ENAMEX> stock. The last time all three companies reported North American automotive losses was in the recession year of 1982.
Yesterday's announcements helped spark a midday wave of program selling in the stock market. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX>'s common closed at $44.375 a share, down 50 cents, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> fell 37.5 cents to end at $47.50, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chrysler</ENAMEX> eased 37.5 cents to $22.25, all in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> composite trading.
Nearly all the decline came in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX>'s U.S. automotive operations. The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dearborn</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mich.</ENAMEX>, auto maker ran a loss of $37 million on assembling and marketing cars in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX>, a deterioration of $378 million in that line from the 1988 quarter.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> managed to show a profit for the quarter primarily because of earnings from overseas auto operations and financial services. A year earlier, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> reported record net of $856.3 million, or $1.78 a share, on revenue of $20.38 billion. In the latest nine months, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> earned $3.52 billion, or $7.51 a share, compared with $4.14 billion, or $8.53 a share.
Still, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mccammon</ENAMEX> said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> expects the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> economy to weaken through the end of 1990, causing weaker sales and production. As a result, fourth-quarter profit will come in below 1988 results, although the drop won't be as sharp as the 44% third-quarter decline, he said.
Part of the drop will come from an anticipated charge of as much as $500 million from the proposed sale of its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rouge Steel</ENAMEX> unit. In the 1988 fourth quarter, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> had net of $1.16 billion, or $2.42 a share.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chrysler</ENAMEX>'s operating profit fell to a scant $22 million, or 10 cents a share, its lowest quarterly total in seven years.
Its $309 million, or $1.32 a share, gain from the sale of 75 million <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mitsubishi</ENAMEX> shares made net $331 million, or $1.42 a share. Sales were flat at $7.88 billion. The results include record quarterly earnings of $76 million from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chrysler Financial Corp.</ENAMEX> A year earlier, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chrysler</ENAMEX>'s net was $113 million, or 50 cents a share.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Miller</ENAMEX> said costs of incentives caused a ``moderate'' loss in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Highland Park</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mich.</ENAMEX>, company's North American car and truck business. He said the loss wasn't ``that much different'' from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX>'s $37 million loss on U.S. automotive operations, but he declined to be specific.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Miller</ENAMEX> said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chrysler</ENAMEX> spent an average of $1,000 a vehicle on its incentive programs in the third quarter, compared with about $450 a vehicle a year earlier -- a ``high-water mark'' at the time.
He said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chrysler</ENAMEX> ``is no longer sure'' of its forecast for industry car and truck sales of 14.2 million in the 1990 model year. Consumers, he said, are balking at higher prices on 1990 cars, especially after seeing the incentive-reduced prices on 1989 models.
In the nine months, net was $1.02 billion, or $4.38 a share, including the gain from the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mitsubishi</ENAMEX> stock sale, compared with $617 million, or $2.77 a share, after a charge of $93 million, or 42 cents a share, for plant closings in the 1988 period. Sales rose 8.4% to $27.95 billion from $25.78 billion.
An 8.5% drop in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">North American</ENAMEX> factory sales of cars and trucks cut into revenue, and rebates to dealers and customers more than offset gains from price increases on 1990 model vehicles delivered during the period, a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX> spokesman said.
The diversified operations helped <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX> build its cash reserves, exclusive of its financial subsidiary, to $5.5 billion as of Sept. 30, a 22% increase from a year earlier. This cushion could come in handy if <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX> has to trim fourth-quarter North American production schedules more than the already scheduled 9.5%.
slides represents income before $309 million after-tax gain from sale of
