Doesn't anybody here want to win this mayor's race?
As they stumble and bumble toward election day two weeks from tomorrow, both Democrat <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">David Dinkins</ENAMEX> and Republican <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rudolph Giuliani</ENAMEX> are in trouble.
``I guess we'll reluctantly go ahead and do it, vote for <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dinkins</ENAMEX>,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Richard Wade</ENAMEX>, a politically active professor who supported <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Richard Ravitch</ENAMEX>, an also-ran in the Democratic primary. ``There's nothing on the other side.''
``We're picking up steam,'' insists <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Roger Ailes</ENAMEX>, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Giuliani</ENAMEX>'s media consultant, whose last big campaign helped put <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">George Bush</ENAMEX> in the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">White House</ENAMEX>. He adds: ``It just hasn't gotten down to the engine room yet.'' But the steam may never reach the engine room. For, just as Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Giuliani</ENAMEX> latches on to an issue that has Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dinkins</ENAMEX> reeling, his campaign desperately needs cash to keep Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ailes</ENAMEX>'s commercials on the air beyond Wednesday or Thursday. To help out this week, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">White House</ENAMEX> is dispatching chief of staff <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John Sununu</ENAMEX> and three Cabinet members -- <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">HUD</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jack Kemp</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Transportation</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Samuel Skinner</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Treasury</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Nicholas Brady</ENAMEX>, according to <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peter Powers</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Giuliani</ENAMEX> campaign manager.
The 62-year-old Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dinkins</ENAMEX>, an ex-Marine, has served as the city clerk and as <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Manhattan</ENAMEX> borough president, a job with limited executive responsibilities (``I ``I defy you to come up with one major accomplishment of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">David Dinkins</ENAMEX>,'' says Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Giuliani</ENAMEX>.)
He defeated the contentious Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Koch</ENAMEX> in the Democratic primary partly because he seemed to offer hope he could heal the city's racial and ethnic wounds. His general-election campaign is almost Reagan-like, all muted pictures and comforting words. His theme is unity, decency, humanity, bringing <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> together again.
Both candidates are negotiating about holding debates, but Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dinkins</ENAMEX> is widely seen as the major obstacle for scheduling them.
The 45-year-old Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Giuliani</ENAMEX> has run a negative campaign to pick up votes leaning to Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dinkins</ENAMEX>. ``He's got to get <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dinkins</ENAMEX>'s negatives up,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lee Miringoff</ENAMEX>, director of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Marist College Institute of Public Opinion.</ENAMEX> ``But our polls show voters don't like the attack stuff. Why, even 20% of the Republican vote is going to <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dinkins</ENAMEX>.''
``It's assault-weapons politics,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John Siegal</ENAMEX>, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dinkins</ENAMEX>'s issues director, insisting there is a strong racist undertone to the <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Giuliani</ENAMEX> effort.
For the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Giuliani</ENAMEX> forces, it's a conundrum. On the one hand, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Giuliani</ENAMEX> wants to cut into Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dinkins</ENAMEX>'s credibility. On the other, he seeks to convince voters he's the new Fiorello <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Laguardia</ENAMEX> -- affable, good-natured and ready to lead <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> out of the mess it's in.
It hasn't helped that he's waffled on abortion and gay rights, sought the support of both the Liberal and Conservative parties (he won the Liberal endorsement) and that he turned to comedian <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jackie Mason</ENAMEX> for help with Jewish voters. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mason</ENAMEX> left the campaign after telling reporters Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dinkins</ENAMEX> is ``a fancy'shvartzer' with a moustache.'' <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Shvartzer</ENAMEX> is a derogatory Yiddish word for a black person.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dinkins</ENAMEX> concedes nothing in his ability to stumble and bumble. He can match <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jackie Mason</ENAMEX> with his own <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Robert ``Sonny'' Carson</ENAMEX>, an angry street organizer who was convicted of kidnapping in 1974. The <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dinkins</ENAMEX> campaign paid Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Carson</ENAMEX> close to $10,000 to get out the vote on primary-election day. Paper work on how it was spent is incomplete.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Carson</ENAMEX> has been charged with being anti-Semitic. Asked about that the other day, he replied, ``Anti-Semitic? I'm anti-white.''
More troubling for Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dinkins</ENAMEX> is his record in personal accounting. It began in 1973, when he was being considered for deputy mayor, and a routine check unearthed the extraordinary fact that he hadn't paid his income tax for the previous four years.
``I was always going to do it tomorrow,'' he explained at the time.
``It looks like serious tax evasion,'' says Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ailes</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Giuliani</ENAMEX> media consultant. ``It follows the same pattern as his tax returns. He waits to talk about it until after he gets caught.''
So far though, no one -- not even former <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> attorney <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Giuliani</ENAMEX> -- has been able to pinpoint just what law Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dinkins</ENAMEX> has broken or just what tax he has evaded.
``The crime goes to character,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ron Maiorana</ENAMEX>, a consultant to the <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Giuliani</ENAMEX> campaign. ``It's serious stuff. He evades and ducks. He's had a history of deception and this is the latest chapter.''
``It makes people think, maybe this guy isn't so squeaky clean after all,'' says Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Garth</ENAMEX>, Mayor <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Koch</ENAMEX>'s media consultant. ``The result may turn out to be a lot closer than people think.
