<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Consumers Power Co.</ENAMEX>, now the main unit of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CMS Energy</ENAMEX>, ran into financial problems over its $4.2 billion <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Midland</ENAMEX> nuclear plant, which was abandoned as a nuclear facility in 1984 because of construction delays and high costs. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CMS</ENAMEX> is nearly done converting the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Midland</ENAMEX> plant to a gas-fired cogeneration facility at a cost of $600 million.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CMS</ENAMEX> management said Thursday that they planned to recommend paying a modest dividend when the board of directors met Friday. The dividend will be paid Nov. 22 to shares of record Nov. 7.
The company suffered a loss of $270 million in 1985, but its financial situation has been improving since then. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CMS</ENAMEX> said it earned $237.8 million in the first nine months
