For a company that sells billions of dollars in military hardware each year, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Northrop Corp.</ENAMEX> is pressing awfully hard to get back a mere $6,250,000.
The missing funds -- and the way they've been accounted for -- are at the center of a long-running dispute between the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Los Angeles</ENAMEX> aerospace company and a well-connected Korean enterprise called <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Asia Culture Travel Development Co.</ENAMEX>
Since news of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Northrop</ENAMEX>'s Korean dealings became public last year, the company has insisted that it sunk the money into a proposed hotel venture in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Seoul</ENAMEX>, losing everything when it was bamboozled by Korean con men. The Koreans say that the hotel was a ruse from the beginning, and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Northrop</ENAMEX> really intended to bribe government officials to buy its ill-fated F-20 Tigershark jet fighter.
Now, a document released by the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">House Energy and Commerce</ENAMEX> subcommittee alleges that <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Northrop</ENAMEX> tried to cover up those purportedly illicit payments by forging signatures, shuffling millions of dollars in and out of banks and even paying hush money to middlemen who threatened to disclose the scam to the authorities.
Some of the allegations were given to the subcommittee during testimony in August 1988. But the document -- featuring a passel of new details -- is sure to revive interest in the matter on <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Capitol Hill</ENAMEX>, where lawmakers this week are deciding on appropriations for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Northrop</ENAMEX>'s most important <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pentagon</ENAMEX> program, the B-2 Stealth bomber. <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Asia</ENAMEX> Culture Travel submitted the document as part of its legal defense to the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">International Chamber of Commerce</ENAMEX>, which is arbitrating the case between <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Asia</ENAMEX> Culture <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Travel</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Northrop</ENAMEX>.
One subcommittee investigator, who works for Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John Dingell</ENAMEX> (D., <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mich.</ENAMEX>), called the information ``a major step forward'' in its own inquiry. A federal grand jury also is actively trying to determine whether <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Northrop</ENAMEX> violated the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Foreign Corrupt</ENAMEX> Practices Act.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Northrop</ENAMEX> has strongly denied any illegalities. It said that in August it made an extensive filing to the chamber that rebuts, point by point, the allegations by <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Asia</ENAMEX> Culture Travel. A copy wasn't immediately available.
In a May 8 filing to the chamber, though, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Northrop</ENAMEX> stressed its view that ``this is not a complex case... but is instead a straightforward breach-of-contract dispute.'' The company added that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Asia Culture Travel</ENAMEX>'s ``allegations are so contradictory and inconsistent that they provide powerful evidence'' that the Koreans ``deceived <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Northrop</ENAMEX>'' by pitching the hotel project.
But <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Asia</ENAMEX> Culture Travel lays out a much different  story in its 52-page brief. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Northrop</ENAMEX>'s first contact with the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Koreans</ENAMEX>, this version of the tangled events goes, occurred in the summer of 1983 when <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Northrop</ENAMEX> approached <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dong Yang Express Co.</ENAMEX>, a bus company that was run by <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lee Minha</ENAMEX>. His brother-in-law was the late <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Park Chong Kyu</ENAMEX>, a powerful businessman.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Park</ENAMEX>, the pistol-packing owner of a notorious <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Seoul</ENAMEX> night spot called the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Safari Club</ENAMEX>, was a member of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Seoul Olympic Organizing Committee</ENAMEX> with easy access to the highest echelons of the Korean government.
The brief alleges that <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Northrop</ENAMEX>, by way of a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Honolulu</ENAMEX>-based consultant named <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">James Shin</ENAMEX>, proposed the idea of selling to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Korea</ENAMEX> as many as 200 F-20s through <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dong Yang Express</ENAMEX>, which was to receive a 2% commission with a $55 million cap. As part of the arrangement, the document contends, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Northrop</ENAMEX> was asked to invest in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Sofitel Seoul</ENAMEX>, ``a high-class hotel'' that was to be built on the site of a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dong Yang Express</ENAMEX> garage.
Though it is typical for American companies to invest in foreign countries in which they want to trade arms, thereby offsetting the cost of currency conversion on its contracts to the overseas government, it was still initially puzzling why <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Northrop</ENAMEX> approached a bus company to do it.
``I first thought it made no sense to offer to an express bus company the distribution of up-to-date fighters,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lee</ENAMEX> told public prosecutors in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Seoul</ENAMEX> who have also investigated the situation, according to the document. ``But later I learned that it was not Dong <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Yang Express</ENAMEX> but Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Park Chong Kyu</ENAMEX> that <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Northrop</ENAMEX> aimed to contact.''
In May 1984, the document asserts, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Northrop</ENAMEX> officials met with Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Park</ENAMEX> -- known best to Americans as <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">C.K. Park</ENAMEX> -- and allegedly asked him to ``perform promotional activities'' for the F-20. The brief says Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Park</ENAMEX> then asked for $5 million up front, adding that ``he could procure such expenses from the budget for the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sofitel Hotel</ENAMEX> project if approved by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Northrop.</ENAMEX>''
But <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Northrop</ENAMEX> declined, the brief says, when its representatives pointed out that a payoff would be illegal and ``such a payment, if done, would constitute a scandal.'' Yet the document alleges that it didn't take long before <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Northrop</ENAMEX> and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Park</ENAMEX> devised a new scheme to funnel the money. The conduit, the filing insists, was to be another hotel project -- this time a joint venture with <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Asia</ENAMEX> Culture Travel, another Park-affiliated concern.
Promotional materials touting <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Asia</ENAMEX> Culture Travel were delivered to <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Northrop</ENAMEX> and appear to have been signed by <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kang Oh-Hyun</ENAMEX>, an official of the firm; in fact, the filing alleges, they were forged by Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Shin</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Northrop</ENAMEX> consultant. The brief says other procedural forms relating to the joint venture appear to have been signed by four <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Asia</ENAMEX> Culture Travel shareholders when Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Park</ENAMEX> came to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Los Angeles</ENAMEX> in the summer of 1984 for the Olympic Games. But three of the holders, the filing says, weren't in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">California</ENAMEX> at the time.
On Aug. 9, 1984, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Northrop</ENAMEX> told Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Park</ENAMEX> that $6,250,000 had been deposited to an account in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hong Kong</ENAMEX> that he controlled. Everything, the arbitration filing suggests, seemed set.
That is, at least until October when, during a test flight, an F-20 crashed. The pilot was killed and the aircraft destroyed. Shortly thereafter another F-20 crashed in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Canada</ENAMEX> during a demonstration, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Northrop</ENAMEX> eventually gave up on the F-20 program after out-of-pocket expenditures of more than $1 billion. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Park</ENAMEX> died of cancer in 1985.
Meanwhile, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Northrop</ENAMEX>'s own board began inquiring about what happened to the hotel -- the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Seoul</ENAMEX> Palace, it was to be called -- and the $6,250,000. It was at that point, the filing alleges, that a cover-up began.
First, the brief says, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Northrop</ENAMEX> wanted to formally cancel with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dong Yang Express</ENAMEX> the earlier <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sofitel Hotel</ENAMEX> transaction that had been proposed. The idea, the filing alleges, was to be able to transfer to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dong Yang Express</ENAMEX> $3.5 million in termination fees. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Donald Foulds</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Northrop</ENAMEX> executive, even allegedly drafted the settlement claim for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dong Yang Express</ENAMEX>.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Foulds</ENAMEX>'s attorney, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jan Handzlik</ENAMEX>, said his client ``denies that he engaged in any improper activity in respect to the Korean hotel project, including any cover-up activities.''
That money, investigators for the House subcommittee said, was in turn designed to be handed back to Northrop to help it account for more than half of the missing $6,250,000. Of the remainder, the filing maintains, $1,750,000 could be chalked up to expenses and $1 million was available through a Park bank account.
But, the filing says, that plan had to be killed when ``the blackmailers appear.'' The first allegedly was a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dong Yang Express</ENAMEX> middleman, who told <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">James Dorsey</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Honolulu</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Northrop</ENAMEX> marketing executive, that he would ``publish all the facts concerning <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Northrop</ENAMEX>'s efforts to sell the F-20 to the Korean government,'' the document says. Both Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dorsey</ENAMEX> and his lawyer, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Daniel Bookin</ENAMEX>, declined to comment.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Welko Gasich</ENAMEX>, then a top <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Northrop</ENAMEX> executive, allegedly handed over $1.5 million to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dong Yang Express</ENAMEX>, which passed on $500,000 to silence the middleman, the document claims. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gasich</ENAMEX> declined to comment; the middleman couldn't be located.
In early 1987, the arbitration filing asserts, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Shin</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Northrop</ENAMEX> consultant, demanded $2 million to remain silent. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Shin</ENAMEX>, who is being sued by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Northrop</ENAMEX> in federal court in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Honolulu</ENAMEX>, couldn't be reached.
It was then that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Northrop</ENAMEX> filed suit against the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Koreans</ENAMEX> -- in what the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">House</ENAMEX> investigators claim was an attempt to make it look as if <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Northrop</ENAMEX> had been swindled.
The company is asking the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">International Chamber of Commerce</ENAMEX> to order <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Asia</ENAMEX> Culture Travel and its associates to return the $6,250,000, plus interest ``at the highest lawful rate.
