<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bank Building & Equipment Corp.</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">America</ENAMEX>, which previously said accounting discrepancies its auditors uncovered would hurt earnings and require restatement of earlier results, increased its projections of the negative fiscal impact, and said it was exploring the company's sale.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bank Building</ENAMEX>, which builds and equips banks, had announced it would restate the first-three  quarters of this fiscal year, which ends Oct. 31.
On Oct. 5, the company estimated after-tax effects on the year's earnings would be ``at least'' $1.3 million. Yesterday, the company said the negative after-tax effect on earnings for the year will be about $3.3 million. For the nine months ended July 31, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bank Building</ENAMEX> had a net loss of $1 million, on revenue of $66.5 million.
Company auditors are continuing their review, and final restated figures aren't yet available. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bank</ENAMEX> Building earlier said the restatement is necessitated by ``certain errors in recording receivables and payables'' at its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Loughman Cabinet</ENAMEX> division. That division's manager has been fired.
