Investors ran away from the stock market yesterday, dumping many recently favored stocks as they fled.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones Industrial Average</ENAMEX> fell 39.55 to 2613.73. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> volume rose to 175,240,000 shares from 155.6 million Wednesday.
Badly shaken by recent big swings in stock prices and the cloudy outlook for the economy, investors sold many of the consumer-oriented blue chips that were the market's star performers only a week ago. Many of those issues-such as <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Philip Morris</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Procter & Gamble</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merck</ENAMEX> -- are in the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones Industrial Average</ENAMEX>.
Traders said investors were either raising cash or buying very selectively. In a sign of just how nervous investors are, precious-metals stocks were among the best performers yesterday.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Compaq Computer</ENAMEX>'s disappointing earnings report after the market closed Wednesday set the pace for the sell-off yesterday. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Compaq</ENAMEX> closed down 8 5/8 to 100 on 2.6 million shares. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Compaq</ENAMEX>, a highly sought stock only a few days ago, hit a record high of 112 1/2 on Oct. 19.
Third-quarter earnings were on the low end of analysts' forecasts,  and the company disclosed that it had uncovered two technical flaws in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Intel</ENAMEX>'s new microprocessor, which could cause delays in shipments of some new <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Compaq</ENAMEX> products. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Intel</ENAMEX> dropped 7/8 to 32 in over-the-counter trading.
``When you see what happened to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Compaq</ENAMEX>, it is completely (numbing) for the mentality of the market,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jack Solomon</ENAMEX>, technical analyst for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bear Stearns</ENAMEX>. ``It is hard for the mind to digest that what was the leading stock is now the one leading you down the tubes.''
Investors took little comfort in yesterday's report that third-quarter gross national product grew at a 2.5% annual rate. Though that growth was in line with expectations, investors focused on signs of a slowdown: a buildup in inventories and dubious strength in consumer spending.
Futures-related selling pushed the industrial average about 45 points lower in the morning as rumors about <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">RJR Nabisco</ENAMEX>'s pending sale of its <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Del Monte</ENAMEX> foods unit spread through the trading pits in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chicago</ENAMEX>. The purchase of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Del Monte</ENAMEX> is likely to be financed with junk bonds or a bridge loan. The stock market has had a heightened concern about turmoil with high-risk financing ever since <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Campeau Corp.</ENAMEX> nearly missed an interest payment on its junk bonds in September.
While futures-related sell programs depressed prices at first, buy programs pared the industrial average's losses later in the session. However, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Donald Selkin</ENAMEX>, head of futures research at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Prudential-Bache Securities</ENAMEX>, said that the stock market appears to be poised for a round of futures-related selling this morning, given the discrepancies between futures and stocks at the close.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> started trading its new ``basket'' product yesterday, with which institutions can buy and sell all the stocks in the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Standard & Poor</ENAMEX>'s 500-stock index in one trade. About $45 million of stock traded through the basket.
In a sign of the credit needs among market makers during the 190-point plunge on Oct. 13, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal Reserve Bank of New York</ENAMEX> said yesterday that loans by <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>'s nine largest banks for the financing of securities positions rose $786 million, to $6.6 billion during the week ending Oct. 18.
Among other computer stocks, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">International Business Machines</ENAMEX> fell 1 1/8 to 100 3/4 on 1.7 million shares, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Digital Equipment</ENAMEX> droped 2 1/4 to 88 and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Unisys</ENAMEX> lost 1/2 to 17. Also, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tandem Computers</ENAMEX> lost 1 to 24 7/8 even though earnings for the September quarter were in line with expectations.
Semiconductor issues slumped as well; <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Texas Instruments</ENAMEX> dropped 1 to 31 1/2, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Motorola</ENAMEX> fell 5/8 to 55 1/4 and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cypress Semiconductor</ENAMEX> lost 1/2 to 12 1/4.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Anheuser-Busch</ENAMEX> slid 1/2 to 38 and led the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX>'s list of most active issues as 4.3 million shares were traded. The stock had plunged 4 3/8 Wednesday on the news of third-quarter earnings weakness and its discounting strategy, which it expects to affect results through the end of 1990.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Philip Morris</ENAMEX> fell 1 7/8 to 41 5/8 on 3.7 million shares, reflecting the possibility that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Anheuser-Busch</ENAMEX>'s decision could have a negative impact on results at its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Miller Brewing</ENAMEX> unit.
Other consumer stocks coming under selling pressure included <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Procter & Gamble</ENAMEX>, which went down 3 1/4 to 126 3/4; <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coca-Cola Co.</ENAMEX>, down 1 3/8 to 71 1/8, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mcdonald</ENAMEX>'s, down 1/4 to 31 1/4; <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pepsico</ENAMEX>, off 1 to 60 3/8, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merck</ENAMEX>, down 1 1/2 to 76 3/4.
Auto stocks slumped as each of the nation's Big Three auto makers reported that third-quarter operating profits were down from 1988. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford Motor</ENAMEX>, which also said it expects results for the fourth quarter to be soft because of a slowdown in auto sales, dropped 3/8 to 47 1/2. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">General Motors</ENAMEX> lost 1/2 to 44 3/8 and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chrysler</ENAMEX> slid 3/8 to 22 1/4.
Oil field-services issues were especially weak. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Shearson Lehman Hutton</ENAMEX> cut short-term investment ratings on <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Schlumberger</ENAMEX>, which went down 2 1/4 to 41 1/8; <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Halliburton</ENAMEX>, down 1 1/8 to 35 1/8; <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dresser Industries</ENAMEX>, off 1 to 37 3/4, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Baker Hughes</ENAMEX>, down 3/4 to 21. Precious-metals stocks, widely viewed as a safe investment haven in periods of uncertainty, posted solid gains. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Newmont Gold</ENAMEX> climbed 2 1/2 to 39, Battle Mountain Gold rose 1 to 16, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hecla Mining</ENAMEX> went up 5/8 to 13 3/8, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Homestake Mining</ENAMEX> added 5/8 to 15 3/4 and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ASA Ltd.</ENAMEX> rose 2 to 46.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tandy</ENAMEX> fell 5/8 to 43 3/8 on 1.8 million shares, including a 1.5 million-share block that the company repurchased as part of an ongoing buy-back program. The block equaled 1.7% of its shares outstanding.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nipsco Industries</ENAMEX>, the owner of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Northern Indiana</ENAMEX> Public Service, rose 1/2 to 17 7/8. Its board authorized the repurchase of an additional 3.5 million common shares, or about 5% of its shares outstanding, under an ongoing buy-back program.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">N.V. Philips</ENAMEX>, whose third-quarter net profit was up 41% from a year earlier, added 1/2 to 22 1/4. Also, the company said it would file for an initial offering of a 20% stake in its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Polygram</ENAMEX> unit, as expected.
Imperial <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chemical Industries</ENAMEX> plunged 6 1/4 to 69 7/8. The company's third-quarter pretax profit was 12% lower than the year-ago level and fell short of its expectations.
Quantum <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chemical</ENAMEX>, which reported a loss for the third quarter, dropped 1 1/2 to 33 1/4. The company also suspended payment of cash dividends on its common stock until at least next April; it plans to pay stock dividends instead.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX>, which said it is holding talks with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> about the latter's $18-a-share takeover offer, advanced 7/8 to 20 1/2. Earlier this month, a special committee of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX>'s board rejected the bid as inadequate.
La <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jolla Bancorp</ENAMEX> climbed 3 to 13. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Security Pacific</ENAMEX> signed a letter of intent to acquire the company in a stock swap valued at $15 a share.
