<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lawrence Insurance Group Inc.</ENAMEX> said it acquired <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Republic Reinsurance Co.</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Houston</ENAMEX> property and casualty reinsurance company, from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Savings Association</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Texas</ENAMEX> for $28 million.
By acquiring the shares, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lawrence Group</ENAMEX> increased its stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lawrence Insurance</ENAMEX> to 93.2% from 91.2%. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lawrence Insurance</ENAMEX> underwrites mostly primary insurance, a company spokesman said. A reinsurance company effectively insures insurance companies that wish to spread the risk of a particular policy.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lawrence Group</ENAMEX> also owns <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lawrence Agency Corp.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Schenectady</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.Y.</ENAMEX>, an insurance agency and brokerage.
