<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Affiliated Bankshares of Colorado Inc.</ENAMEX> said it agreed to sell its 10% interest in Rocky Mountain <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bankcard Systems</ENAMEX> for $18.5 million to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Colorado National Bank</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Denver</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Central Bank</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Denver</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Colorado National</ENAMEX> is a unit of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Colorado National Bankshares Inc.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Central</ENAMEX> is a unit of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Bank System</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Minneapolis</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Affiliated</ENAMEX> said it expects to record a pretax gain of about $18.5 million from the sale of the credit-card business, which should more than offset any reduction in the carrying value of real estate and real-estate loans on its books.
