<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paramount Pictures Corp.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>, named <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Arthur Cohen</ENAMEX>, executive vice president of advertising at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Revlon Inc.</ENAMEX>, as the new president of marketing for its motion picture group.
Movie studios rarely turn outside the industry for marketing executives. A few years ago, for example, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coca-Cola Co.</ENAMEX>, which owns 49% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Columbia Pictures Entertainment Inc.</ENAMEX>, sent one of its soft drink marketing executives, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peter Sealey</ENAMEX>, to run marketing at the studio. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Sealey</ENAMEX> didn't stay long, however, leaving after a series of management changes. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Columbia</ENAMEX> is in the process of being acquired by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony Corp.</ENAMEX>
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Cohen</ENAMEX> fills a post vacated earlier this year by <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Sidney Ganis</ENAMEX> when Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ganis</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paramount</ENAMEX>'s head of distribution, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Barry London</ENAMEX>, were named co-presidents of the motion picture group. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paramount Pictures</ENAMEX> is a unit of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paramount Communications Inc.</ENAMEX>
Prior to joining <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Revlon</ENAMEX> in 1986, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Cohen</ENAMEX> held a number of marketing and advertising posts. From 1982 to 1985, he was president of the ill-fated <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tele1st</ENAMEX> venture of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ABC Video Enterprises</ENAMEX> unit of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Capital Cities/ABC Inc.</ENAMEX> Tele1st attempted to sell movies via a service that enabled subscribers with videocassette recorders to tape movies delivered on a special scrambled channel overnight.
