The bolstered cellular agreement between <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bellsouth Corp.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">LIN Broadcasting Corp.</ENAMEX> carries heightened risks and could fail to fend off <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mccaw Cellular Communications Inc.</ENAMEX>, the rival suitor for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">LIN</ENAMEX>.
Moreover, the amended pact shows how <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mccaw</ENAMEX>'s persistence has pushed <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">LIN</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bellsouth</ENAMEX> into a corner, forcing huge debt on the proposed new company. The debt, estimated at $4.7 billion, could mortgage the cellular company's future earning power in order to placate some <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">LIN</ENAMEX> holders in the short term.
The plan still calls for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">LIN</ENAMEX> to combine its cellular telephone properties with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bellsouth</ENAMEX>'s and to spin off its broadcasting operations. But under new terms of the agreement, announced Friday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">LIN</ENAMEX> holders would receive a special cash dividend of $42 a share, representing a payout of about $2.23 billion, shortly before the proposed merger. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">LIN</ENAMEX> said it expects to borrow the money to pay the dividend, but commitments from banks still haven't been obtained. Under previous terms, holders would have received a dividend of only $20 a share.
In addition, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">LIN</ENAMEX> would exercise its right to buy out for $1.9 billion the 55% equity interest of its partner, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Metromedia Co.</ENAMEX>, in a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> cellular franchise. That money also would have to be borrowed. In effect, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mccaw</ENAMEX> has forced <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">LIN</ENAMEX>'s hand by bidding $1.9 billion for the stake earlier this month.
``We're taking on more debt than we would have liked to,'' acknowledged <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Michael Plouf</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">LIN</ENAMEX>'s vice president and treasurer. Although he expressed confidence that the proposed new company's cash flow would be sufficient to cover interest payments on the debt, he estimated that the company wouldn't be profitable until 1994 or later.
Analyst estimate the value of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bellsouth</ENAMEX> proposal at about $115 to $125 a share. They value <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mccaw</ENAMEX>'s bid at $112 to $118 a share. The previous <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bellsouth</ENAMEX> pact was valued at about $98 to $110 a share.
``We're very pleased with the new deal. We didn't expect <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bellsouth</ENAMEX> to be so responsive,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Frederick A. Moran</ENAMEX>, president of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Moran Asset Management Inc.</ENAMEX>, which holds 500,000 LIN shares. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bellsouth</ENAMEX>'s ``back-end protection was flawed previously. We think this is a superior deal to <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mccaw</ENAMEX>'s. We're surprised. We didn't think a sleeping {Bell} mentality would be willing to take on dilution.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bellsouth</ENAMEX>'s revised proposal surprised many industry analysts, especially because of the company's willingness to accept some dilution of future earnings. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">William O. Mccoy</ENAMEX>, president of the company's <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bellsouth Enterprises Inc.</ENAMEX> unit, said the revised agreement with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">LIN</ENAMEX> would dilute <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bellsouth</ENAMEX> earnings by about 9% in both 1990 and 1991 and by significantly less thereafter. Indeed, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bellsouth</ENAMEX>'s cellular operations were among the first in the country to become profitable.
For 1988, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bellsouth</ENAMEX> earned $1.7 billion, or $3.51 a share, on revenue of $13.6 billion. Analysts were predicting 1990 Bellsouth earnings in the range of $3.90 a share, or $1.9 billion, but now those estimates are being scaled back.
In national over-the-counter trading, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">LIN</ENAMEX> shares soared $4.625 to closed at $112.625, while <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mccaw</ENAMEX> fell $2.50 a share to $37.75.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Leon</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bear Stearns</ENAMEX> speculated that <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mccaw</ENAMEX>, in an attempt to buy time, might consider filing an antitrust suit against <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bellsouth</ENAMEX> with the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Justice Department</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> District Judge <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Harold Greene</ENAMEX>, who oversees enforcement of the consent decree that broke up the Bell system in 1984.
Indeed, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mccaw</ENAMEX> seemed to hint at that option in a brief statement. Urging LIN directors to conduct ``a fair auction on a level playing field,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mccaw</ENAMEX> asked how well the public interest would be served ``with the Bell operating companies controlling over 94% of all cellular {potential customers} in the nation's top 10 markets.
