I don't want to feel guilty representing my constituents. And if I think that some people {on <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">HUD</ENAMEX> Secretary <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jack Kemp</ENAMEX>'s} staff are off base in terms in which they're evaluating certain things affecting my hometown, I have to tell you something -- I'm not going to take it. I think that I'm elected to represent the people that sent me here. And one of our charges is to be an ombudsman for our area. And if we're not ombudsman for our area, we ought to be thrown out of office. On the other hand, if we're asking for something unreasonable or unethical and so on, then that's a whole different story. But if I feel that there are situations where I'm trying to get housing for our area -- whatever it happens to be -- and I have to feel that I can't even ask a question, I've got to tell you, I think that's outrageous..
