A decline in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Allied-Signal Inc.</ENAMEX>'s automotive business contributed to flat sales and only slightly higher earnings in the third quarter.
For the nine months, the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Morris Township</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.J.</ENAMEX>-based company, with businesses in aerospace, automotive products and engineered materials, earned $413 million, or $2.77 cents a share, up 15% from $359 million, or $2.40 a share. Sales eased 0.2% to $8.88 billion from $8.90 billion.
Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Edward L. Hennessy Jr.</ENAMEX> said that a drop in sales of auto and truck parts contributed to lower earnings in the automotive unit. He also cited unfavorable foreign-exchange rates and a lower tax rate. Earnings for the group declined to $11 million from $33 million last year.
Earnings at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Allied-Signal</ENAMEX>'s aerospace business rose to $55 million from $41 million a year ago, primarily on higher sales and profit in its engines and auxiliary power units.
In <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> composite trading yesterday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Allied-Signal</ENAMEX> shares closed at $35.125, off 87.5 cents.
