<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">H&R Block</ENAMEX> is one of the great success stories of U.S. business. Oddly enough, this presents a problem for the stock.
Some money managers are disenchanted with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">H&R Block</ENAMEX> because they suspect the company's glory days are past, or at least passing. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Block</ENAMEX>'s tax-preparation business is mature, they say, and some of its diversifications are facing tough competition.
But the tax-preparation business simply has no more room to grow, says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mark Cremonie</ENAMEX>, director of research for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Capital Supervisors Inc.</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chicago</ENAMEX> firm that manages $6.5 billion. ``You go to any medium-sized town in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> and you're going to see <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">H&R</ENAMEX> Block tax services.''
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Cremonie</ENAMEX>'s firm once held about 4.8% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">H&R Block</ENAMEX>. That was before the 1986 tax ``reform'' made taxes more complex than ever. ``One thing you can bet on,'' he says, ``is that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Congress</ENAMEX> will do stupid things with the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tax Code.</ENAMEX>'' But <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Capital Supervisors</ENAMEX> sold the last of its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">H&R Block</ENAMEX> holdings earlier this year. ``They're thrashing around for diversification,'' he says. ``I think a lot of their businesses are just so-so.''
Last week the stock hit an all-time high of 37 1/4 before getting roughed up in the Friday-the-13th minicrash. It closed yesterday at 34 3/4.
To be sure, the stock still has a lot of fans. ``If you invested $10,000 in the initial public offering in 1962, it would be worth well over $5 million today,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Fredric E. Russell</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tulsa</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Okla.</ENAMEX>, money manager. ``I don't know what the risk is {of holding the stock}. Taxes are not going out of business.''
Many of his peers feel the same way. The number of big institutions that own <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">H&R Block</ENAMEX> shares is 207 and growing, according to a midyear tally by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CDA Investment Technologies</ENAMEX>. Brokerage houses are sweet on <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">H&R Block</ENAMEX>, too. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Zacks Investment Research</ENAMEX> counts five brokerage houses that consider the stock a buy, and four that call it a hold. None dare say to sell it.
But some money managers are doing just that. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Eugene Sit</ENAMEX>, president of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sit Investment Associates</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Minneapolis</ENAMEX>, says, ``When we bought it, we thought the growth rate was going to accelerate'' because of computerized tax filing and instant refunds (the customer gets a refund immediately but pays extra to the tax preparer, which waits for Uncle <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Sam</ENAMEX>'s check).
But neither of those developments did much to juice up growth, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Sit</ENAMEX> says. He figures Block earnings are now growing at about a 10% annual rate (down from about 14% the past five years) and will grow at an 8%-10% rate in the future.
Two other money managers, in explaining why they have sold large amounts of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">H&R Block</ENAMEX> stock this year, spoke on the condition they not be named.
``There's no more growth in the tax business {except} for increasing prices,'' the money manager added. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Compuserve</ENAMEX> subsidiary (which provides information to home-computer users) is ``where the growth is,'' he said, but its format is ``still too complicated.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Compuserve</ENAMEX> provides about 20% of both sales and earnings. The tax business still provides about 70% of earnings, on about 50% of sales. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Personnel Pool</ENAMEX> (temporary workers, mostly in the health-care area) chips in close to 25% of sales but only about 9% of earnings.
The shortage of nurses is crimping profit at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Personnel Pool</ENAMEX>, said the second money manager. He concedes <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">H&R Block</ENAMEX> is ``well-entrenched'' and ``a great company,'' but says ``it doesn't grow fast enough for us. We're looking for something that grows faster and sells at a comparable {price-earnings} multiple.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Thomas M. Bloch</ENAMEX>, president and chief operating officer, says ``I would disagree'' that the tax business is mature. For example, he says, the company is planning to go nationwide with a new service, tested in parts of the country, aimed at taxpayers who want refunds in a hurry.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bloch</ENAMEX> concedes that a recent diversification attempt fell through. ``We're still interested {in diversifying},'' he says, ``but we'd rather be prudent than make a mistake.'' He also says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Compuserve</ENAMEX>'s earnings continue to grow ``20% to 30% a year'' in spite of tough competition from giants like <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sears</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IBM</ENAMEX>. And he says Block's other businesses are growing, although less consistently.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">H&R Block</ENAMEX>
(<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NYSE</ENAMEX>; Symbol:<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">HRB</ENAMEX>)
Business: Tax Preparation
Year ended April 30, 1989:
Revenue: $899.6 million
Net loss: $100.2 million; $1.90 a share
First quarter, July 31, 1989:
Per-share earnings: Loss of 8 cents vs. loss of 9 cents
145,954 shares
Common shares outstanding: 52.6
