<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dayton Hudson Corp.</ENAMEX> said it accepted for purchase seven million common shares at $62.875 each, under the terms of a Dutch auction self-tender offer. The offer expired at 12:01 a.m. yesterday.
In a Dutch auction, the buyer sets a price range and holders give a price in that range at which they're willing to sell their shares. The buyer then picks a price and buys shares at that price from holders who offered to sell at that price or lower. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dayton Hudson</ENAMEX>'s repurchase offer, representing about 9% of its common shares outstanding, had established a range of between $60 and $65 for the buy-back.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dayton Hudson</ENAMEX> said it accepted all odd-lot shares tendered at or below the final $62.875 price; the preliminary proration factor for other shares tendered at or below the final price is 98%.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Minneapolis</ENAMEX>-based retailer said it expects to pay for the seven million shares next Thursday. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tendered</ENAMEX> shares not purchased will be returned to holders.
In <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> composite trading, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dayton</ENAMEX> rose $1 to $61.125.
