At 13,000 feet, the engines restarted. But knowing that mechanics would probably ground him for repairs, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Brown</ENAMEX> skipped his stop in nearby <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chicago</ENAMEX> and set course to get his load -- a few hundred parcels -- to the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Memphis</ENAMEX> package-sorting  hub on time. Had he been a little less gung-ho, ``I'd have gotten the thing on the ground and headed for the nearest bar,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Brown</ENAMEX> says.
That may soon change. This month, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal</ENAMEX>'s 2,048 pilots, including some 961 acquired along with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tiger International Inc.</ENAMEX> in February, will decide whether to elect the powerful <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Air Line Pilots Association</ENAMEX> as their bargaining agent. The election, which would bring the first major union to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> operations, has pitted new hires against devoted veterans such as Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Brown</ENAMEX>. It has also rattled <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal</ENAMEX>'s strongly anti-union management, which is already contending with melding far-flung operations and with falling profits.
``A union, sooner or later, has to have an adversary, and it has to have a victory,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Frederick W. Smith</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal's</ENAMEX> chairman and chief executive, says with disdain. ``In our formula, we don't have any losers except the competition.''
What managers really fear is that the pro-union movement could spread beyond the pilots. Under federal transportation law, a government mediator is attempting to reconcile the melding of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tiger</ENAMEX>'s job classifications into <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal's</ENAMEX>. Depending on the outcome, the merged company may face union elections this fall among airplane mechanics, ramp workers, stock clerks and flight dispatchers. These groups constitute up to 10% of its work force.
``Unions would have a profound effect on the whole culture of the company,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bernard La Londe</ENAMEX>, a professor at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ohio State University</ENAMEX> at <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Columbus</ENAMEX> and a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal</ENAMEX> consultant.
That culture, carefully crafted by Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Smith</ENAMEX>, leaves little, if any, room for unions. Since founding the company, the charismatic <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Vietnam</ENAMEX> vet, who is still only 46 years old, has fostered an ethos of combat. Flights are ``missions.'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Smith</ENAMEX>'s managers have, at times, been called ``Ho <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Chi Minh</ENAMEX>'s Guerrillas.'' The Bravo Zulu award, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> accolade for a ``job well done,'' is bestowed on <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal</ENAMEX>'s workers who surpass the call of duty. Competitors are known as the ``enemy.''
To reinforce employees' dedication, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Smith</ENAMEX> pays well. He also lets workers vent steam through an elaborate grievance procedure and, as a perk, fly free in empty cockpit seats. He gives pep talks in periodic ``family briefings'' beamed internationally on ``<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">FXTV</ENAMEX>,'' the company's own television network.
And, with many of his 70,000 workers, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Smith</ENAMEX>'s damn-the-torpedoes attitude has caught on. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">James Cleveland</ENAMEX>, a courier who earned a Bravo Zulu for figuring out how to get a major customer's 1,100-parcel-a-week load to its doorstep by 8 a.m., considers himself far more than a courier. ``We don't just hand the customer the package. That's just the beginning,'' he says. ``In essence, we run the show.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">David Sanders</ENAMEX>, a longtime pilot, bristles at the mere suggestion that a union might tamper with his flight schedule. ``This is <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">America</ENAMEX>,'' he says. ``Nobody has the right to tell me how much I can work.''
The operational freedom has also given Federal a leg up on archrival <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Parcel Service Inc.</ENAMEX>, the nation's largest employer of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Brotherhood of Teamsters</ENAMEX> members. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UPS</ENAMEX> won't discuss its labor practices, but, according to Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Cleveland</ENAMEX>, a former <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UPS</ENAMEX> employee, and others, union work rules prohibit UPS drivers from doing more than carrying packages between customers and their vans. Because UPS drivers aren't permitted to load their own vehicles at the depot, say these couriers, packages often get buried in the load and are delivered late.
Labor problems are the last thing Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Smith</ENAMEX> needs right now. Although the Tiger acquisition has brought Federal a long way toward becoming the global player it wants to be, it also has brought problems. It more than doubled <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal</ENAMEX>'s long-term debt to $1.9 billion, thrust the company into unknown territory -- heavy cargo -- and suddenly expanded its landing rights to 21 countries from four.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal's</ENAMEX> stock price, however, has held up well, driven in part by the general run-up of airline stocks, analysts say. Since trading as low as $42.25 a share in May, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal's</ENAMEX> shares have rallied as high as $57.87 in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> composite trading. They closed Friday at $53.25, down 50 cents on the day.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal Express</ENAMEX> officials acknowledge mistakes in their drive overseas but say it will pay off eventually. Analysts expect <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal</ENAMEX>'s earnings to improve again in its fiscal third quarter ending Feb. 28, when the company should begin benefiting from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tiger</ENAMEX>'s extra flights, back-up planes and landing rights. Until then, they expect the cost of integrating the two carriers to continue crimping profits.
For now, the union issue is the most nettlesome of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal</ENAMEX>'s Tiger problems, management believes. Although encouraging dialogue between managers and workers, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Smith</ENAMEX> doesn't countenance what he considers insubordination. When a large group of pilots once signed petitions opposing work-rule and compensation changes, he called a meeting in a company hangar and dressed them down for challenging his authority. He then made most of the changes, pilots say.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Smith</ENAMEX> angered <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal's</ENAMEX> pilots, too. In his haste to seal the deal with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tiger</ENAMEX> Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Saul Steinberg</ENAMEX> last August, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Smith</ENAMEX> ignored a promise that he had made to his own pilots three years ago: that any fliers acquired in future mergers would be ``end-tailed'' -- put at the bottom of the pilot seniority list that determines work schedules, pay and career options. The Tiger merger agreement stipulated that the lists be combined on the basis of tenure.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Smith</ENAMEX> is trying hard to allay the anger. And even some pro-union pilots say his charisma and popularity among the many former military fliers could be tough to beat. ``A lot of people are identifying a vote for representation as a vote against <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Fred Smith</ENAMEX>,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">J.X. Gollich</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tiger-turned-Federal</ENAMEX> pilot and union activist.
Such animosity could prove pivotal in the union vote. A large majority of the 961 former Tiger fliers support the union, according to a union study. But though most of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">1,087 Federal</ENAMEX> pilots are believed opposed, it is unclear just how much their loyalty to Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Smith</ENAMEX> has been eroded.
The fight has turned ugly and, among pilots at least, has shattered the esprit de corps that Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Smith</ENAMEX> worked so hard to build. Anti-union pilots have held ballot-burning parties. Some younger pilots say they have had to endure anti-union harangues by senior pilots while flying across the country.
And for now, at least, the competition isn't the only enemy. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Barney Barnhardt</ENAMEX>, a 727 captain and leader of the pro-union forces, said he has received two anonymous death threats and been challenged to a fight with tire irons by a colleague. ``The pilots are either for us or extremely against us,'' he says with a sigh.
