<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL Corp.</ENAMEX>'s third-quarter net income fell 72%, but that reflected a large year-earlier special gain and sizable expense this year for stock appreciation rights tied to recent takeover activity.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX>, parent of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Airlines</ENAMEX>, said net income fell to $110.9 million, or $5.11 a share, from $402.4 million, or $18.68 a share. The year-earlier quarter included a one-time after-tax gain of $223.4 million from the sale of interests in its computerized reservations partnership, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Covia</ENAMEX>.
The company said its third-quarter results reflected the recent sharp climb in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> stock to $282 a share as of Sept. 29, sparked by bids from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Los Angeles</ENAMEX> investor <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Marvin Davis</ENAMEX> and a labor-management buy-out group. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX>'s board approved the labor-management bid Sept. 14. But the bid collapsed two weeks ago, and the stock has dropped sharply since. Thus, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> said it expects to reverse most of the stock appreciation expenses in the fourth quarter.
The stock appreciation rights are related to stock options that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> officers hold. As the value of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> stock rises, the company must reflect this in its accounting methods as an increased expense.
In <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> composite trading yesterday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> shares rose $9.75 to $170.75 on volume of 1.1 million shares.
Excluding the stock appreciation expense this year and the special gain last year, per-share earnings would have been $6.74 in the third quarter, compared with $8.31. Most industry analysts expected <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> to report third-quarter earnings of around $7 a share.
Third-quarter revenue rose 7% to $2.58 billion from $2.41 billion. Third-quarter traffic was up 3% to 19.3 billion revenue passenger miles from 18.8 billion in the year earlier. A revenue passenger mile is one paying passenger flown one mile.
For the nine months, net income fell 71% to $317.3 million, or $14.66 a share, from $1.1 billion, or $34.35 a share, which includes the gain from the sale of Covia interests. Revenue increased 10% to $7.43 billion from $6.76 billion. Traffic was nearly flat at 52.8 billion revenue passenger miles vs. 52.6 billion miles a year earlier.
Separately, the leadership of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX>'s machinists union met to discuss the possibility of proposing a recapitalization to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX>'s board. The leadership came to no conclusion, and discussions will continue. The board said Monday it believes the company should remain independent for now. Takeover stock traders and other investors, however, have been pushing for some form of recapitalization to regain the losses they suffered when the labor-management bid collapsed.
