<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Fireman's Fund Corp.</ENAMEX> said third-quarter net income plunged 85% to $7.2 million from last year's $49.1 million, or 99 cents a share, because of ravages of Hurricane Hugo and increased reserves for legal expenses.
Payout of preferred dividends resulted in a net loss of five cents a share in the most recent quarter. Revenue edged up 3.4% to $904 million from $874 million in last year's third quarter.
In <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> composite trading, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Fireman's</ENAMEX> closed at $35.50 a share, down 50 cents.
Impact of the Oct. 17 <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">San Francisco</ENAMEX> earthquake, which will be recorded in the fourth quarter, isn't expected to exceed $50 million after taxes, the company added.
Hurricane Hugo accounted for about $36 million in pretax third-quarter losses, net of reinsurance recoveries.
The company said there was an additional increase in loss and loss-expense reserves of $71 million reflecting ``higher than expected'' development in claims legal expenses from to prior periods.
For the third quarter, net premiums were $742 million, up 9.6% from $677 million in last year's quarter, because of the expiration of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">National Indemnity</ENAMEX> quota share reinsurance agreement.
Net premiums written through Sept. 30 fell 5% to $2.1 billion from $2.2 billion a year ago, because of the writing of fewer policies at flat prices, the company said.
