A group including <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ESL Partners Ltd.</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Fort Worth</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Texas</ENAMEX>, investment partnership, and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Richard E. Rainwater</ENAMEX>, a former adviser to the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Fort Worth</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bass</ENAMEX> family, said it reduced its stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Anacomp Inc.</ENAMEX> to 3.6% of the common shares outstanding.
An <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Anacomp</ENAMEX> official said the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Indianapolis</ENAMEX> computer-services concern had no comment on the group's share sales.
In March, the group disclosed it held a 7.2% stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Anacomp</ENAMEX> for investment purposes. It said then it had had and would continue to have discussions with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Anacomp</ENAMEX>'s management concerning its investment.
