<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MGM Grand Inc.</ENAMEX> has agreed to pay $93 million and nearly 1.8 million common shares to buy 117 acres of land along the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Las Vegas</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Nev.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Strip</ENAMEX> as a site for its planned movie-studio and theme-park resort.
The purchase price was disclosed in a preliminary prospectus issued in connection with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MGM Grand</ENAMEX>'s planned offering of six million common shares. The luxury airline and casino company, 98.6%-owned by investor <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kirk Kerkorian</ENAMEX> and his <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tracinda Corp.</ENAMEX>, earlier this month announced its agreements to acquire the properties, but didn't disclose the purchase price.
The proposed stock offering and issuance of nearly 1.8 million common shares in connection with the land purchase will bring <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MGM Grand</ENAMEX>'s total shares outstanding to 28.7 million, of which 72% will be owned by Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kerkorian</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Tracinda</ENAMEX>, according to the prospectus.
In over-the-counter trading, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MGM</ENAMEX> Grand was bid at $17.50 a share.
Proceeds from the offering are expected to be used for remodeling the company's <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Desert Inn</ENAMEX> resort in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Las Vegas</ENAMEX>, refurbishing certain aircraft of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MGM Grand Air</ENAMEX> unit, and to acquire the property for the new resort. The company said it estimates the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Desert Inn</ENAMEX> remodeling will cost about $32 million, and the refurbishment of the three DC-8-62 aircraft, made by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mcdonnell Douglas Corp.</ENAMEX>, will cost around $24.5 million.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MGM Grand</ENAMEX> said the latest stock offering won't cover the $600 million or more cost of building the proposed resort and theme park, and added it will need to seek additional financing, either through bank borrowings or debt and equity offerings, at a later date. Construction is set to begin in early 1991.
The resort will include the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MGM Grand Hotel</ENAMEX>, a multi-spired, castle-like facility that will include 5,000 rooms and 85,000 square feet of casino space. The facility will be marketed toward families, and room rates will be between $35 and $55 a night, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MGM Grand</ENAMEX> said.
The prospectus didn't include many details about the studio and theme park, although conceptual drawings, released this month, show that it may feature several ``themed'' areas similar to those found at parks built by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Walt Disney Co.</ENAMEX>
