Traders credited <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Euro Disney</ENAMEX>'s share performance to the tremendous hyping of the project that the shares are destined to help finance: <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Walt Disney Co.</ENAMEX>'s 4,800-acre theme park 20 miles east of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Paris</ENAMEX>. The park is slated to open in 1992.
``The issue was very well-received -- <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Disney</ENAMEX> is such a well-known, you can say world-wide, name,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Vernon Dempsey</ENAMEX>, head trader of European equities at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Kleinwort Benson Ltd.</ENAMEX>, which is making a market in the issue.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dempsey</ENAMEX> estimated that the issue's <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX> debut was accompanied by ``very, very heavy turnover -- between five million and six million shares.'' Most of the buying was institutional, he added.
Official trading in the shares will start in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Paris</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Brussels</ENAMEX> on Nov. 6, when the French-franc denominated offering, valued at the equivalent of nearly $1 billion, comes to market in the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">European Community</ENAMEX>. U.S. investors will be permitted to buy the shares from EC investors 90 days later.
Because of the interest connected with the issue, the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX> exchange took the unusual step of letting traders establish an officially sanctioned when-issued market.
``A lot of people are getting hurt on this wicked whipsawing,'' cautioned <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Alistair Cuddeford</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Salomon Brothers International Ltd.</ENAMEX> trader who makes a market in franc-denominated <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Euro Disney</ENAMEX> shares. ``There should be no great rush for investors to buy this. A lot of big European banks, mostly French, and Swiss arb accounts have been buying the stock just to flip it'' for a quick profit, he said.
