<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Intel Corp.</ENAMEX>'s most powerful computer chip has flaws that could delay several computer makers' marketing efforts, but the ``bugs'' aren't expected to hurt <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Intel</ENAMEX> and most computer makers.
But while <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">International Business Machines Corp.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Compaq Computer Corp.</ENAMEX> say the bugs will delay products, most big computer makers said the flaws don't affect them. ``Bugs like this are just a normal part of product development,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Richard Archuleta</ENAMEX>, director of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hewlett-Packard Co.</ENAMEX>'s advanced systems development. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hewlett</ENAMEX> announced last week that it planned to ship a computer based on the 486 chip early next year. ``These bugs don't affect our schedule at all,'' he said.
Most of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Compaq</ENAMEX>'s decline is being attributed to a third-quarter earnings report that came in at the low end of analysts' expectations.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Intel</ENAMEX> said it had corrected the problems and would start producing bugless chips next week. ``We should not be seeing any more,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bill Rash</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Intel</ENAMEX>'s director for the 486 chip.
What's more, the bugs only emerge on esoteric applications such as computer-aided design and scientific calculations, he said, and then very seldom. ``These errata do not affect business programs,'' he said. The bugs will cause problems in ``specific and rare circumstances that will not occur in typical applications'' such as word-processing and spreadsheets, said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Michael Slater</ENAMEX>, editor of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Microprocessor Report</ENAMEX>, an industry newsletter.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sun</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hewlett-Packard</ENAMEX> and others say <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Intel</ENAMEX> isn't wholly to blame for the snafu. The real culprits, they said, are computer makers such as <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IBM</ENAMEX> that have jumped the gun to unveil 486-based products. ``The reason this is getting so much visibility is that some started shipping and announced early availability,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hewlett-Packard</ENAMEX>'s Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Archuleta</ENAMEX>. ``You can do that but you're taking a risk. Those companies are paying the price for taking the risk.''
In late September, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IBM</ENAMEX> began shipping a plug-in card that converts its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">PS</ENAMEX>\ model 70-A21 from a 80386 machine to an 80486 machine. An <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IBM</ENAMEX> spokeswoman said the company told customers Monday about the bugs and temporarily stopped shipping the product.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IBM</ENAMEX> has no plans to recall its add-on cards, the spokeswoman said, and could probably circumvent the bugs without long product delays. ``We don't look at this as a major problem for us,'' she said.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Compaq</ENAMEX>, which said it discovered the bugs, still plans to announce new 486 products on Nov. 6. Because of the glitch, however, the company said it doesn't know when its machine will be commercially available. That's a break from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Compaq</ENAMEX> tradition, because the company doesn't announce products until they're actually at the dealers.
The problem is being ballyhooed, experts say, because the 486 is <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Intel</ENAMEX>'s future flagship. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Intel</ENAMEX>'s microprocessors are the chips of choice in many of today's personal computers and the 80486 microprocessor is the spearhead of the company's bid to guard that spot in the next generation of machines.
``Although these sorts of bugs are not at all uncommon, the 486 is an extremely high-profile product,'' said Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Slater</ENAMEX>, the newsletter editor.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Intel</ENAMEX>'s 80486 chip is the Corvette of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Intel</ENAMEX>'s microprocessors, a super-fast, super-expensive chip that only the most power-hungry computer users are likely to buy for at least several years.
Machines using the 486 are expected to challenge higher-priced work stations and minicomputers in applications such as so-called servers, which connect groups of computers together, and in computer-aided design.
That's what will keep computer makers coming in spite of the irritation of bugs. Big personal computer makers and many makers of engineering workstations are developing 486-based machines, which are expected to reach the market early next year.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Andy Zipser</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dallas</ENAMEX> contributed to this article.
