<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ratners Group PLC</ENAMEX>'s U.S. subsidiary has agreed to acquire jewelry retailer <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Weisfield's Inc.</ENAMEX> for $50 a share, or about $55 million.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ratners</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Weisfield's</ENAMEX> said they reached an agreement in principle for the acquisition of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Weisfield</ENAMEX>'s by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sterling Inc.</ENAMEX> The companies said the acquisition is subject to a definitive agreement. They said they expect the transaction to be completed by Dec. 15.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Weisfield</ENAMEX>'s, based in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Seattle</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Wash.</ENAMEX>, currently operates 87 specialty jewelry stores in nine states. In the fiscal year ended Jan. 31, the company reported sales of $59.5 million and pretax profit of $2.9 million.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ratners</ENAMEX>, which controls 25% of the British jewelry market, would increase the number of its U.S. stores to about 450 stores from 360. It has said it hopes to control 5% of jewelry business in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> by 1992; currently it controls about 2%.
