A shiny new takeover deal sparked a big rally in stock prices, which buoyed the dollar. Bond prices also edged higher.
Despite all the furor over program trading, program trading played a big role in yesterday's rally. Some traders point out that as the big brokerage firms back out of program trading for their own accounts or for clients, opportunities increase for others to engage in the controversial practice. That's what happened yesterday.
The rally notwithstanding, there are plenty of worries about the short-term course of stock prices. A slowing economy and its effect on corporate earnings is the foremost concern of many traders and analysts. Unless the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal Reserve</ENAMEX> eases interest rates soon to stimulate the economy, profits could remain disappointing.
Yesterday's major economic news -- a 0.2% rise in the September index of leading economic indicators -- had little impact on financial markets. But the next important piece of news on the economy's health -- this morning's release of the national purchasing manager's survey for October -- could prompt investors into action.
A report late yesterday that the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chicago</ENAMEX>-area purchasing managers survey showed increased economic activity in that part of the country cut into bond-price gains. If the national survey confirms a pickup in the manufacturing sector, it could further depress bond prices while bolstering stock prices and the dollar.
Meanwhile, bond investors are laboring under the onus of a national debt ceiling debate. Although the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Treasury</ENAMEX> is expected to announce details of its November quarterly refunding operation today, the Nov. 79 schedule could be delayed unless <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Congress</ENAMEX> and the president act soon to lift the nation's debt ceiling.
