<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford Motor Co.</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ltd.</ENAMEX>, the U.K. unit of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford Motor Co.</ENAMEX>, said it offered its hourly workers a 15% raise in wages over two years as a first offer in contract talks.
A <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> spokesman said 33,000 manual workers at the company's 21 plants in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.K.</ENAMEX> have been offered 8% in the first year and 7% in the second year.
But <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Charlie Whelan</ENAMEX>, an official of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Amalgamated Engineering Union</ENAMEX>, said the offer was rejected by union leaders as ``totally unacceptable.''
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> wage settlement will be watched closely as a barometer of wage inflation in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.K.</ENAMEX> The annual underlying average increase in wages is currently running at about 8.75%, and overall inflation at about 7.6%. Prime Minister <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Margaret Thatcher</ENAMEX> urged companies not to give in to demands that would aggravate inflation.
Union leaders earlier this month lodged a claim for a ``significant'' raise, aimed at bringing <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX>'s hourly wages in line with the motor company's European plants. The unions haven't made a counter-demand to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX>. They recently rejected <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Vauxhall Motors Ltd.</ENAMEX>'s offer of a 9.1% raise, made as part of a two-year package.
