<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX> share prices closed sharply lower Thursday after the market's confidence in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.K.</ENAMEX> corporate profits was shaken severely by bellwether <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Imperial Chemical Industries PLC</ENAMEX>'s disappointing earnings in the third quarter.
Stocks rose in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tokyo</ENAMEX> for the first time since Monday, and ended mixed in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Frankfurt</ENAMEX>.
In <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">ICI</ENAMEX>, which is part of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Financial Times</ENAMEX> 100-share index, said its pretax profit for the quarter dropped 12%, significantly worse than market expectations. Its profit for the first nine months of the year rose only 9%, also short of market expectations.
As <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ICI</ENAMEX>'s share price fell, the 100-share index followed. The index closed at its intraday low of 2129.4, down 32.5 points.
``<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ICI</ENAMEX> is a bellwether of U.K. corporate profitability,'' a senior dealer with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warburg Securities</ENAMEX> said. ``Its results were disappointing. The market followed.''
The 30-share index fell 31.4 points to close at 1720.5. Volume was 443.6 million shares traded, better than 374.6 million Wednesday, but still a relatively thin session.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ICI</ENAMEX> finished 73 pence a share lower at # 10.97 ($17.70) on turnover of 3.4 million shares.
Analysts had anticipated soft earnings in petrochemicals and plastics, but said they were surprised by trading losses in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">ICI</ENAMEX>'s specialty paints and films operations.
Dealers and analysts also said that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ICI</ENAMEX>'s troubles in specialty paints helped underscore growing worries over the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> economy. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ICI</ENAMEX>'s paint operations are heavily involved in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX>
Those concerns were fortified by <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Wall Street</ENAMEX>'s continued slide, with the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> Industrial Average down 35.25 points at 2618.03 when <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX> closed.
In other shares, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.K.</ENAMEX> textile group <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tootal</ENAMEX> rose 7 to 120 pence on conditional clearance from regulators for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coats Viyella's</ENAMEX> bid for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tootal</ENAMEX>, so long as <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Coats</ENAMEX> spins off its U.K. sewing thread business. Coats slid 5 to 142.
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tokyo</ENAMEX> stocks rebounded sharply from two consecutive daily losses, helped by index-related buying by investment funds in the afternoon session.
On Thursday, the market opened in a bullish mood with participation from institutional investors, who had refrained from active trading in the past couple of months.
Market observers attributed improved sentiment to the recent stability of the dollar, which offset expectations that the U.S. currency might surge above the 145-150 yen level.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nikkei</ENAMEX> continued to gain during the afternoon session, briefly reaching above its recent record level.
Outstanding winners Thursday were non-life insurance and securities companies.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Yasuda Fire & Marine</ENAMEX> advanced 90 yen to 1,680 yen ($11.90). <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Taisho Marine & Fire</ENAMEX> was up 80 at 1,620, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tokio Marine & Fire</ENAMEX> advanced 40 to 2,230.
Securities companies also made across-the-board gains as recent increases in stock trading volume are expected to boost their commission income, traders said.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Yamaichi Securities</ENAMEX> gained 120 to 1,940, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nomura Securities</ENAMEX> surged 260 to 3,450, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nikko Securities</ENAMEX> gained 110 to 1,940.
Steel shares also ended higher. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sumitomo Metal</ENAMEX> was up 22 to 703, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nippon Steel</ENAMEX> advanced 24 to 735.
Frankfurt prices ended mixed in thin trading after an early rally led by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Deutsche Bank</ENAMEX> fizzled during the session. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">DAX</ENAMEX> index, which reached a peak around 1500 early in the day, closed at 1482.62, up only 1.54 points from Wednesday.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Deutsche Bank</ENAMEX> surged at the opening on news that the bank has 10% holdings in several large companies, including insurer <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Allianz</ENAMEX> and reinsurer Munich Re. Because the shares are kept at the historically lowest value on the books, they constitute huge hidden reserves, traders said.
The disclosure late Wednesday came as <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Deutsche Bank</ENAMEX> announced the issue of 1.2 million new shares for placement in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tokyo</ENAMEX> market.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Deutsche Bank</ENAMEX> jumped 28.5 marks early in the session, pulling the broader market along, traders said.
But profit-taking soon wiped out these gains, traders said. While <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Deutsche Bank</ENAMEX> was still 12 marks higher at 657 ($358) at the close, most other blue-chip shares had small losses.
Traders said the late decline points to a deep sense of unease in the market.
Many investment funds have already closed their books for the year, a dealer said. ``People have made excellent profits in the first 10 months, and they don't want to risk that any more. The mood is very cautious, so I don't think we will go firmer any time soon.''
But other traders said there are good buying opportunities at the lower levels because the market should soon pull out of its slump. They pointed to last year's example, when the stock market staged a major rally just before the Christmas holidays.
Among other banks, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dresdner Bank</ENAMEX> gained 1.5 to 321.5 after receiving official authorization to acquire <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Banque</ENAMEX> Internationale <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">de Placement</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">France</ENAMEX>, but <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Commerzbank</ENAMEX> slipped 0.5 to 246.
Elsewhere, share prices closed higher in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Zurich</ENAMEX>, lower in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Paris</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Brussels</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Milan</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Amsterdam</ENAMEX>, and mixed in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Stockholm</ENAMEX>.
Stocks closed higher in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Sydney</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Taipei</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Wellington</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Seoul</ENAMEX>, lower in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hong Kong</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Singapore</ENAMEX> and mixed in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Manila</ENAMEX>.
