<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">REAL ESTATE INVESTMENT TRUSTS</ENAMEX>, or <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Reits</ENAMEX>, were the darlings of investors in the 1960s. But they started to fall on hard times in 1974.
These pooled investments in trusts, which drew income from owned properties or from interest on mortgages, were hit by the real estate doldrums of that year. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Overbuilding</ENAMEX>, inflation, high interest and materials costs, mortgage defaults and some questionable lending practices combined to hurt <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Reits</ENAMEX>.
Cash-pressed, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Reits</ENAMEX> in 1974 began to sell out at bargain prices, merge with stronger ones, omit dividends and even fail. That year 19 of the 20 biggest losers on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> were Reits; as much as 96% of their market value was wiped out.
In their heyday, after their debut with federal blessing in 1960 as a spur for real-estate investments, they were popular because they had tax-free status if they paid 90% (currently 95%) of their profits to shareholders.
``The outlook for the industry is grim,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Howard Foster</ENAMEX>, an <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">E.F. Hutton</ENAMEX> analyst, in January 1974. He predicted that the number of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Reits</ENAMEX> would plunge to 50 from 207. Some did fail within a few years, but there are 169 today.
Since the real-estate recovery in the early 1980s, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Reits</ENAMEX>' assets have risen steadily to about $41 billion currently from a record $40.6 billion last year and $7 billion in 1980. In 1974, the figure was $21.2 billion.
