Disappointing earnings news from some technology companies unnerved investors in the over-the-counter market, who sold shares of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Apple Computer</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Intel</ENAMEX> and many other computer-related concerns.
The drop in those and other technology stocks contributed to an 0.7% slide by the Nasdaq composite index. It finished at 467.22, down 3.45. The nervousness about the technology stock outlook also hurt the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> Industrial Average, which slipped about 1%.
Mostly because of the sell-off in technology stocks, the Nasdaq 100 Index of the OTC's largest non-financial issues dropped 4.58 to 457.52. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nasdaq Financial</ENAMEX> Index of giant insurance and banking issues lost 2.38 to 458.32.
Some traders said the sell-off of technology stocks on low volume reflected a lack of conviction by investors. But <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Charlie Howley</ENAMEX>, vice president in charge of OTC trading at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Soundview Financial</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Stamford</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Conn.</ENAMEX>, said the selling was orderly.
``It's a quiet retreat,'' said Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Howley</ENAMEX>. ``It's nothing dramatic, just a routine sell-off.'' Some of it was due to lower-than-expected earnings from leading companies, he said. But some of it also represented profit-taking by investors who have made big gains in some issues.
Yesterday's volume of 117.2 million shares was far below last week's sizzling average of nearly 177 million. For October so far, daily volume is averaging 150.3 million, putting it on track to be the year's busiest month.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Apple Computer</ENAMEX>, which reported lackluster earnings Friday, lost 1 1/4 to 46 3/4 on 1.1 million shares. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Stratus Computer</ENAMEX>, which reported earnings late Friday that were in line with a disappointing forecast, eased 3/4 to 24 on 816,000 shares.
Investors apparently didn't like the news from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rainbow Technologies</ENAMEX> either. It said net income was 17 cents a share in the third quarter, compared with 16 cents a share a year earlier. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rainbow</ENAMEX>'s stock dropped 2 to 14 1/4.
Among takeover stocks, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jefferson Smurfit</ENAMEX> jumped 1 1/4 to 42 1/2 after <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">SIBV</ENAMEX>-<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MS Holdings</ENAMEX> said the price to be paid to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jefferson Smurfit</ENAMEX>'s minority holders has been raised to $43 a share. The increase of $1.25 a share is being made to settle shareholder litigation relating to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">SIBV</ENAMEX>-<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MS</ENAMEX>'s tender offer.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">SIBV-MS Holdings</ENAMEX> is a new company jointly owned by an affiliate of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jefferson Smurfit</ENAMEX> and a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Morgan Stanley</ENAMEX> limited partnership. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jefferson Smurfit</ENAMEX> affiliate, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Smurfit International B.V.</ENAMEX>, holds about 78% of the shares outstanding. These shares will be bought by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">SIBV</ENAMEX>-<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MS Holdings</ENAMEX> at $41.75 each after the acquisition of the minority shares.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Michael R. Weisberg</ENAMEX>, partner in charge of research at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Robertson Stephens & Co.</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">San Francisco</ENAMEX>, said some investors have already made the switch. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Robertson Stephens</ENAMEX> Index of 340 emerging growth stocks is up 23.1% for the year through Friday. The rise matches that of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> industrials this year.
``It's been a spectacular year for the emerging growth stock investor,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Weisberg</ENAMEX> said. He predicted that the most popular growth companies will be those with ``some kind of unique product or franchise'' that makes them appear able to sustain their momentum. He puts the OTC market's <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nellcor</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Office Club</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bizmart</ENAMEX> on the list.
Elsewhere, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Valley National</ENAMEX> continued its slide, dropping 2 1/8 to 15 on 1.7 million shares. The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Arizona</ENAMEX> banking concern is facing difficulties related to weakness in the real estate market in the state.
