<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">BROWN-FORMAN Corp.</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Louisville</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ky.</ENAMEX>) -- <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">David R. Jackson</ENAMEX>, formerly vice president, managing director of corporate communications for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Maxwell Communication Inc.</ENAMEX>, was named vice president and assistant to the chairman of this maker of alcoholic beverages and consumer products.
