The maker of household products said the new dividend is payable Dec. 1 to shares of record Nov. 10.
Separately, the company's board adopted a proposal to amend its 1986 shareholder rights plan, further insulating the company from takeover.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rubbermaid</ENAMEX> officials said they aren't aware of any effort to take over the company, but believed the shareholder plan needed to be strengthened. ``The board has stated repeatedly that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rubbermaid</ENAMEX> should be independent,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Walter W. Williams</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rubbermaid</ENAMEX> president.
Some changes to the plan were minor adjustments, but the most significant was an amendment that provides that if any investor holds 25% or more of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rubbermaid</ENAMEX>'s voting securities, each right held by others would entitle the holder to buy <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rubbermaid</ENAMEX> shares with a market value of twice the right's exercise price.
