Its capital spending is growing at double-digit rates for the second year in a row, and its superefficient producers of everything from cars to computer chips are rushing to expand capacity, modernize factories and develop new products.
``The boom's so huge,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mitsuru Saito</ENAMEX>, an economist at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sanwa Research Institute</ENAMEX>, ``it makes you think of the Golden'60s,'' when <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX> developed rapidly.
The more factories and robots Japanese manufacturers add, the more they will be able to export, and the less their domestic customers will need to import.
So big is the capital-spending boom that Japanese companies' outlays in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX> topped American companies' domestic outlays by $521.4 billion to $494.8 billion in the 12 months ended March 31 even though <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX>'s total output of goods and services is less than two-thirds <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">America</ENAMEX>'s.
From a financial standpoint, the boom couldn't come at a better time. Many Japanese companies expect record profits this fiscal year, and Japanese interest rates, though up a bit recently, are still low. And in a business system where shareholders have few rights and expect only modest dividends, companies can plow their profits back into plant and equipment.
But the worriers remain unconvinced. With <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX> running enormous trade surpluses against much of the world, they think that <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX> should meet the increased domestic demand by importing more. And eventually, they contend, domestic demand will weaken, forcing companies to emphasize exports again. ``If there's a further drive to export,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Nobuyuki Arai</ENAMEX>, an economist at the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Japan Development Bank</ENAMEX>, ``that'll be a problem.''
In contrast to previous economic booms, Japanese auto companies aren't just trying to boost production. Many are pouring money into developing high-quality products to target affluent consumers and, to some extent, to avoid direct combat with cheaper cars from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">South Korea</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Taiwan</ENAMEX>. Others are replacing older facilities with flexible assembly lines on which different models can be turned out at once. So many companies are investing in high-tech machinery that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Fanuc Ltd.</ENAMEX>, a robot maker, also had to build a new plant. The buildup is ``making <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX> clearly more efficient, more technologically advanced and more competitive,'' declares a Western diplomat in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tokyo</ENAMEX>.
With demand growing and workers in short supply, many Japanese manufacturers are spending heavily on automation. Among them are the shipbuilders, which had halved their shipyard work forces to cut costs during a prolonged slump in demand but now are capturing an increased share of the strengthening global market. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sasebo Heavy Industries Co.</ENAMEX>, a medium-sized shipbuilder, expects its sales to increase 30% this year, largely because of rising demand for oil tankers.
The emphasis on market share is evident at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Daikin Industries Ltd.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX>'s biggest maker of industrial air conditioners. Seeing new office buildings sprout up and its sales soar, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Daikin</ENAMEX> is building another plant, which will lift its production capacity 50%. The expansion is aimed not just at meeting demand but also at expanding the company's market share to 30% from 27% currently. Besides, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Daikin</ENAMEX>'s major competitors, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hitachi Ltd.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mitsubishi Heavy Industries Ltd.</ENAMEX>, ``are all adding production lines,'' a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Daikin</ENAMEX> spokesman says. ``Until now, we were trying to increase productivity with the facilities we already had. But we can't produce enough anymore.''
The competition is even more heated in the auto industry, where companies are racing one another in a world-wide market. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nissan</ENAMEX> aims to expand its 25% share of the market to 30% by spending $141 million on a plant in southern <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX> that could make as many as 240,000 cars a year. Meanwhile, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Toyota Motor Corp.</ENAMEX>'s $247 million buildup is increasing its annual capacity by 180,000 cars, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Honda</ENAMEX> is spending $317 million on expansion. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mazda Motor Corp.</ENAMEX> is still considering its options, but it boldly aims to double its annual domestic sales to 800,000 cars in the next four years.
Moreover, much of the investment boom is in high-tech fields in which Japanese companies have only limited foreign competition; so, more investment practically assures more exports. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Toshiba Corp.</ENAMEX>, for example, is spending $986 million on two new plants to build four-megabit dynamic random access memories, the next generation of computer chips. The product isn't widely used yet, but <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Toshiba</ENAMEX>, which has already beaten everyone else in producing the current-generation one-megabit <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Drams</ENAMEX>, believes that its early investment will heighten its chances of beating its competitors again. ``It's important to gain leadership,'' a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Toshiba</ENAMEX> spokesman says.
Meanwhile, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Toshiba</ENAMEX>'s Japanese rivals, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hitachi</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Fujitsu Ltd.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NEC Corp.</ENAMEX>, aren't sitting still. After doubling production in one plant, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NEC</ENAMEX> is spending $275 million to build another plant that, in two years, will be able to make a million four-megabit Drams a year. The new chip plants ``won't be excessive investment,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hajime Sasaki</ENAMEX>, an <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NEC</ENAMEX> vice president. ``We have enough products to make and the markets to sell these products.''
What if its sales weaken someday? Japanese companies have a caveat competitor attitude. If excess capacity develops, they say, not everyone will suffer. The losers will be those with the least attractive products, and many of them, analysts think, will be foreign companies.
