<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford Motor Co.</ENAMEX> intensified its battle with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">General Motors Corp.</ENAMEX> over <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar PLC</ENAMEX> by saying it is prepared to make a bid for all of the British auto maker when restrictions on its shareholding are lifted.
``We have not made that decision'' to seek a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> special shareholders' meeting, said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Martyn Watkins</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> spokesman in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX>. He emphasized that the car maker only would bid for all of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> under the right circumstances, and said ``those circumstances aren't right or possible at the moment.''
Last month, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> announced plans to acquire as much as 15% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX>. Since then, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> officials have confirmed that they are discussing an alliance with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX> and said last week that they hoped to reach an agreement within a month.
Analysts have been expecting a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX>-<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> pact that would give the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> car maker an eventual 30% stake in the British company and create joint ventures that would produce an executive-model range of cars. But the specter of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> eventually launching a full-fledged bid could unravel the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX>-<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> talks.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> seems to be losing interest in giving <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX> a minority stake, said one individual close to the talks, adding, ``It wouldn't surprise me if {<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> executives} want to wait and see what the color of that {<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> bid} is'' first. He predicted <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> officials will meet with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> executives in the next week to outline their proposed offer. Sir <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John Egan</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX>'s chairman, so far has refused to meet with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> officials, but he is believed to be willing to consider a specific bid proposal.
As for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX>, its ``fallback position has to be a full bid itself,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stephen Reitman</ENAMEX>, European auto-industry analyst at <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX> brokers <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UBS-Phillips & Drew</ENAMEX>. A <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> takeover of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> would ``have such implications for the balance of power in the 1990s that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">General Motors</ENAMEX> can't afford to step aside. They will have to throw their hat in the ring.''
A <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX> spokesman yesterday reiterated the company's interest in acquiring a minority stake to help <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> remain independent.
A pitched battle could mean <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> would fetch # 10 ($16.02) a share, or about # 1.8 billion ($2.88 billion), several analysts believe. The prospect of such a takeover fight has sent <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> shares soaring in recent weeks. U.S. takeover-stock speculators now own an estimated 25% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> shares. In a declining <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX> stock market yesterday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> shares were down four pence from Monday in late trading, at 694 pence ($11.11) a share. In the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX>'s American depositary receipts rose 12.5 cents in over-the-counter trading, to $11.25.
