<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stuart E. Eizenstat</ENAMEX>, a partner in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Washington</ENAMEX> law firm of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Powell</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Goldstein</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Frazer & Murphy</ENAMEX>, was named a director of this utility holding company, increasing board membership to 14.
