When <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Adolph Coors Co.</ENAMEX> announced the appointment of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">William Coors</ENAMEX> as president late Wednesday, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peter Coors</ENAMEX> wasn't promoted -- at least not officially.
But the announcement by the big <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Golden</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Colo.</ENAMEX>, brewer was an implicit statement of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peter Coor</ENAMEX>'s rising role at the company, analysts say. It also underscores the difficult task ahead as <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coors</ENAMEX> attempts to purchase <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Stroh Brewery Co.</ENAMEX> and fight off increasingly tough competition from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Anheuser-Busch Cos.</ENAMEX>
The latest management shuffling at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coors</ENAMEX> seemed to focus on <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jeffrey Coors</ENAMEX>, who will relinquish the president's post to his uncle <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">William</ENAMEX>, who is 73. The elder <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coors</ENAMEX> has been chairman since 1970. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jeffrey</ENAMEX>, who at 44 is one year older than his brother <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peter</ENAMEX>, will head up <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coors Technology Co.</ENAMEX>, a small unit he has run for several years.
But <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coors</ENAMEX> insists the administrative changes won't really shift responsibilities at the company. Indeed, a spokesman for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coors</ENAMEX> said that since January, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peter</ENAMEX> has been reporting directly to <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">William</ENAMEX>, rather than to his brother. The change in titles ``makes the structure conform to the reality,'' the spokesman said. (<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">William</ENAMEX>, the brothers, another brother <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Joe Jr.</ENAMEX>, and their father <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Joseph Sr</ENAMEX>. all serve on the company's nine-member board.)
According to analysts, the changes reflect the tough task the company faces in integrating the operations and marketing efforts of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Stroh</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coors</ENAMEX>, steering the merger through the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Justice Department</ENAMEX> and continuing to fight the battle <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coors</ENAMEX> is waging with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Anheuser</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Miller Brewing Co.</ENAMEX>, a unit of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Philip Morris Cos.</ENAMEX>
``It's gray-beard time,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Tom Pirko</ENAMEX>, president of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bevmark Inc.</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Los Angeles</ENAMEX> consulting firm, referring to the move of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">William</ENAMEX> into the presidency. ``This is a time of tremendous risk at the company, and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peter</ENAMEX> has a tremendous amount of responsibility.'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Putting William</ENAMEX> at the helm probably won't increase the elder <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coors</ENAMEX>'s imput into the beer business, but ``it doesn't hurt to have a senior statesman at the top,'' he said.
In a brief telephone interview yesterday, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peter Coors</ENAMEX> said his uncle ``is our leader. We depend on all his years of experience and knowledge in the industry, and that doesn't change.'' But in January, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peter</ENAMEX> said, his uncle told him and his brothers, ``You guys run those units.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coors</ENAMEX> stressed that the removal of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jeff</ENAMEX> from the presidency wasn't a demotion, but would allow him to devote his full attention to his unit. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coors</ENAMEX> has continually pointed to the importance of the technology unit to its diversification efforts.
But overall, ``<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coors</ENAMEX>'s success or lack thereof depends on the beer business,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Emanuel Goldman</ENAMEX>, analyst at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Painewebber Inc.</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">San Francisco</ENAMEX>.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Goldman</ENAMEX> credits <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peter Coors</ENAMEX> with ``pulling <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coors</ENAMEX>'s marketing efforts into the 20th century'' by pushing for intensified marketing efforts, modern advertising campaigns and significantly higher marketing expenditures. Analysts also credit Peter with selling other family members on the purchase of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stroh</ENAMEX>, a transaction that will cost about $425 million and slap a big piece of debt on <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coors</ENAMEX>'s books for the first time in the company's history.
``<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peter</ENAMEX> had a major struggle in getting this done,'' said Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Pirko</ENAMEX>. Taking on debt was controversial within the family, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Pirko</ENAMEX> added, but in the end, ``<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peter</ENAMEX> called the shots.''
In yesterday's interview, however, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peter</ENAMEX> declined to take individual credit for the moves. ``We manage as a team here,'' he said. ``The team establishes the goals. It's the result that's important, not who's the architect or the driving force.''
And <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peter</ENAMEX> will continue to be under the gun, given the dominance of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Anheuser</ENAMEX>, the stubbornly flat beer market of the past decade and recent <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coors</ENAMEX> financial results that have been frustratingly mediocre. So far this year, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coors</ENAMEX>' market share has been slipping and so has net income, due to increased costs and increased price competition, the company said.
Price competition is about to become even more fierce. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Anheuser</ENAMEX> announced on Wednesday that it would begin discounting Budweiser, its flagship brand, which analysts say will put exceptionally heavy pressure on <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coors</ENAMEX> management in the midst of a major merger.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peter Coors</ENAMEX>, however, said the discounting by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Anheuser</ENAMEX> could also mean that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coors</ENAMEX>' increased marketing efforts are having an impact. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Furthermore</ENAMEX>, he said, ``I don't know how the industry can get too much tougher. This is just a signal that the toughness is going to continue.
