<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">GORBACHEV</ENAMEX> ANNOUNCED unilateral cuts of nuclear arms in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Baltic</ENAMEX> region.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Kremlin</ENAMEX> leader unveiled a plan to reduce nuclear weapons in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Baltic Sea</ENAMEX>, including the scrapping of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Moscow</ENAMEX>'s nuclear-armed submarines by 1991. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gorbachev</ENAMEX>, on an official visit to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Finland</ENAMEX>, also said the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Soviet Union</ENAMEX> has removed all tactical nuclear missiles that could strike <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">northern Europe</ENAMEX>. In <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Moscow</ENAMEX>, leading progressives have drafted a blueprint designed to push the nation closer to a free-market system. The plan includes liberalizing the system of prices, breaking up industrial monopolies and putting unprofitable state-owned companies out of business.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> signaled the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Soviet Union</ENAMEX> that it is willing to discuss an offer by Foreign Minister <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Shevardnadze</ENAMEX> to curtail military bases in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Europe</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">LAWSON</ENAMEX> RESIGNED as <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX>'s finance minister amid a policy dispute.
In a letter to Prime Minister <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Thatcher</ENAMEX>, the chancellor of the exchequer said he was leaving his cabinet post because ``the successful conduct of economic policy'' wasn't possible so long as Sir <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Alan Walters</ENAMEX> remained as her economic adviser. Sir <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Alan</ENAMEX>, however, also quit. Thatcher named Foreign Secretary <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Major</ENAMEX> to succeed <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lawson</ENAMEX>, and Home Secretary <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hurd</ENAMEX> was appointed foreign minister.
Sir <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Geoffrey Howe</ENAMEX>, deputy prime minister, said in the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">House</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Commons</ENAMEX> that <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX>'s economic and monetary policies would remain ``unchanged.''
An East German Politburo member met with opposition leaders in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">East Berlin</ENAMEX> for what were considered the first substantive talks on demands for Western freedoms. Communist authorities urged pro-democracy activists to halt protests for internal changes, but about 100,000 people in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dresden</ENAMEX> ignored the appeal and staged a rally.
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">South Africa</ENAMEX> has test-fired an intermediate-range ballistic missile that could carry nuclear warheads and was built with help from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Israel</ENAMEX>, a U.S. official said. The aide said <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Israel</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">South Africa</ENAMEX> also are cooperating on the development of a long-range missile. Premier <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Shamir</ENAMEX> denied that <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Israel</ENAMEX> provided any technology to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Pretoria</ENAMEX>.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">White House</ENAMEX> has reached an accord with the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Senate Intelligence Committee</ENAMEX> on new rules for covert operations to give <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bush</ENAMEX> a freer hand to involve the U.S. in foreign coup plots. The panel agreed to rescind <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Reagan</ENAMEX>-era curbs and give U.S. agents wide latitude to join coup planning, officials said.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bush</ENAMEX> extended most-favored-nation trade privileges to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hungary</ENAMEX>, saying it had honored its pledge of political and economic restructuring. The president's move, which came three days after <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Budapest</ENAMEX> declared itself a democracy, made Hungary the first country to be freed from a 1974 law denying U.S. trade credits to most communist nations.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">House</ENAMEX>-<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Senate</ENAMEX> negotiators cleared a $3.18 billion anti-drug and anti-crime initiative, trimming domestic and defense spending to pay for it. The package would put more emphasis on treatment, education and prevention programs favored by Democrats than <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bush</ENAMEX>'s smaller plan.
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">San Francisco Bay</ENAMEX> area officials urged residents of tent cities in the agricultural community of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Watsonville</ENAMEX> to move to shelters, expressing concern over health and safety dangers from unrefrigerated food and open cooking fires. Tolls on bridges went back into effect, and traffic officers resumed issuing tickets in the region.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.N.</ENAMEX> announced that its high commissioner for refugees, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jean-Pierre Hocke</ENAMEX>, resigned amid allegations of financial impropriety, mismanagement and favoritism to Western donor nations. The 51-year-old Swiss's resignation is effective Wednesday.
A <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">China Airlines</ENAMEX> jetliner crashed into a mountainside in eastern <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Taiwan</ENAMEX> and all 54 people aboard, including at least one American, were believed killed. The incident occurred shortly after the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Taiwanese</ENAMEX> plane took off from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hualien</ENAMEX>, enroute to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Taipei</ENAMEX>.
Former <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">HUD</ENAMEX> chief <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Pierce</ENAMEX> informed a House subcommittee that he will again refuse to answer its questions about mismanagement and political favoritism at the department he led for eight years under <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Reagan</ENAMEX>. He refused to testify last month, invoking his right against self-incrimination.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bush</ENAMEX> is scheduled to travel to Costa Rica today to participate in the Central American nation's celebration of 100 years of democracy. The president has ruled out any talks with <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Nicaragua</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ortega</ENAMEX> during the two-day gathering, where leaders of 18 nations are expected to discuss regional issues.
Christian and Moslem forces traded artillery fire across <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Beirut</ENAMEX>'s sectarian dividing line, the first major breach of an Arab-sponsored cease-fire that began about a month ago. An Arab League envoy, meanwhile, traveled to Beirut from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Damascus</ENAMEX> to help arrange a meeting of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Lebanon</ENAMEX>'s lawmakers to choose a new head of state.
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Pakistan</ENAMEX>'s opposition introduced a noconfidence motion in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Islamabad</ENAMEX>'s Parliament. Prime Minister <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bhutto</ENAMEX> predicted that the move to oust her would be defeated. The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX>, meanwhile, has told the opposition parties that any change in government must be accomplished without compromising the country's fledgling democracy.
A Chinese government spokesman said martial law, entering its sixth month in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Beijing</ENAMEX>, will be lifted soon. The spokesman, quoted in the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">People's Daily</ENAMEX> newspaper, didn't offer a timetable. Premier <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Li Peng</ENAMEX> declared martial law May 20 amid studentled pro-democracy protests.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">National Football</ENAMEX> League owners elected lawyer <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Paul Tagliabue</ENAMEX> as commissioner, succeeding <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Pete Rozelle</ENAMEX>, who announced his retirement in March after 30 years in the post. The 48-year-old <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Tagliabue</ENAMEX>, an <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NFL</ENAMEX> counsel, is to serve a five-year term.
