<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX> share prices closed sharply lower Friday in active trading after Chancellor of the Exchequer <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Nigel Lawson</ENAMEX>'s resignation slapped the market and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Wall Street</ENAMEX>'s rapid initial sell-off knocked it down.
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX> shares were depressed initially by overnight losses in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> and by the drop in sterling after Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lawson</ENAMEX>'s resignation. It showed some early resilience after central bank support firmed sterling, but the weight of Wall Street late in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX> trading, and signs of further weakness in the British pound, proved a hefty load to bear. <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> stocks recovered some of their losses after the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX> market closed.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Financial Times</ENAMEX> 100-share index shed 47.3 points to close at 2082.1, down 4.5% from the previous Friday and 6.8% from Oct. 13, when <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Wall Street</ENAMEX>'s plunge helped spark the current weakness in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX>.
Dealers said the turnover, largely confined to the 100-share index stocks, partly reflected the flurry of activity typical at the close of a two-week trading account and the start of a new account. But they said Friday's focus on the top-tier stocks telegraphed active overseas selling and showed the broad-based fears over the status of the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.K.</ENAMEX> economy and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX>'s currency in the wake of the upheaval in Prime Minister <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Margaret Thatcher</ENAMEX>'s cabinet.
A senior dealer with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warburg Securities</ENAMEX> noted <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Gas</ENAMEX>, the most active blue-chip stock at 20 million shares traded, was affected by the political implications of Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lawson</ENAMEX>'s departure and Mrs. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Thatcher</ENAMEX>'s cabinet shuffle.
He attributed the unusually high volume to broad-based selling on fears that the Thatcher government may be in turmoil and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Labor Party</ENAMEX> positioned to regain control of the government and renew efforts at nationalization.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Gas</ENAMEX> shed 8.5 pence a share to close at 185 pence ($2.90).
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Petroleum</ENAMEX> fell 5 to 286 on 14 million shares traded. Dealers said the multinational oil company was pressured by recent brokerage recommendations urging investors to switch into <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Shell Trading & Transport.</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Shell</ENAMEX> eased 1 to 416 on turnover of 4.8 million shares.
Among the other actively traded blue-chip issues, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Imperial Chemical Industries</ENAMEX> dropped 11 to # 10.86, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hanson</ENAMEX> skidded 9.5 to 200.5, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Telecom</ENAMEX> fell 10 to 250.
An official at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Wako Securities</ENAMEX> said brokerages' excessive expectations about recent advances in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tokyu Group</ENAMEX> shares and real estate issues were dashed Friday.
Dealers placed heavy buy orders in the morning to start the first trading day for November transactions. But they failed to sell these stocks to client investors, who were cautious about the sharp gains these issues made this week, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Wako</ENAMEX> official said.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Fund</ENAMEX> managers said Friday's profittaking was a natural result of the week's ``abnormal fever'' in buying real estate, shipbuilding, steel and construction shares.
Frankfurt prices closed lower again Friday, the fourth decline in the past five days and the culmination of a week that saw the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">DAX</ENAMEX> index lose 4%. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">DAX</ENAMEX> dropped 19.69 points Friday to 1462.93.
Traders said the continued turbulence in other markets, coupled with the drop in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX> following the <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lawson</ENAMEX> resignation, were responsible.
Traders said the market remains extremely nervous because of the wild swings seen on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> last week. That's leaving small investors with cold feet, they said, and prompting institutions to take a reserved stance on the sidelines as well, at least until the market in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> settles down somewhat.
Share prices also closed lower in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Sydney</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hong Kong</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Singapore</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Taipei</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Manila</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Wellington</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Seoul</ENAMEX>. Concern about declines in other markets, especially <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>, caused selling pressure.
Source: <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Morgan Stanley Capital Intl</ENAMEX>.
