<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Morgan Grenfell Group PLC</ENAMEX> said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John Craven</ENAMEX>, group chief executive officer, is taking over the chairmanship of the merchant banking group from Sir <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peter Carey</ENAMEX>, who is retiring.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Craven</ENAMEX> said his move to the chairmanship means he will take a less active role in the day-to-day management of the group, but he added that the merchant bank's strategic focus remains unchanged.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Craven</ENAMEX> joined <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Morgan Grenfell</ENAMEX> as group chief executive in May 1987, a few months after the resignations of former Chief Executive <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Christopher Reeves</ENAMEX> and other top officials because of the merchant bank's role in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Guinness PLC</ENAMEX>'s controversial takeover of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Distiller's Co.</ENAMEX> in 1986.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Morgan Grenfell</ENAMEX> said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Michael Dobson</ENAMEX>, currently group deputy chief executive, will assume the chief executive position.
The merchant bank also announced that finance director <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">David Eward</ENAMEX> is taking early retirement for personal reasons. His duties will be taken over by <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Anthony Richmond-Watson</ENAMEX>, who has been elected deputy chairman.
News of Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Eward</ENAMEX>'s retirement comes one day after <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Morgan</ENAMEX> said that <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Christopher Whittington</ENAMEX> resigned as chairman of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Morgan</ENAMEX>'s banking subsidiary to join a financial services firm.
