Some gifts are better left unopened.
In 1984, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Howard Conant</ENAMEX>, a director of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Valspar Corp.</ENAMEX>, donated to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Goodwill Industries Inc.</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chicago</ENAMEX> an eight-acre site on the city's west side, where <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Valspar</ENAMEX> had operated a paint factory. Goodwill planned to sell the property and pocket the proceeds, as it had in many similar cases.
Six months later, Goodwill says, it was stunned to learn from the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Illinois Environmental Protection Agency</ENAMEX> that Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Conant</ENAMEX>'s gift was contaminated and that the charity, as the current owner, could be held responsible for any cleanup costs. Only this June, after the state agency made a more complete survey of the site, did Goodwill realize the extent of the problem: The property contains more than 70 storage tanks holding hazardous oily solvents and lead, and the soil is contaminated by similar substances.
``It's a toxic time bomb,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">James D. Wadsworth</ENAMEX>, president of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chicago Goodwill</ENAMEX>, which is independent of sister Goodwills around the country. Cleaning up the site is expected to cost many millions of dollars. Paying even a portion of the cleanup costs could bankrupt the charity, which has annual revenue of $6 million, says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Russell B. Selman</ENAMEX>, Goodwill's lawyer. In a pending lawsuit, the charity has asked a federal district court in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chicago</ENAMEX> to rescind its donation agreement with <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Valspar</ENAMEX> and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Conant</ENAMEX>.
Goodwill's problem looms as a potential threat to any charity that accepts property gifts in the new age of tough environmental laws. Under federal and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Illinois</ENAMEX> law, present and past owners of a contaminated site are among those who can be held liable for all cleanup costs, regardless of who caused the problem; regulators generally assign the costs.
Donating contaminated property allows companies to share the costs of their environmental problems, says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Laurence Molloy</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Molloy Corp.</ENAMEX>, an environmental management firm in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>. It also allows businesses to stop paying taxes and insurance on land they no longer use and to take a tax deduction on the property, tax lawyers say.
Nonprofit organizations might escape liability by showing that they didn't know a site was contaminated, but to succeed they must also show that they conducted an investigation before accepting the donation and that it didn't disclose the toxic-waste problem. Such an investigation can cost as much as $50,000.
Charities face a dilemma, because they can't reject gifts of property without significantly reducing their revenue. Since 1984, non-cash donations, which include real estate, have accounted for 20% of corporate giving, according to the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Conference Board</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> trade group that tracks corporate giving. In 1983, such donations represented only 11% of corporate giving.
Still, because of the hazards, many nonprofit organizations are tightening their rules on such gifts. Since June, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Salvation Army</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Eastern</ENAMEX> division has refused real-estate donations unless the donor first conducts an environmental assessment of the property. ``We tend to be very careful,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Carl Schoch</ENAMEX>, property secretary for the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Eastern</ENAMEX> division. ``We're aware an owner might want to get rid of'' a hazardous site.
At the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nature Conservancy</ENAMEX>, site inspections, which have been mandatory since the late'70s, ``are now specifically geared to looking for hazardous-waste problems,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Michael Dennis</ENAMEX>, general counsel for the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Rosalind</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Va.</ENAMEX>, group.
So far the organization hasn't incurred any major liabilities. Last year it went back to a donor eight years after accepting a gift when the conservancy learned of waste on the site. The donor agreed to share the cleanup costs. Now the group is considering hiring environmental specialists and engineers to work for it and investigate properties.``All you need is one hazardous property, and you could have a multimillion-dollar liability on your hands,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dennis</ENAMEX> says.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Universities</ENAMEX> also are proceeding with caution. In 1987 the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">University of Minnesota</ENAMEX> spent $100,000 cleaning up toxic waste at a property donated by a local power utility. The site had been contaminated by a company that leased the property and is now bankrupt. Now all property transfers involving the university are scrutinized for potential hazards -- at a base cost of about $20,000 for preliminary research and soil samples -- and scuttled if environmental problems can't be resolved.
Many nonprofit groups spurn some donations out of fear of potential problems. The Council on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Environment</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York City</ENAMEX>, a governmental agency, refused a gift of a site to be used for a children's playground when the council learned an auto repair shop had been located there. Little money was available for tests on the site, but ``common sense said there could be problems,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lys Mclaughlin</ENAMEX>, the agency's executive director.
Since receiving the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Valspar</ENAMEX> gift, the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chicago</ENAMEX> Goodwill has virtually closed the door on property donations, says its president, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Wadsworth</ENAMEX>. But that's no help in its current toxic-waste mess. In its suit, Goodwill claims that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Valspar</ENAMEX>, a paint and varnish maker based in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Minneapolis</ENAMEX>, and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Conant</ENAMEX> haven't met terms of the donation agreement or environmental regulations about property transfers.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Conant</ENAMEX>, however, isn't about to take back his gift. His lawyer, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Michael Quinn</ENAMEX>, says he doesn't want the land back because its value has declined since it was donated due to vandalism or poor maintenance. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Valspar</ENAMEX>, which had leased the property from Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Conant</ENAMEX>, says it has complied with all requests from the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Illinois</ENAMEX> EPA about the site. ``We have empathy for the unfortunate situation Goodwill is in, but that doesn't mean a legal obligation attaches to it,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Leo G. Stern</ENAMEX>, a lawyer for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Valspar</ENAMEX>. Both <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Valspar</ENAMEX> and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Conant</ENAMEX> argue that Goodwill doesn't have standing to bring its suit.
As the litigation progresses toward the pretrial fact-finding stage, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Goodwill's</ENAMEX> bills continue to mount. It has already spent more than $50,000 on security guards and fences at the site. The charity also owes $400,000 in back taxes on the property; its tax-exempt status applies only if property is being used for charitable purposes.
The state of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Illinois</ENAMEX> has sued Goodwill for a share of the cleanup costs at a second site, a former paint factory in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chicago</ENAMEX>. That property was donated to Goodwill by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Artra Group Inc.</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Northbrook</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ill.</ENAMEX>, company with interests in fashion jewelry and accessories. Goodwill later sold the site, before, it says, there was any indication of contamination.
Some charity officials now say <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Congress</ENAMEX> should exempt nonprofit organizations that receive land donations from any cleanup liability. That seems unlikely, though, because ``everyone wants an exemption,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">David Van Slyke</ENAMEX>, a lawyer with the enforcement and compliance division of the federal <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">EPA</ENAMEX>. ``But the agency is trying to be equitable. We're not trying to jam people when they are an innocent party.'' For now, Goodwill's  Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Wadsworth</ENAMEX> lectures other charities about accepting land donations. ``It's supposed to be a gift,'' he says. ``But it can turn out to be a liability.
