<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Xerox Corp.</ENAMEX>'s third-quarter net income grew 6.2% on 7.3% higher revenue, earning mixed reviews from Wall Street analysts.
Quarter net for the business-machines and financial-services company rose to $155 million, or $1.41 a share, from $146 million, or $1.37 a share, in the year-earlier period. Revenue rose to $4.45 billion from $4.15 billion.
In <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> composite trading, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Xerox</ENAMEX> closed at $62.75 a share, up $1.
Sales growth and profit in business products and systems -- <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Xerox</ENAMEX>'s main business -- were ``disappointing,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">B. Alex Henderson</ENAMEX>, who follows the company for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Prudential-Bache Securities Inc.</ENAMEX>
Sales of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Xerox</ENAMEX> copiers and other office products grew 1.6%; ``we expected growth of 6% to 7%,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Henderson</ENAMEX> said. Operating-profit margins slipped almost 18%, to 4.3% of sales, the analyst noted.
Still, with competitors such as <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Eastman Kodak Co.</ENAMEX> faltering in copier sales, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Xerox</ENAMEX>'s sales increases ``were encouraging,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Eugene Glazer</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dean Witter Reynolds Inc.</ENAMEX> ``They are holding their own in a weak market, and the restructuring is working,'' he says.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">David T. Kearns</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Xerox</ENAMEX> chairman and chief executive officer, cited the restructuring and ``strong'' cost controls for the 13% growth in profit from business products and systems operations.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Glazer</ENAMEX> expects Xerox to experience tough sledding, though, in financial services because of rate pressures and uncertainty surrounding tax treatment of capital gains.
In the quarter, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Crum & Forster</ENAMEX> insurance unit reported $200 million before tax of capital gains from property and casualty operations. The subsidiary also increased reserves by $140 million, however, and set aside an additional $25 million for claims connected with Hurricane Hugo.
