<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">W.R. Grace & Co.</ENAMEX> said it formed a new horticultural-products company by combining its soil-nutrients and fertilizers business with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sierra Chemical Co.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Milpitas</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Calif.</ENAMEX>
The business is expected to have sales of about $100 million in 1990, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Grace</ENAMEX> said. The new company's product lines will be aimed at nurseries, greenhouses and the lawn and garden industry.
