<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Liberty National Bancorp</ENAMEX> said its acquisition of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Florence Deposit Bank</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Florence</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ky.</ENAMEX>, first announced in April, has been completed in a transaction valued at $13.1 million.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Liberty National</ENAMEX> exchanged about 78.64 shares of its common stock for each of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Florence Deposit</ENAMEX>'s 5,600 shares outstanding.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Liberty National</ENAMEX>, a bank holding company, has assets exceeding $3 billion.
