A <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">REVISED</ENAMEX> BID FOR <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> is being prepared by a labor-management group, sources said. The new proposal, which would transfer majority ownership of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Air</ENAMEX>'s parent to employees and leave some stock in public hands, would be valued at $225 to $240 a share, or as much as $5.42 billion. But <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX>'s board isn't expected to give quick approval to any offer substantially below the $300-a-share bid that collapsed recently.
Takeover stock speculators have incurred paper losses of over $700 million from the failed <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> offer, their worst loss ever on a single deal.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Saab</ENAMEX> ended talks about a possible alliance after <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> concluded that the cost to modernize <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Saab</ENAMEX>'s car operations would outweigh the likely return. The collapse Friday prompted speculation that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford</ENAMEX> would intensify its pursuit of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX>, which is negotiating a defensive alliance with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX>.
Stock prices edged up in quiet trading Friday. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> industrials rose 5.94, to 2689.14, making the gain for the week a record 119.88 points, or 4.7%. Most bond prices fell, but junk bonds and the dollar rose.
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York City</ENAMEX> bonds were sold off by many investors last week amid political and economic uncertainty.
More banks are being hurt by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Arizona</ENAMEX>'s worsening real-estate slump. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Interstate Bancorp</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Los Angeles</ENAMEX> said Friday it expects a $16 million quarterly loss, citing property-loan losses at its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Arizona</ENAMEX> unit.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">OPEC</ENAMEX>'s ability to produce more oil than it can sell is starting to cast a shadow over world oil markets. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">OPEC</ENAMEX> officials worry that prices could collapse a few months from now if the group doesn't adopt new quotas.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Saatchi & Saatchi</ENAMEX> has attracted offers for some of its advertising units but has rejected them, sources said. The proposals, from suitors including <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Interpublic Group</ENAMEX>, come as the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX>-based ad giant struggles through its most difficult period ever.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Kodak</ENAMEX> entered the high-definition television market by unveiling a device that can convert conventional film into high-definition video.
A handful of small U.S. firms are refusing to cede the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">HDTV</ENAMEX>-screen market to Japanese manufacturers.
Freight rates are bottoming out and starting to rebound. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Trucking</ENAMEX>, shipping and air-freight firms are all planning rate increases, reflecting higher costs and tightened demand.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Texaco</ENAMEX> has purchased an oil-producing company in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Texas</ENAMEX> for $476.5 million. It is <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Texaco</ENAMEX>'s first major acquisition since the legal battle with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pennzoil</ENAMEX> began over four years ago.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Winnebago</ENAMEX> posted a widened quarterly loss and slashed its dividend in half, reflecting the deepening slowdown in recreational vehicle sales.
Markets --
Dollar: 142.43 yen, up 0.73; 1.8578 marks, up 0.0108.
