<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New Hampshire Yankee Co.</ENAMEX>, operator of the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Seabrook</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.H.</ENAMEX>, nuclear power facility, said the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nuclear Regulatory Commission</ENAMEX> fined it $50,000 in connection with improper procedures in shutting down the plant during low-power testing last June.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Edward A. Brown</ENAMEX>, president of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New Hampshire</ENAMEX> Yankee, said it accepts the decision and will pay the fine. He noted that the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NRC</ENAMEX> called the event an ``aberration'' and never questioned the safety of the plant.
In June, the plant's No. 2 executive, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">George Thomas</ENAMEX>, was fired because of improper control-room procedures at the plant before the shutdown.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New Hampshire</ENAMEX> Yankee is 35.6%-owned by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Public Service Co.</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New Hampshire</ENAMEX>.
