<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Equitec Financial Group</ENAMEX> said it will ask as many as 100,000 investors in 12 of its public real-estate limited partnerships to give approval to rolling them up into a new master limited partnership.
Under the proposal by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Equitec</ENAMEX>, a financially troubled real-estate syndicator, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hallwood Group Inc.</ENAMEX> would replace <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Equitec</ENAMEX> as the newly formed master limited partnership's general partner and manager. Shares of the new partnership would trade on an exchange like a stock.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hallwood</ENAMEX> is a merchant bank whose activities include the ownership, management and financial restructuring of shopping centers, office buildings, apartments and other real estate.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Equitec</ENAMEX> posted a $3.3 million net loss in the second quarter on $11.8 million of revenue, compared with a net loss of $12.9 million in the year-earlier period on revenue of $9.1 million.
In <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> composite trading, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Equitec</ENAMEX> closed at $2.625 a share, unchanged.
