Two rival bidders for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Connaught Biosciences</ENAMEX> extended their offers to acquire the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Toronto</ENAMEX>-based vaccine manufacturer Friday.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Institut Merieux S.A.</ENAMEX>, which offered 942 million Canadian dollars (US$801.2 million), or C$37 a share for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Connaught</ENAMEX>, said it would extend its bid, due to expire last Thursday, to Nov. 6.
A C$30-a-share bid by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ciba-Geigy Ltd.</ENAMEX>, a pharmaceutical company based in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Basel</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Switzerland</ENAMEX>, and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">California</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chiron Corp.</ENAMEX>, a bioresearch concern, was extended to Nov. 16. It had been due to expire Friday evening.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merieux</ENAMEX> previously said it would ensure its bid remained open pending a final decision by Canadian regulators on whether to approve the takeover. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merieux</ENAMEX>, a vaccine and bioresearch firm based in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Lyon</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">France</ENAMEX>, is controlled 50.1% by state-owned <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rhone Poulenc S.A.</ENAMEX>
The Canadian government previously said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Merieux</ENAMEX>'s bid didn't offer enough ``net benefit'' to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Canada</ENAMEX> to be approved, and gave Merieux an until mid-November to submit additional information.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merieux</ENAMEX> officials said last week that they are ``highly confident'' the offer will be approved once it submits details of its proposed investments to federal regulators.
Both offers are conditional on regulatory approvals and enough shares being tendered to give the bidders a majority of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Connaught</ENAMEX>'s shares outstanding.
Separately, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ontario Supreme Court</ENAMEX> said it will postpone indefinitely a ruling on the lawsuit launched by the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">University of Toronto</ENAMEX> against <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Connaught</ENAMEX> in connection with the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merieux</ENAMEX> bid.
Lawyers for the two sides weren't immediately available for comment.
