<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cilcorp Inc.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Peoria</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ill.</ENAMEX>, said it agreed to acquire the environmental consulting and analytical service businesses of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hunter Environmental Services Inc.</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Southport</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Conn.</ENAMEX>
The utility holding company said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hunter</ENAMEX> will receive 390,000 shares of a new series of Cilcorp convertible preferred stock with a face value of $39 million for the businesses. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cilcorp</ENAMEX> will also assume $22 million of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hunter</ENAMEX>'s existing debt. As part of the agreement, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cilcorp</ENAMEX> said it will pay Hunter $4 million in exchange for agreements not to compete.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cilcorp</ENAMEX> said the businesses to be acquired had revenue of $76 million for the year ended March 31.
Separately, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cilcorp</ENAMEX> said it plans to purchase as many as 1.4 million shares, or 10% of its common stock outstanding from time to time on the open market and through privately negotiated transactions.
