Japanese investors, reassured by Monday's strong rally on Wall Street, erased most of that day's losses on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tokyo Stock Exchange</ENAMEX>. But analysts said the rebound didn't remove the cautious mood from the market.
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tokyo</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nikkei</ENAMEX> Index of 225 stocks jumped 527.39 points to close at 34996.08. The rise came a day after the year's biggest drop on Monday, when the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nikkei</ENAMEX> fell 647.33, or 1.8%, in response to Friday's 6.9% plunge on <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Wall Street</ENAMEX>.
``We're back to square one,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Simon Smithson</ENAMEX>, an analyst in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX> for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Kleinwort Benson International Inc.</ENAMEX>
The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tokyo</ENAMEX> rally seemed to confirm the view, frequently expressed in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX> in the past few days, that the drop in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> was a local problem related to merger and acquisition activity in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX>
``This time we don't really have to worry about <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tokyo</ENAMEX>,'' said an official at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Daiwa Securities Co.</ENAMEX> ``Nothing has changed fundamentally in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tokyo</ENAMEX> market.''
``People are placing small bets. There's no huge buying,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stephen Hill</ENAMEX>, head of equity sales at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jardine Fleming Securities Ltd.</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tokyo</ENAMEX>. ``Really brave views right now would be foolhardy.''
Yesterday's buyers favored real estate, construction and other large-capitalization issues, reflecting the fact that many <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tokyo</ENAMEX> investors now feel safer with domestically oriented stocks, analysts said.
They also are concerned about the persistent strength of the dollar against the yen, as a weaker yen leads to higher import prices in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX> and adds to domestic inflationary pressures.
Currency concerns also weigh heavily on interest rate-sensitive stocks such as banking and other financial issues because of fears that Japanese interest rates might have to rise to keep the dollar in check.
Among steel shares, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NKK</ENAMEX> rose 19 to 705 yen ($4.97) a share, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nippon Steel</ENAMEX> gained 17 to 735. Construction shares that gained included <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Shimizu</ENAMEX>, which rose 130 to 2,080. In the real estate sector, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mitsui Real Estate Development</ENAMEX> was up 100 at 2,760, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mitsubishi Estate</ENAMEX> gained 80 to 2,360.
Prices opened strongly on the basis of Monday's Wall Street rally and yesterday's gains in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tokyo</ENAMEX>. But the advance faltered as index-options traders and investors jittery about the U.K. economic outlook took over. The unexpectedly wide U.S. August trade deficit of $10.77 billion hit an already jittery <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.K.</ENAMEX> market in midafternoon.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Michael Hicks</ENAMEX>, who manages sales and trading for brokerage concern <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Societe Generale Strauss Turnbull</ENAMEX>, said: ``It's a nervous market. It was all over the place. If you bought, you wish you hadn't, and if you sold, you wish you hadn't.'' He said the current market ``is all about sentiment, and the sentiment in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX> is 90% anxiety and worry.'' <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX>'s economic fundamentals, he said, ``don't look very bright.''
Dealers said <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX> showed signs of calming in midafternoon after Wall Street avoided sharp losses despite the trade report, but a wave of futures-related selling later in the session sent buyers back to the sidelines. Still, some sectors found buying interest after being actively sold in recent weeks.
On the corporate front, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ford Motor</ENAMEX> announced that it raised its stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.K.</ENAMEX> luxury car maker <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> to 10.4% from 5%. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jaguar</ENAMEX> shares jumped 23 before easing to close at 654, up 6.
Brewery stocks were firm to higher on talk of early bargain-hunting, but most ended below their peaks. Bass ended up 3 higher at 966, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Guinness</ENAMEX> closed at 589, down 7, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Scottish & Newcastle</ENAMEX> dropped 11 to 359, but Whitbread Class A shares rose 17 to 363. Dealers said there was late talk of a Whitbread sale of brewing operations to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Scottish & Newcastle</ENAMEX>.
In other European markets, share prices closed sharply higher in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Frankfurt</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Zurich</ENAMEX> and posted moderate rises in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Stockholm</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Amsterdam</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Milan</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paris</ENAMEX> closed lower, and most <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Brussels</ENAMEX> shares were unable to trade for a second consecutive day because of technical problems. South African gold stocks closed higher.
Elsewhere, share prices rebounded in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hong Kong</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Sydney</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Singapore</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Wellington</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Taipei</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Manila</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Seoul</ENAMEX>. In <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hong Kong</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Sydney</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Singapore</ENAMEX> -- the largest of those exchanges -- stocks recovered one-third to one-half of the ground they lost in Monday's plunge, with major market indexes posting gains of 3.6% to 4.4%.
