At first <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> didn't open because of an order imbalance. When it did a half-hour into the session, it was priced at $150 a share, down more than $28 from Monday's close. It sank further to as low as $145, but a big rally developed in the last half hour, pushing the stock back up to close at $170, down just $8.375 from Monday. In the process, 4.9 million shares traded, making <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> the second most active issue on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX>.
``It was chaotic. But we like to call it'controlled chaos,''' said 47-year-old <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Robert J. Jacobson Jr.</ENAMEX>, grandson of the firm's founder. He manned the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> post yesterday with <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Christopher Bates</ENAMEX>, 33, an energetic Long Islander who's a dead ringer for actor <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Nicolas Cage</ENAMEX>.
Both Jacobson traders, who had been hoping <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> trading would get back to normal, read the news about the unraveling of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> takeover plans on the train into work yesterday morning. The news told them it would be a while longer before <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> resumed trading like a regular airline stock after months of gyrations. When Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jacobson</ENAMEX> walked into the office at 7:30 a.m. <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">EDT</ENAMEX>, he announced: ``OK, buckle up.''
Messrs. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jacobson</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bates</ENAMEX> walked on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX> floor at about 8:45 a.m. yesterday and immediately spotted trouble. Already entered in the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX>'s computers and transmitted to their post were sell orders for 65,000 <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> shares.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> news had already caused a selling furor in the so-called third market, in which firms buy and sell stock away from the exchange floor. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX>, which closed on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX> Monday at $178.375 a share, traded in the third market afterward as low as $158 a share. There were rumors of $148-a-share trades.
In the 45 minutes before the 9:30 opening bell, the Jacobson specialists kept getting sell orders, heavier than they imagined. And at 9:15, they posted a $135 to $155 ``first indication,'' or the price range in which the stock would probably open. That range was quickly narrowed to $145 to $155, although traders surrounding the post were told that $148 to $150 would be the likely target.
When <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> finally opened a half hour late, some 400,000 shares traded at $150. There was ``selling pressure from everyone,'' said one trader.
This month's Friday-the-13th market plunge spurred by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> news wasn't as bad for the Jacobson specialists as yesterday's action. On that earlier day, the stock's trading was halted at a critical time so the specialists could catch their breath. Not yesterday.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jacobson</ENAMEX>, his gray hair flying, didn't wear out his red-white-and-blue sneakers, but he sweat so much he considered sending out for a new shirt.
The heavy buying in the last half hour led the specialists to take special steps.
About 11,000 shares sold at $170 on the bell, representing about eight to 10 late orders, the specialists estimate.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX> traders praised the Jacobson specialists for getting through yesterday without a trading halt. In <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chicago</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> spokesman, ``by way of policy,'' declined to comment on the company's stock or the specialists' performance.
Leaving the exchange at about 5 p.m., the Jacobson specialists made no predictions about how trading might go today. Said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Earl Ellis</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jacobson</ENAMEX> partner who got involved in the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> action, ``It all starts all over again'' today.
