They want late-night shuttles to the biology labs. They want a 24-hour library. And like college radicals everywhere, they are talking about a demonstration -- where protesters would gather quietly near the science building and raise their hands, classroom style.
``We could have called ourselves the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Academic Intellectual Society</ENAMEX>, but then everyone would have said, `Oh, you mean the nerd-and-geek club,''' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Leonid Fridman</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">SONG</ENAMEX>'s graduate-student adviser, told 19 attendees at the club's inaugural meeting earlier this month. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Membership</ENAMEX> has since swelled to between 20 and 25.
Some people may think of nerds as calculator-toting, socially awkward individuals with shirt-pocket liners for their pencils and a preoccupation with computers and matters numerical. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Geeks</ENAMEX>, by at least one definition, are chicken-mutilating circus freaks.
The club plans to show nerdy movies, such as ``<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Real Genius</ENAMEX>,'' in which physics whizzes pop corn with lasers; and naturally, the ``<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Revenge</ENAMEX> of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nerds</ENAMEX>,'' a tale of college males with runny noses and ill-fitting pants. One of its ``more ambitious goals'' is to get <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jaime Escalante</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Los Angeles</ENAMEX> high-school mathematics teacher featured in the film ``Stand and Deliver,'' to come to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Harvard</ENAMEX> for a guest lecture.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nerds</ENAMEX> and geeks sometimes find themselves a bit isolated at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Harvard</ENAMEX>. So Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kahn</ENAMEX> says high priority is being given to creating a computerized matchmaking service ``where instead of being matched for eye color, you could be matched for similar intellectual interests.'' For instance? ``I'm a math major, but I want to know about psychobiology. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hopefully</ENAMEX>, I'd find someone in psychobiology who wanted to know more about mathematics.''
