<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pacific First Financial Corp.</ENAMEX> said it signed a non-binding letter of intent to acquire the construction lending unit of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Old Stone Bank</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">California</ENAMEX>.
Terms haven't been finalized, but the transaction is expected to close by year end, Pacific First said.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Old Stone</ENAMEX>'s construction lending portfolio includes about $250 million in real-estate loans outstanding. The unit has 30 employees in four <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">California</ENAMEX> offices, the company said.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pacific First owns Pacific First Federal Savings Banks</ENAMEX> and other financial services firms.
