But why should an iffy $6.79 billion leveraged buy-out deal shake the foundations of the entire stock market?
Opinions vary about how important the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> deal was to the market's health, but analysts generally agree that the market gyrations created as the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> plan crumbled revealed a fundamental change in investor psychology.
The reaction to the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> debacle ``is mindless,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John Connolly</ENAMEX>, chief market strategist at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dean Witter.</ENAMEX> ``<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> is a small deal as far as the overall market is concerned. The only way you can make it a big deal is to draw linkages that just don't make sense.'' He suggests, for example, that investors may have assumed that just because <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> couldn't get financing, no leveraged buy-outs can get financing. Carried even further, some investors assumed that since leveraged buy-outs are the only thing propping up stock prices, the market would collapse if no more Lbos could be done.
``There will still be deals,'' argues Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Connolly</ENAMEX>. ``There may not be as many and the buyers may not get away with some of the things they've done in the past, but deals won't disappear.'' He forecasts that the emphasis in mergers and acquisitions may soon return to what he calls ``strategic deals, in which somebody is taking over a company not to milk the cash flow, but because it's a good fit.''
And even without deals, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Connolly</ENAMEX> figures the market would remain healthy. He notes, for instance, that there hasn't been a merger or acquisition among the 30 stocks in the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> Industrial Average since 1986, yet that average only three weeks ago hit a record high.
``Those stocks are up because their earnings are up and their dividends are up,'' he says.
Even the volatility created by stock index arbitrage and other computer-driven trading strategies isn't entirely bad, in Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Connolly</ENAMEX>'s view. For the long-term investor who picks stocks carefully, the price volatility can provide welcome buying opportunities as short-term players scramble frantically to sell stocks in a matter of minutes. ``Who can make the better decision, the guy who has 10 seconds to decide what to do or the guy with all the time in the world?'' he says. ``What on earth does the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> deal have to do with the price of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Walmart</ENAMEX>, which I was able to buy on Oct. 16 at a very attractive price?''
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Kidder Peabody</ENAMEX>'s Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jarrett</ENAMEX> also sees some benefits to the stock market's recent drop. ``We've run into a market that was beginning to run out of steam and get frothy,'' he says. ``The balloon had been blown up so big that when somebody came along with a pin -- in this case the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> deal -- we got a little pop.''
The pop sobered up investors who had been getting a little too ebullient, says Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jarrett</ENAMEX>. ``It provided an excuse for people to get back to reality and to look at the economic data, especially the third-quarter economic numbers, and to realize that we can't continue to gloss over what is going on in the junk bond market.''
But that's not the only problem for stocks. The other two props -- earnings and the economic outlook -- are troubling, too. ``<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">M&A</ENAMEX> is getting all the headlines right now, but these other things have been building up more gradually,'' she says. Third-quarter earnings have been generally disappointing and with economic data showing a clear slowing, the outlook for earnings in the fourth quarter and all of 1990 is getting worse.
``There are a lot more downward than upward revisions and it looks like people are questioning corporate profits as a means of support for stock prices,'' she says.
With all this, can stock prices hold their own? ``The question is unanswerable at this point,'' she says. ``It depends on what happens. If the economy slips into a recession, then this isn't a level that's going to hold.''
Stock prices tumbled for a third consecutive day as earnings disappointments, a sluggish economy and a fragile junk bond market continued to weigh on investors.
Oil stocks escaped the brunt of Friday's selling and several were able to post gains, including <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chevron</ENAMEX>, which rose 5/8 to 66 3/8 in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX> composite trading of 2.4 million shares. The stock's advance reflected ongoing speculation that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pennzoil</ENAMEX> is accumulating a stake in the company, according to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> Professional Investor Report.
Both companies declined to comment on the rumors, but several industry analysts told the Professional Investor Report they believed it was plausible that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pennzoil</ENAMEX> may be buying Chevron shares as a prelude to pushing for a restructuring of the company.
The precious metals sector outgained other <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> industry groups by a wide margin for the second consecutive session. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hecla Mining</ENAMEX> rose 5/8 to 14; <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Battle Mountain Gold</ENAMEX> climbed 3/4 to 16 3/4; <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Homestake Mining</ENAMEX> rose 1 1/8 to 16 7/8; <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lac Minerals</ENAMEX> added 5/8 to 11; <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Placer Dome</ENAMEX> went up 7/8 to 16 3/4, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ASA Ltd.</ENAMEX> jumped 3 5/8 to 49 5/8.
Gold mining stocks traded on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> also showed strength. Echo Bay Mines rose 5/8 to 15 7/8; Pegasus Gold advanced 1 1/2 to 12, and Corona Class A gained 1/2 to 7 1/2.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Unisys</ENAMEX> dropped 3/4 to 16 1/4 after posting a third-quarter loss of $4.25 a share, including restructuring charges, but other important technology issues were mixed.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Compaq Computer</ENAMEX>, which had lost 8 5/8 Thursday following a disappointing quarterly report, gained 5/8 to 100 5/8. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">International Business Machines</ENAMEX> dropped 7/8 to 99 7/8. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Digital Equipment</ENAMEX> tacked on 1 1/8 to 89 1/8, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hewlett-Packard</ENAMEX> fell 3/8 to 49 3/8.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Erbamont</ENAMEX> advanced 1 1/8 to 36 1/2 on 1.9 million shares. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Montedison</ENAMEX>, which owns about 72% of the company's common stock, agreed to buy the rest for $37 a share. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Himont</ENAMEX>, another majority-owned unit of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Montedison</ENAMEX>, added 1 1/4 to 47 1/8.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Milton Roy</ENAMEX> jumped 2 to 18 3/8. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Crane</ENAMEX> said it holds an 8.9% stake in the company and may seek control. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Crane</ENAMEX> dropped 1 1/8 to 21 1/8.
