<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bay Financial Corp.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Boston</ENAMEX>, which has been reporting big losses and warning of a possible bankruptcy-law filing, said it was sued by a holder.
The real estate investment trust said the ``purported class action suit,'' seeks ``damages and other remedies under federal securities law and state law.'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gerald E. Wilson</ENAMEX>, corporate secretary and legal counsel, said the company wouldn't disclose further details. He declined to name the shareholder, the plaintiff's lawyer or the court where the lawsuit was filed.
In <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> composite trading, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bay</ENAMEX> closed at $2.625, down 25 cents.
