<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing Co.</ENAMEX>'s third-quarter profit leaped 68%, but Wall Street's attention was focused on the picket line, not the bottom line.
In fact, the earnings report unfolded as representatives of the world's No. 1 jet maker and the striking Machinists union came back to the negotiating table for their first meeting in two weeks. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Doug Hammond</ENAMEX>, the federal mediator in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Seattle</ENAMEX>, where <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> is based, said the parties will continue to sit down daily until a new settlement proposal emerges or the talks break off again.
Despite the progress, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> indicated that the work stoppage, now in its 27th day, will have ``a serious adverse impact'' on the current quarter.
Because it's impossible to gauge how long the walkout by 55,000 Machinists rank and file will last, the precise impact on <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX>'s sales, earnings, cash flow and short-term investment position couldn't be determined.
The investment community, however, strongly believes that the strike will be settled before there is any lasting effect on either <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> or its work force. The company's total firm backlog of unfilled orders at Sept. 30 stood at a mighty $69.1 billion, compared with $53.6 billion at the end of
Although the company could see fourth-quarter revenue shrink by nearly $5 billion if it isn't able to deliver any more planes this year, those dollars actually would just be deferred until 1990. And the company is certain to get out some aircraft with just supervisors and other non-striking employees on hand.
``It's not a pretty picture,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">David Smith</ENAMEX>, an analyst with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Raymond James & Associates</ENAMEX>. ``But it would just mean a great first and second quarter next year.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Phillip Brannon</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merrill Lynch</ENAMEX> Capital Markets added: ``You don't want to minimize this and say nobody is looking at it. But the strike hasn't gone on long enough for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> to lose business in any real sense.''
That's the primary reason the company's share price has held up so well when, in Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Smith</ENAMEX>'s words, ``most companies would have unraveled'' by now. In <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> composite trading, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> closed yesterday at $54.50 a share, off a scant 12.5 cents.
Still, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> went through its normal verbal gymnastics and played up the downside. In a statement, Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Frank Shrontz</ENAMEX> asserted that the company ``faces significant challenges and risks,'' on both its commercial and government contracts.
And, of course, there's the unsteady labor situation. Besides the Machinists pact, accords representing 30,000 of the company's engineering and technical employees in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Puget Sound</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Wichita</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Kan.</ENAMEX>, areas expire in early December. Also, a contract with the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Auto Workers</ENAMEX> at the company's helicopter plant in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Philadelphia</ENAMEX> expired Oct. 15. This contract, covering about 3,000 hourly production and maintenance workers, is being extended on a day-to-day basis.
The Machinists rejected a proposal featuring a 10% base wage increase over the life of the three-year contract, plus bonuses of 8% the first year and 3% the second. On top of that, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> would make cost-of-living adjustments projected to be 5% for each year of the contract.
The union, though, has called the offer ``insulting.'' The company reiterated yesterday that it's willing to reconfigure the package, but not add to the substance of it.
