<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">SYDNEY</ENAMEX>-<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qintex Australia Ltd.</ENAMEX>, under pressure from bank lenders, has called in accounting firm Peat <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Marwick</ENAMEX> Hungerfords to help oversee asset sales and restructure the resorts and media company.
The appointment of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Peat Marwick</ENAMEX>, which has a unit that specializes in advising troubled companies, came about as a result of a round of meetings held by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qintex Australia</ENAMEX> Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Christopher Skase</ENAMEX> with bank creditors.
Yesterday, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Skase</ENAMEX> said the company is ``solvent and with the continued support of its bankers is able to meet its financial commitments.''
Qintex <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Australia</ENAMEX> is a unit of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qintex Ltd.</ENAMEX> The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qintex group</ENAMEX>'s problems began in earnest in March, when Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Skase</ENAMEX> agreed to buy <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MGM/UA Communications Co.</ENAMEX> But the transaction faltered in September, when <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qintex Australia</ENAMEX> was forced to increase its offer to US$1.5 billion following a counterbid from <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rupert Murdoch</ENAMEX>; the deal fell apart altogether earlier this month.
