<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Anheuser</ENAMEX>, the world's largest brewer and U.S. market leader, has historically been reluctant to engage in price-cutting as a means of boosting sales volume. With the passing of the heady days of swelling industry sales, however, the once-sporadic and brief forays into discounting are becoming standard competitive weapons in the beer industry.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">St. Louis company</ENAMEX> said major rivals, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Philip Morris Co.</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Miller Brewing</ENAMEX> unit and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Adolph Coors Co.</ENAMEX> ``have been following a policy of continuous and deep discounting for at least the past 18 months'' on their premium brands, pricing their product as much as 25 cents a 12-pack below <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Anheuser</ENAMEX>'s Budweiser label in many markets. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Anheuser</ENAMEX> said it's discounting policy basically would involve matching such moves by rivals on a market-by-market basis.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Anheuser-Busch</ENAMEX> announced its plan at the same time it reported third-quarter net income rose a lower-than-anticipated 5.2% to $238.3 million, or 83 cents a share, from $226.5 million, or 78 cents. Third-period sales were $2.49 billion, up from last year's $2.34 billion.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Anheuser</ENAMEX> said its new strategy -- started in some markets last month and expected to be applied soon in selected markets nationwide -- will mean lower-than-anticipated earnings for the last half of 1989 and for 1990. The projection sent <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Anheuser</ENAMEX> shares plunging $4.375 in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> composite trading yesterday. The stock closed at $38.50 on heavy volume of about 3.5 million shares. Shares of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coors</ENAMEX>, the company's sole publicly traded major competitor, fell $1.50 apiece to $19.125 in national over-the-counter trading, apparently on investor concerns over potential fallout from the coming pricing struggle.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Anheuser</ENAMEX> noted that ``beer industry sales volume is 1989 is following the trend that has characterized the last half of the'80s, with sales volume being essentially flat'' while consolidation creates fewer, bigger players.
``We can not permit a further slowing in our volume trend,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Anheuser</ENAMEX> said, adding it will take ``appropriate competitive pricing actions to support our long-term market share growth strategy'' for the premium brands. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Anheuser</ENAMEX> said it continues to hold to its earlier-announced goal of a 50% U.S. market share by the mid-1990s.
Beneath the tepid news-release jargon lies a powerful threat from the brewing giant, which last year accounted for about 41% of all U.S. beer sales and is expected to see that grow to 42.5% in the current year. ``<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Anheuser</ENAMEX> is the biggest guy in the bar, and he just decided to join in the barroom brawl,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Joseph J. Doyle</ENAMEX>, an analyst with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Smith Barney</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Harris Upham & Co.</ENAMEX> ``It's going to get bloody.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jerry Steinman</ENAMEX>, publisher of Beer Marketers Insights, a trade newsletter, said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Anheuser</ENAMEX>'s announcement means ``everybody else in the industry is going to have a difficult time reaching their profit objectives.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Prudential-Bache Securities Inc.</ENAMEX> analyst <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">George E. Thompson</ENAMEX> downplayed the importance of the announcement, and called any comparison between the coming beer-industry tiff and the seemingly unending ``cola wars,'' unwarranted. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Thompson</ENAMEX> calls discounting ``a loser's game for anyone without a dominant market share,'' and projected that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Anheuser</ENAMEX>'s statement of intent could simply be a means of warning competitors to ease up on price-cutting or face a costly and fruitless battle.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Thompson</ENAMEX> noted that the disappointing earnings, which fell five cents a share short of his own projections, contributed to the sell-off by an edgy and currently unforgiving investing public.
But <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Smith Barney</ENAMEX>'s Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Doyle</ENAMEX>, who yesterday trimmed his 1990 Anheuser earnings projection to $2.95 a share from $3.10, called the market's reaction ``justified.'' While the third-quarter earnings were a ``moderate disappointment,'' he said, ``the real bad news is the intensity of price competition'' in the premium-beer sector.
According to Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steinman</ENAMEX>, the newsletter publisher, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Anheuser</ENAMEX>'s market share is nearly twice that of its nearest competitor, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Miller Brewing</ENAMEX>, which had a 21.2% stake last year. It's followed by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Stroh Brewery Co.</ENAMEX>, which has agreed to sell its assets to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coors</ENAMEX>. Both <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coors</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Stroh</ENAMEX> have recently been ceding market share to <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Miller</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Anheuser</ENAMEX>.
