The ground ruptured along a 20-to-30-mile stretch of the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">San Andreas</ENAMEX> Fault on Tuesday, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Johnson</ENAMEX> added. In 1906, the rupture was 300 miles long and a couple feet wide.
``Landfill -- loose and unconsolidated earth -- may feel like rock but it behaves like liquid when you shake it,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Douglas Segar</ENAMEX>, professor of geosciences at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">San Francisco State University</ENAMEX> in a televised interview. ``It liquefies in a patchwork quilt pattern. Our quake behaved much like the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mexico City</ENAMEX> earthquake, where great damage was miles from the epicenter.''
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Johnson</ENAMEX>, of the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Berkeley</ENAMEX> seismographic station, said: ``Landfill can be done if it's properly compacted. You can drive piles on it and build on it.'' He cited the example of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">San Francisco</ENAMEX>'s financial district, where many new glass towers survived almost unscathed.
But the public policy issues raised by earthquake damage will be difficult to address, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Johnson</ENAMEX> predicted.
One old building, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Golden State Bank</ENAMEX> Building on <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Front Street</ENAMEX>, had its yellow brick facade sheared off by the shock of the quake, leaving a wedge of its third floor open to the air, while piles of dusty bricks tumbled to the street below narrowly missing rush-hour pedestrians and cars. Reinforcing such old building stock, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Johnson</ENAMEX> said, ``comes down to money. It's a danger. We know it's there. And sooner or later, we have to do something about it.''
``The big one is still due,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Johnson</ENAMEX> predicted in an interview. ``The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Bay Area</ENAMEX> has three very dangerous faults, the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">San Andreas</ENAMEX>, the Hayward fault and the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Calaveras</ENAMEX> fault. It {Tuesday's quake} hasn't solved our problem. In <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">California</ENAMEX>, this is the reality.
