<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Procter & Gamble Co.</ENAMEX>, helped by a gain from a lawsuit settlement and continued growth overseas, posted a 38% rise in fiscal first-quarter net income.
Excluding the gain, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">P&G</ENAMEX>'s earnings were close to analysts' predictions of about $1.40 a share for the quarter. Wall Street had expected a modest rise in the company's domestic sales and earnings, and more substantial increases in overseas results. One factor helping sales and earnings was a 3% price rise for most <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">P&G</ENAMEX> products, except coffee, analysts said.
Unit volume, or amount of products shipped, rose about 11% in the international segment, with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">P&G</ENAMEX> continuing to win market share in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX>'s diaper and detergent markets. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jay Freedman</ENAMEX>, analyst with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Kidder, Peabody & Co.</ENAMEX>, said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">P&G</ENAMEX>'s Always sanitary napkin, sold under the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Whisper</ENAMEX> name in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX>, has firmly established itself as a leading brand. He figures <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">P&G</ENAMEX> will expand its personal-care product line in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX> to ``continue that momentum.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">P&G</ENAMEX>'s U.S. shipments were up just 1%, partly because the company decided to shift more promotions and sales for health and beauty products to the fiscal second quarter. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hugh Zurkuhlen</ENAMEX>, analyst with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Salomon Bros.</ENAMEX>, predicts the shift will mean <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">P&G</ENAMEX>'s sales growth in the second quarter will be ``in the double digits.''
For fiscal 1990, analysts expect <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">P&G</ENAMEX>'s sales to continue to grow, with earnings climbing between 15% and 20%. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lynne Hyman</ENAMEX>, vice president of equity research for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Boston Corp.</ENAMEX>, expects <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">P&G</ENAMEX> to post net of about $4.20 a share, on a post-split basis. ``But I'm recognizing there's a good chance they'll do a bit better than that,'' she says. In fiscal 1989, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">P&G</ENAMEX> earned $3.56 a share, adjusted for the stock split.
One big factor affecting the fiscal second half will be the new stewardship of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Edwin L. Artzt</ENAMEX>, who becomes chairman and chief executive officer in January. Because of his remarkable success turning around <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">P*/NNP&G</ENAMEX>'s international operations, analysts have high hopes for his tenure. ``If he does to the domestic operations what he did internationally,'' says Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Zurkuhlen</ENAMEX>, ``this company will earn $6 or $7 a share in a few years.
