Pinnacle <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">West Capital Corp.</ENAMEX> said it suspended indefinitely its common stock dividend and reported a 91% plunge in third-quarter net income.
The announcement, made after the close of trading, caught analysts by surprise. The company closed at $12 a share, down 62.5 cents, in composite trading on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pinnacle West</ENAMEX> slashed its quarterly dividend to 40 cents per share from 70 cents in December, saying at the time that it believed the new, lower dividend was ``sustainable.''
A company spokesman said the decision to eliminate the dividend resulted from a quarterly appraisal and that circumstances had changed since the December announcement. He declined to elaborate.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Edward J. Tirello Jr.</ENAMEX>, an analyst at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Shearson Lehman Hutton Inc.</ENAMEX>, speculated that the sudden dividend elimination presages an expensive agreement with thrift regulators over the company's insolvent <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Merabank</ENAMEX> savings and loan unit.
Analysts have estimated that <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Pinnacle West</ENAMEX> may have to inject between $300 million and $400 million into the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merabank</ENAMEX> unit before turning the thrift over to federal regulators.
The latest financial results at the troubled utility and thrift holding company, based in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Phoenix</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ariz.</ENAMEX>, reflect continuing problems at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merabank</ENAMEX> and losses in real-estate, venture-capital and uranium-mining operations.
Utility operations, the only company unit operating in the black in the latest period, had a 26% drop in profit, to $86.3 million, largely as a result of outages at the company's huge Palo <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Verde</ENAMEX> nuclear facility and the cost of purchased replacement power.
In other operations, losses at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merabank</ENAMEX> totaled $85.7 million in the latest quarter, compared with a $2.5 million profit a year earlier. The latest quarter includes a $42.7 million addition to loan-loss reserves. As recently as August, the company said it didn't foresee a need for substantial additions to reserves.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pinnacle's Suncor Development Co.</ENAMEX> real-estate unit's loss narrowed to $13.8 million from $78.4 million. The latest period included a $9 million write-down on undeveloped land, while the year-earlier  period included a $46 million reserve for real-estate losses.
Losses at its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Malapai Resources Co.</ENAMEX> uranium-mining unit narrowed to $3.4 million from $18 million a year ago, which included a $9 million write-down of utility inventories.
Losses at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">El Dorado Investment Co.</ENAMEX>, the venture-capital operation, widened to $6.8 million from $425,000 a year earlier. The latest quarter included a $6.6 million write-down of investments.
