A <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> bankruptcy judge has temporarily stopped the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Resolution Trust Corp.</ENAMEX> from placing an insolvent thrift institution under government control.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Deltacorp</ENAMEX>, the holding company that owns the thrift, contends that the federal law empowering the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">RTC</ENAMEX> to place failing savings and loan associations under government control conflicts with the federal bankruptcy law, Chapter
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Deltacorp</ENAMEX> has a bankruptcy petition pending in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>. The company is scheduled to appear before federal bankruptcy Judge <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Tina L. Brozman</ENAMEX> Thursday to ask her to impose a 60-day preliminary injunction on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Office of Thrift Supervision</ENAMEX>, the enforcement arm of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">RTC</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Deltacorp</ENAMEX> hopes within 60 days it will be able to sell the thrift, says its lawyer <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">David M. Friedman</ENAMEX>, a partner with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Gordon Hurwitz Butowsky Weitzen Shalov & Wein</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>.
Passed early this year, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Financial Institutions Reform</ENAMEX>, Recovery, and Enforcement Act authorizes the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">RTC</ENAMEX> to declare troubled thrift institutions insolvent and place them in receivership. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">RTC</ENAMEX> can then close the thrift institution and sell it whole or in parts. Established three months ago, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">RTC</ENAMEX> has taken over 256 thrifts valued at $95.6 billion.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">RTC</ENAMEX> was on the verge of placing <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Colonial Savings Bank</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Roselle</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.J.</ENAMEX>, a subsidiary of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Deltacorp</ENAMEX>, into receivership. This week <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Deltacorp</ENAMEX> persuaded Judge <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Brozman</ENAMEX> to issue a temporary restraining order, arguing that before its thrift was taken over the apparent conflict between the two federal laws should be resolved.
According to Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Friedman</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">RTC</ENAMEX>'s pending takeover would impair the company's ability under Chapter 11 to recoup loses by putting its subsidiary up for bid. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Friedman</ENAMEX> claims <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Deltacorp</ENAMEX> estimates that by selling the thrift it could make about $23 million. If the government sells the thrift, the company will make far less, he contends.
``If the court were to issue the injunction, it would set a significant precedent,'' says Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Friedman</ENAMEX>, who says he doesn't know how many other companies are in a position to use the bankruptcy law as a shelter against <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">RTC</ENAMEX> takeovers.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jerome Kowalski</ENAMEX>, a partner with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Parker Chapin Flattau & Klimpl</ENAMEX> who has clients in situations similar to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Deltacorp</ENAMEX>, says lawyers would be ``foolish not to tell clients to follow'' the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Deltacorp</ENAMEX> strategy.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Office of Thrift Supervision</ENAMEX> failed to return numerous phone calls.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">REAGAN</ENAMEX> TOOK more than 10 months on average to nominate federal judges.
That's the conclusion of a study by <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Daniel Meador</ENAMEX>, a law professor at the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">University of Virginia</ENAMEX>. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Meador</ENAMEX>, a former assistant attorney general, criticizes what he calls ``inordinate delays'' in filling federal judgeships and suggests the creation of a permanent office on judicial nominations within the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Justice Department</ENAMEX>.
Federal judges in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Washington</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">D.C.</ENAMEX>, and other areas complained recently that long-standing vacancies have contributed to mounting backlogs of cases. Forty-five federal judgeships are vacant nationwide.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Meador</ENAMEX>, whose study appears in the fall issue of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">University of Virginia's Journal of Law & Politics</ENAMEX>, writes that ``it is not rare for two or more years to pass before the administration sends a nomination to the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Senate</ENAMEX>.'' His study covers the years 1979 to 1988.
Under Attorney General <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dick Thornburgh</ENAMEX>, a committee of ten senior <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Justice Department</ENAMEX> officials evaluate potential judicial nominees and send recommendations to the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">White House</ENAMEX>. Congressional Democrats have accused Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Thornburgh</ENAMEX> of delaying the nomination process.
But a spokesman for the the attorney general said the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Senate Judiciary Committee</ENAMEX> contributed to the problem by failing to act on nominations made during the final months of the Reagan administration.
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> DISTRICT JUDGE upholds <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>'s ``Son of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Sam</ENAMEX>'' law.
The state law, designed to prevent lawbreakers from profitting from such things as books and movies about their crimes, survived its first federal challenge in a ruling by Judge <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John F. Keenan</ENAMEX> in federal court in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Simon & Schuster Inc.</ENAMEX> sued to have the law declared unconstitutional, claiming it restricts publishers' freedom of speech. The company filed the suit in 1986 after the ``Son of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Sam</ENAMEX>'' law was applied to ``Wiseguy: Life in a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mafia Family</ENAMEX>,'' a best-seller by <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Nicholas Pileggi</ENAMEX>. The book was based on the life of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Henry Hill</ENAMEX>, whom the court refers to as a ``career criminal'' and who received payments from the publisher in return for his life story.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Simon & Schuster</ENAMEX> said many books about criminal activities would never be published if criminals couldn't be paid for their stories, and that this had a chilling effect on the publishing industry.
But Judge <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Keenan</ENAMEX> said, ``Although it may be more difficult for publishers and authors to create books with the cooperation of a criminal source {under the ``Son of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Sam</ENAMEX>'' law}, it is not impossible nor is such cooperation proscribed.'' The judge added, ``The speech itself is not the target of {the state law}; the profit-making aspect is the target.''
A spokeswoman for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Simon & Schuster</ENAMEX> said the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> company would appeal the ruling.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">BAKER & Mckenzie Moscow</ENAMEX> bound.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chicago</ENAMEX> law firm, the world's largest, will open the first Soviet-accredited office of a foreign law firm in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Moscow</ENAMEX> later this year.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coudert Brothers</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> law firm, and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Arnold & Porter</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Heron</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Burchette</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ruckert & Rothwell</ENAMEX>, both in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Washington</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">D.C.</ENAMEX>, have had lawyers in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Soviet Union</ENAMEX> under the auspices of companies' trade offices or in unofficial capacities. But 1,400-lawyer <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Baker & Mckenzie</ENAMEX> will open a full-fledged branch.
The firm will have 46 offices in 27 countries. It became the first foreign firm with an <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Eastern European</ENAMEX> branch when it opened in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Budapest</ENAMEX> two years ago.
Three lawyers, headed by partner <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Paul J. Melling</ENAMEX>, will be in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Moscow</ENAMEX> full-time. Ten lawyers from the firm's other offices will work with them. Fifteen joint ventures have already signed on as clients, according to <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Robert W. Cox</ENAMEX>, chairman of the firm.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ILLINOIS JUDGE</ENAMEX> joins firm.
After nine years in the state judiciary, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">William R. Quinlan</ENAMEX>, 49 years old, has joined the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chicago</ENAMEX> law firm of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Phelan</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pope & John</ENAMEX> as a partner. He will specialize in complex commercial and environmental litigation at the 75-lawyer firm.
In a Oct. 23 resignation letter to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Illinois</ENAMEX> Gov. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">James R. Thompson</ENAMEX>, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Quinlan</ENAMEX> said he could no longer sit on the bench and fulfill financial responsibilities to his family. He said that while education costs and living expenses spiralled, judicial salaries in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Illinois</ENAMEX> haven't increased for four years. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Quinlan</ENAMEX> was appointed to the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Illinois Appellate Court</ENAMEX> in 1985. He served as a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Circuit Court</ENAMEX> judge in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Cook County</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ill.</ENAMEX>, and corporation counsel for the city of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chicago</ENAMEX>.
``The judiciary is called upon to decide the most important issues facing our society. But we're not spending the money to staff it with the best people we can get or keeping the best people there,'' says Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Quinlan</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">DISNEY SUES Amvest</ENAMEX> for copyright infringement.
Noting that the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Happy Hampster</ENAMEX> isn't one of its creations, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Walt Disney Co.</ENAMEX> filed a $17 million suit in federal court against <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Amvest Video Corp.</ENAMEX>, of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Rahway</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.J.</ENAMEX>
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Disney</ENAMEX> alleges <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Amvest</ENAMEX> violated its copyrights at least 170 times in at least 23 video cassettes, some of them full-length Disney movies such as <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bambi</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Fantasia</ENAMEX>. The suit also alleges Amvest created a character called the Happy Hampster which it is trying to pass off as a Disney character.
In addition to the $17 million in damages -- $100,000 for each copyright infringement -- <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Disney</ENAMEX> is seeking unspecified punitive damages.
A spokeswoman for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Amvest</ENAMEX> had no comment and said the company hadn't yet seen the suit.
