It was the second anniversary of the 1987 crash, but this time it was different. Stocks rallied on good earnings reports and on data that showed less inflation than expected.
The industrials were up about 60 points in the afternoon, but cautious investors took profits before the close.
Traders said a variety of factors triggered the rally. The consumer price index rose 0.2% in September, while many economists were looking for a 0.4% increase. Stock-index arbitrage buy programs -- in which traders buy stock against offsetting positions in futures to lock in price differences -- helped the rally's momentum.
The euphoria was such that investors responded to good earnings reports of companies such as <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Express</ENAMEX>, while ignoring the disappointing profits of companies such as <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Caterpillar</ENAMEX>, analysts said.
Stock-index arbitrage trading was a minor influence in yesterday's rally, traders said. Institutional buyers were the main force pushing blue chips higher.
One floor trader noted in astonishment that nobody seemed to mind the news that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Airways</ENAMEX> isn't making a special effort to revive the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> buy-out. The announcement of the buy-out's troubles triggered the market's nose dive a week ago.
Takeover enthusiasm may have been renewed when an investor group disclosed yesterday that it had obtained all the financing required to complete its $1.6 billion leveraged buy-out of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Medical International.</ENAMEX> ``That's put some oomph back into this market,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peter Vandenberg</ENAMEX>, a vice president of equity trading at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Shearson Lehman Hutton.</ENAMEX>
But some traders thought there was less to the rally than met the eye. ``There is no strength behind this rally,'' asserted <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Chung Lew</ENAMEX>, head trader at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Kleinwort Benson North America</ENAMEX>. ``It's traders squaring positions. It's not good; the market is setting up for another fall.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Medical</ENAMEX> jumped 1 7/8 to 23 5/8.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IMA Acquisition</ENAMEX>, an investor group that includes <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Boston</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pritzker</ENAMEX> family of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chicago</ENAMEX>, said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chemical Bank</ENAMEX> had made arrangements for 23 other banks to provide $509 million in bank financing for the buy-out offer. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chemical</ENAMEX> and six other banks, along with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Boston</ENAMEX>, are providing the rest of the $1.6 billion.
Elsewhere on the takeover front, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Time Warner</ENAMEX> advanced 2 5/8 to 136 5/8 and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner Communications</ENAMEX> tacked on 7/8 to 63 7/8. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Delaware Supreme Court</ENAMEX> affirmed a ruling that barred Chris-Craft Industries from voting its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> preferred stock as a separate class in deciding on the companies' proposed merger.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paramount Communications</ENAMEX> climbed 1 1/4 to 58 1/2 and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MCA</ENAMEX> rose 1 1/2 to 64; both media companies have long been mentioned as potential acquisition candidates. Among other actual and rumored targets, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Woolworth</ENAMEX> rose 1 1/4 to 60 1/2, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Upjohn</ENAMEX> went up 1 1/8 to 39 3/4, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Armstrong World Industries</ENAMEX> gained 1 to 40 1/8 and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Kollmorgen</ENAMEX> rose 3/4 to 13 7/8.
In addition:
-- <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Soo Line</ENAMEX> jumped 2 3/4 to 20 1/4, above the $19.50 a share that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Canadian Pacific</ENAMEX> offered for the company in a takeover proposal.
-- <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Xtra</ENAMEX> gained 1 1/8 to 27 1/8. Investor <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Robert M. Gintel</ENAMEX>, who owns a 4.7% stake in the company, said he plans a proxy fight for control of its board.
Buying interest also resurfaced in the technology sector, including <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">International Business Machines</ENAMEX>, whose board approved a $1 billion increase in its stock buy-back program. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IBM</ENAMEX> rose 2 3/8 to 104 1/8 as 2.2 million shares changed hands.
On the other hand, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Symbol Technologies</ENAMEX> dropped 1 1/4 to 18 1/2 after <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Shearson Lehman Hutton</ENAMEX> lowered its short-term investment rating on the stock and its 1989 earnings estimate, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Commodore International</ENAMEX> fell 7/8 to 8 after the company said it expects to post a loss for the September quarter.
Insurance stocks continued to climb on expectations that premium rates will rise in the aftermath of the earthquake in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">San Francisco</ENAMEX> area. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American International Group</ENAMEX> climbed 4 to 106 5/8, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">General Re</ENAMEX> rose 3 1/8 to 89 5/8, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kemper</ENAMEX> added 2 1/2 to 48, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AON</ENAMEX> went up 1 3/8 to 36 and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chubb</ENAMEX> rose 1 1/4 to 82 1/4.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Capital Cities</ENAMEX>-<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ABC</ENAMEX> surged 42 5/8 to 560. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Kidder Peabody</ENAMEX> raised its investment rating on the stock and its earnings estimates for 1989 and 1990, based on optimism that the company's ABC television network will continue to fare well in the ratings.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dun & Bradstreet</ENAMEX> lost 1 7/8 to 51 7/8 on 1.8 million shares. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merrill Lynch</ENAMEX> lowered its short-term rating on the stock and its estimate of 1990 earnings, citing a sales slowdown in the company's credit-rating business.
Pinnacle <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">West Capital</ENAMEX>, which suspended its common-stock dividend indefinitely and reported a 91% decline in third-quarter earnings, fell 5/8 to 11 3/8.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">B.A.T Industries</ENAMEX>, the most active <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Amex</ENAMEX> issue, rose 3/8 to 12 3/8. The company received shareholder approval for its restructuring plan, designed to fend off a hostile takeover bid from a group headed by financier Sir <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">James Goldsmith</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">TRC Cos.</ENAMEX>, the target of an investigation by the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> inspector general, dropped 2 to 10 3/4. The probe involves testing procedures used on certain government contracts by the company's <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Metatrace</ENAMEX> unit.
