<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Georgia-Pacific Corp.</ENAMEX> offered to acquire <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Great Northern Nekoosa Corp.</ENAMEX> for $58 a share, or about $3.18 billion.
Executives at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nekoosa</ENAMEX> couldn't be reached, and officials at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Georgia Pacific</ENAMEX> declined to comment. Analysts, however, were surprised because the tender offer appeared unsolicited. ``It's quite a bombshell,'' said one, adding that the offer could spark a period of industry consolidation.
The two companies would appear to be a logical fit because of their complementary lines, and analysts described the offer, representing a 36% premium over <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nekoosa</ENAMEX>'s market price, as fair. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nekoosa</ENAMEX> closed yesterday at $42.75, up $2.75, in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> composite trading.
But industry observers still questioned whether <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Georgia Pacific</ENAMEX> will ultimately prevail. ``You have to watch out for counterbids,'' said one analyst. ``<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">International Paper</ENAMEX> or <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Weyerhaeuser</ENAMEX> could step in.''
That collapse, following on the heels of disarray in the market for high-risk, high-yield bonds, cast doubt on the entire takeover business, which has fueled both big profits among <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Wall Street</ENAMEX> securities firms and big gains in the stock market generally.
While <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Georgia-Pacific</ENAMEX>'s stock has outperformed the market in the past two years, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nekoosa</ENAMEX> has lagged the market in the same period.
Yesterday's rise in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nekoosa</ENAMEX>'s share price came on volume of 786,700 shares, four times the daily average.
According to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> Professional Investor <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Report</ENAMEX>, options trading in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nekoosa</ENAMEX> was also heavy, ranking only behind <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">International Business Machines Corp.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> in volume on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chicago Board Options Exchange</ENAMEX>.
According to the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Value Line Investment Survey</ENAMEX>, demand for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nekoosa</ENAMEX>'s commodity paper has weakened, prompting earnings to decline by 6.6% in the third quarter ended Sept. 30. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Value Line</ENAMEX> added, ``With discounts widening on business papers, and with newsprint and corrugated shipments flat, we expect negative earnings comparisons through next year.''
The purchase of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nekoosa</ENAMEX> would easily eclipse <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Georgia-Pacific</ENAMEX>'s $530 million acquisition of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Brunswick Pulp & Paper Co.</ENAMEX> last year. That acquisition, which also included the assumption of $135 million in debt, was designed to allow <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Georgia-Pacific</ENAMEX> to capitalize on the strong demand for softwood pulp, as well as reduce its exposure to the housing market.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Wasserstein Perella & Co.</ENAMEX> is the dealer-manager for the offer, which will expire Nov. 29, unless extended.
