After coming close to a partial settlement a year ago, shareholders who filed civil suits against <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ivan F. Boesky</ENAMEX> and the partnerships he once controlled again are approaching an accord, people familiar with the case said.
Meanwhile, within the next few weeks, the limited partners in <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ivan F. Boesky & Co</ENAMEX>. L.P. are expected to reach a partial settlement with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Drexel Burnham Lambert Inc.</ENAMEX> regarding the distribution of the $330 million in partnership assets, said one of the individuals. Under the terms of the settlement, the limited partners would drop their civil suits against <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Drexel</ENAMEX>, now pending in federal court in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>, another individual said.
Attorneys involved in the talks said that the parties were closer to accord than they were a year ago, when reports of an imminent agreement circulated. One individual said the shareholders' accord was ``well worked out.''
However, less optimistic attorneys warned that because of the tangle of numerous defendants and plaintiffs with overlapping claims, there is always the possibility that the talks will again fall apart.
A shareholders' accord would provide the first restitution to thousands of individuals and institutions claiming losses as a result of insider trading by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boesky & Co.</ENAMEX>, once the largest arbitrage fund in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> The plaintiffs are investors who bought and sold securities in which Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Boesky</ENAMEX> and his partnerships were dealing. Some claim they suffered losses because they sold while he was buying and others because they bought while he was selling.
Stocks involved in the shareholder suits include <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Union Carbide</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">RJR Nabisco</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Natural Resources</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boise Cascade Corp.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">General Foods Corp.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Houston Natural Gas</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FMC Corp.</ENAMEX>
There are at least 27 class-action shareholder suits that have been consolidated in federal court in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> under <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> District Judge <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Milton Pollack</ENAMEX>. Among the defendants are Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Boesky</ENAMEX>; the now-defunct <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ivan F. Boesky & Co.</ENAMEX>; Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Boesky</ENAMEX>'s main underwriter, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Drexel Burnham; and Cambrian & General Securities PLC</ENAMEX>, a British investment fund once controlled by Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Boesky</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Charles Davidow</ENAMEX>, of the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Washington</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">D.C.</ENAMEX>-based law firm <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Wilmer</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cutler & Pickering</ENAMEX>, which represents Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Boesky</ENAMEX> in this matter, said only that ``discussions are under way. There are no agreements yet.''
It has been three years since Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Boesky</ENAMEX>, now in prison, agreed to pay a $100 million fine to settle the government's charges that he had traded illegally using insider information. Out of this, the government set up a $50 million fund for plaintiffs who can prove their financial losses. According to <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">William Orbe</ENAMEX>, an attorney at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Grais & Richards</ENAMEX>, the escrow agents for the fund, as of Sept. 30 the fund amounted to $60.5 million.
Separately, attorneys for the 42 or so limited partners have had serious discussions that could lead to the distribution of the partnership's assets. The limited partners include insurance companies, financial institutions and individual investors.
An agreement with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Drexel</ENAMEX> regarding the limited partners' investments is an essential step toward getting their money back. This is because a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Delaware</ENAMEX> court earlier this year said that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Drexel</ENAMEX> is entitled to get its money back before or at the same time as the limited partners. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Drexel</ENAMEX> is owed $20 million by the partnership.
An individual familiar with the negotiations said that whatever investments the limited partners do not recoup from the $330 million in partnership assets, they will receive from the $350 million restitution fund available as a result of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Drexel</ENAMEX>'s settlement with the government in December 1988.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Drexel</ENAMEX> agreed to plead guilty to six felony counts and pay $650 million, of which $350 million was set aside for shareholders and other plaintiffs, including the limited partners, who claim they were injured by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Drexel</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">JAILED AFRICAN-AMERICAN</ENAMEX> activist wins a battle against the
U.S. District Judge <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Robert P. Patterson Jr.</ENAMEX> ordered the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FBI</ENAMEX> to immediately begin processing Herman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Benjamin Ferguson</ENAMEX>'s request for documents stemming from the agency's investigation of him during the 1960s. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FBI</ENAMEX> had said it would not be able to begin processing the request until June
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ferguson</ENAMEX>, who is 68 years old, fled the U.S. in 1970 after exhausting his appeals of a 1968 conviction on conspiracy to murder. He turned himself in to authorities in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> earlier this year. He maintains that the information from the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FBI</ENAMEX> will help him get his 1968 conviction vacated and his bail-jumping indictment dismissed. His attorneys claim he was framed by the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FBI</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> police as part of a campaign to destroy the black liberation movement of the 1960s.
The judge said that if the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FBI</ENAMEX>'s proposed schedule was followed in releasing the documents, ``a delay of over one year will have occurred and plaintiff will have served approximately two-thirds of his 3 1\ minimum sentence by the time he receives the files.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gabriel W. Gorenstein</ENAMEX>, the assistant <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> attorney handling the case for the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FBI</ENAMEX>, said no decision has been made about appealing the judge's ruling.
FEDERAL COURTS URGED to cut costs and reduce delays of civil suits.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Washington</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">D.C.</ENAMEX>, think tank recommends that the courts adopt different ``tracks'' for different types of civil cases in order to separate the handling of highly complex suits from simpler ones. Complex cases, such as antitrust suits and many business disputes, would receive intense supervision by federal judges to keep pretrial proceedings moving. Standard cases would require less judicial attention, and fast-track cases could be resolved quickly.
Although some of the study's recommendations resemble those of similar projects, the makeup of the task force was unusually diverse, adding significance to the effort. It included lawyers from civil rights and consumer groups, plaintiffs' lawyers and defense attorneys, corporate counsel and law professors.
