<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Texaco Inc.</ENAMEX> has purchased an oil-producing company in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Texas</ENAMEX> for $476.5 million, its first major acquisition since its legal brawl with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pennzoil Co.</ENAMEX> began more than four years ago.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">White Plains</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.Y.</ENAMEX>, oil company said Friday that it had acquired <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tana Production Corp.</ENAMEX>, a subsidiary of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">TRT Energy Holdings Inc.</ENAMEX>, for $95.1 million in cash, with the rest to be paid in shares of a new, non-voting issue of preferred stock.
``This acquisition is another indication of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Texaco</ENAMEX>'s commitment to increase the company's reserve base,'' said Chief Executive Officer <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">James W. Kinnear</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Texaco</ENAMEX> has also been attempting to sell oil properties. At least two years ago, the company put 60 million barrels of oil reserves on the block. They were either too small or uneconomic to maintain, the company said. Not all of those parcels have yet been sold.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Texaco</ENAMEX> acquired Tana before it completed those sales because Tana's properties are high quality and near other fields <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Texaco</ENAMEX> already owns, a company spokeswoman said.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pennzoil</ENAMEX> had sued <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Texaco</ENAMEX> for improperly interfering with its acquisition of a portion of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Getty Oil Co.</ENAMEX> Eventually, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Texaco</ENAMEX>, which was forced into bankruptcy proceedings by that litigation, settled its fight with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pennzoil</ENAMEX> for $3 billion in 1986. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Icahn</ENAMEX>, who played a key role in the settlement and attempted subsequently to take control of the company, sold his stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Texaco</ENAMEX> just last summer.
