<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Security</ENAMEX> said it signed a letter of intent to purchase <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">La Jolla Bancorp</ENAMEX>, agreeing to pay $15 of its own stock for each share of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">La Jolla</ENAMEX>. Based on the current number of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">La Jolla</ENAMEX> shares, that gives the transaction a value of $104 million.
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">La Jolla</ENAMEX> is the parent company of La <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jolla Bank & Trust Co.</ENAMEX>, which has 12 branches in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">San Diego County</ENAMEX>. As of Sept. 30, the bank had assets of $511 million and deposits of $469 million, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Security Pacific</ENAMEX> said.
