<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Amdahl Corp.</ENAMEX>, a maker of mainframe computers, reported a sharp decline in net income for its third quarter, citing pricecutting by competitors and adverse effects from a strong U.S. dollar.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Amdahl</ENAMEX>'s results were somewhat worse than expected. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jay Stevens</ENAMEX>, an analyst with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dean Witter Reynolds</ENAMEX>, said he expected the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Sunnyvale</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Calif.</ENAMEX>, company to earn 35 cents a share for the quarter and said the firm's weaker profit was partly the result of increased competition from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">International Business Machines Corp.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Amdahl</ENAMEX>'s principal competitor for mainframe sales.
