<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Daiwa Securities Co.</ENAMEX> named Masahiro Dozen president.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dozen</ENAMEX> is taking over the reins of a securities company that does very well in its domestic market but that is still seeking to realize its potential in global investment banking and securities dealing.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Daiwa</ENAMEX> is one of the world's largest securities firms. As of March 31, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Daiwa group</ENAMEX> had shareholder equity of 801.21 billion yen ($5.64 billion). For the six months ended Sept. 30, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Daiwa</ENAMEX> reported unconsolidated (parent company) net income of 79.03 billion yen ($556.5 million) on revenue of 332.38 billion yen ($2.34 billion). Both figures were record highs.
Several observers interpreted Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dozen</ENAMEX>'s appointment as an attempt by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Daiwa</ENAMEX> to make its international operations more profitable while preparing the firm for the effects of the continuing deregulation of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX>'s domestic markets, which should mean increased competition.
American institutional investors have never had a large appetite for Japanese equities. And while the Japanese have stepped up their purchases of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> shares in the past several months, they have shown themselves in the past to be fickle investors.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dozen</ENAMEX> knows these problems firsthand. When he arrived in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> in 1969 -- the start of an eight-year tour -- he tried selling Japanese yen-denominated bonds to U.S. investors. ``He made desperate efforts, using the yellow pages from beginning to end,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Koji Yoneyama</ENAMEX>, president of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Daiwa</ENAMEX>'s U.S. unit. ``But not a single piece of paper was sold.''
By his own account, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dozen</ENAMEX> didn't do much better with U.S. bonds. In an interview a few months ago, he recalled how after some training at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Salomon Brothers Inc.</ENAMEX>, he successfully bid for the opportunity to sell portions of 20 U.S. corporate bond issues. But he couldn't sell any. ``Japanese stock salesmen selling American bonds? Maybe it's crazy,'' he said.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dozen</ENAMEX> even related the indignity suffered when he and two colleagues went on an overnight fishing expedition off the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New Jersey</ENAMEX> shore and caught nothing. Upon returning to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>, ``Exhausted, I got into a taxicab, and the woman driver said: `Americans make better fishermen,''' he recalled.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Undaunted</ENAMEX>, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dozen</ENAMEX> said that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Daiwa</ENAMEX>'s goal is to build ``a high-technology oriented international organization with maybe some Japanese flavor to it.''
He said that he was particularly interested in his firm gaining expertise in futures, options, mortgaged-backed securities, computerized trading and investment systems as well as mergers and acquisitions. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dozen</ENAMEX> said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Daiwa</ENAMEX>'s strengths were its large capital base, its influential position in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tokyo</ENAMEX> market and its links to Japanese corporations and institutional investors.
In his climb to the top, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dozen</ENAMEX> also headed the company's stock-exchange division, its fixed-income units and its international operations. ``He was constantly picking up new things to fill out his experience; he is very well-balanced,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Takuro Isoda</ENAMEX>, chairman of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Daiwa</ENAMEX>'s U.S. unit in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>.
If Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dozen</ENAMEX> has a weakness, it may be his golf game. ``He digs in the sand instead of hitting the ball, like a farmer,'' said Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Yoneyama</ENAMEX>.
