<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Exxon Corp.</ENAMEX> said its third-quarter earnings slipped 9% as profits from two of its three major businesses sagged. All cleanup costs from last spring's Alaskan oil spill were reflected in earlier results, it said.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Exxon</ENAMEX>
Although <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Exxon</ENAMEX> spent heavily during the latest quarter to clean up the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Alaskan</ENAMEX> shoreline blackened by its huge oil spill, those expenses as well as the cost of a continuing spill-related program are covered by $880 million in charges taken during the first half.
An <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Exxon</ENAMEX> official said that at this time the oil company doesn't anticipate any additional charges to future earnings relating to the cleanup of oil spilled when one of its tankers rammed into an underwater reef. She added, however, that charges already taken don't take into account the potential effect of litigation involving the oil spill. She said that impact can't be reasonably assessed yet.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Exxon</ENAMEX>'s net income during the third quarter dropped to $1.11 billion, or 87 cents a share, from $1.22 billion, or 93 cents a share, a year earlier. Revenue rose 8.1%, to $23.65 billion from $21.88 billion. During the third quarter, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Exxon</ENAMEX> purchased 8.34 million shares of its stock at a cost of $373 million. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Exxon</ENAMEX>'s profitability, like that of many other oil companies, was hurt during the third quarter by declining returns from the chemicals and refining and marketing businesses. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Exxon</ENAMEX>'s earnings from chemicals operations fell $90 million, to $254 million, while refining and marketing profits declined $180 million, to $357 million.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ashland</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ky.</ENAMEX>, oil company reported a $38 million charge resulting from settlement of a 10-year dispute with the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">National Iranian Oil Co.</ENAMEX> over claims that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ashland</ENAMEX> didn't pay for Iranian crude it had received. In September, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ashland</ENAMEX> settled the long-simmering dispute by agreeing to pay Iran $325 million.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ashland</ENAMEX> also took a $25 million after-tax charge to cover anticipated costs to correct problems with boilers built by one of its subsidiaries. The oil refiner also booked a $15 million charge for selling <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ashland Technology Corp.</ENAMEX>, one of its subsidiaries, at a loss.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Amerada Hess</ENAMEX>
Profits improved across <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hess</ENAMEX>'s businesses. Refining and marketing earnings climbed to $33.3 million from $12.9 million, and exploration and production earnings rose to $37.1 million from $17.9 million. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hess</ENAMEX>'s earnings were up despite a $30 million charge to cover the cost of maintaining operations after Hurricane Hugo heavily damaged the company's refinery at <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">St. Croix</ENAMEX>. It is widely known within industry circles that <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hess</ENAMEX> had to buy oil products in the high-priced spot markets to continue supplying its customers. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hess</ENAMEX> declined to comment.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Phillips Petroleum</ENAMEX>
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Phillips Petroleum</ENAMEX>'s third-quarter earnings slid 60%, to $87 million, or 36 cents a share, from $215 million, or 89 cents a share. Revenue rose 6.9%, to $3.1 billion from $2.9 billion. Shrinking profit margins in chemical and refining and marketing sectors accounted for most of the decline, said Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">C.J. Silas</ENAMEX> in a statement. Despite higher oil prices, exploration and production profits were off because of foreign-currency losses and some construction costs incurred in one of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Phillips</ENAMEX>' <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">North Sea</ENAMEX> oil fields. A year ago, results were buoyed by a $20 million after-tax gain from an asset sale.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Occidental</ENAMEX> said oil and gas earnings fell to $17 million from $20 million. The latest period includes net gains of $32 million in non-recurring credits from the sale of properties, indicating operating losses for the quarter in the oil and gas division. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chemical</ENAMEX> earnings fell 10%, reflecting softening of demand.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Atlantic Richfield</ENAMEX>
Citing its reduced ownership in the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lyondell Petrochemical Co.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Atlantic Richfield</ENAMEX> reported that net income slid 3.1% in the third quarter to $379 million, or $2.19 a share, from $391 million, or $2.17 a share, for the comparable period last year. Sales fell 20%, to $3.7 billion from $4.6 billion.
Arco's earnings from its 49.9% stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lyondell</ENAMEX> fell to $37 million from $156 million for the same period last year, when <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lyondell</ENAMEX> was wholly owned. Offsetting the lower stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lyondell</ENAMEX> were higher crude oil prices, increased natural gas volumes and higher coke prices, the company said. Coal earnings rose to $26 million from $21 million.
For the nine months, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Arco</ENAMEX> reported net income of $1.6 billion, or $8.87 a share, up 33% from $1.2 billion, or $6.56 a share a year earlier. Sales were $12 billion, off 13% from $13.8 billion.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jeff Rowe</ENAMEX> contributed to this article.
