<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ronald B. Koenig</ENAMEX>, 55 years old, was named a senior managing director of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Gruntal & Co.</ENAMEX> brokerage subsidiary of this insurance and financial-services firm. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Koenig</ENAMEX> will build the corporate-finance and investment-banking business of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Gruntal</ENAMEX>, which has primarily been a retail-based firm. He was chairman and co-chief executive officer of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ladenburg</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Thalmann & Co.</ENAMEX> until July, when he was named co-chairman of the investment-banking firm along with <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Howard L. Blum Jr.</ENAMEX>, who then became the sole chief executive. Yesterday, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Blum</ENAMEX>, 41, said he wasn't aware of plans at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ladenburg</ENAMEX> to name a co-chairman to succeed Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Koenig</ENAMEX> and said the board would need to approve any appointments or title changes. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Blum</ENAMEX> added he wasn't surprised Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Koenig</ENAMEX> resigned, but his departure was ``nothing that we desired or worked for.'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Koenig</ENAMEX> said: ``I just got a tremendous offer from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Gruntal</ENAMEX>.
