Many investors give <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Michael Foods</ENAMEX> about as much chance of getting it together as <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Humpty Dumpty</ENAMEX>. But now at least there's a glimmer of hope for the stock.
But at least Burger King has signed on, and says that by year end it won't be using any shell eggs. The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Miami</ENAMEX> fast-food chain, owned by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Grand Metropolitan</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX>, expects to consume roughly 34 million pounds of liquefied eggs annually.
So there is reason to believe that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Michael's</ENAMEX> hopes for a bacteria-free, long-shelf-life egg weren't all hype. (Easy Eggs are pasteurized in a heat-using process.) Still, caution is advisable. A company official says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Michael</ENAMEX>'s break-even volume on Easy Eggs is around 60 million pounds a year -- apparently well above current shipments and a far cry from what the company once suggested was a billion-pound market waiting for such a product. Perhaps to debunk the analysts' talk of over-capacity, Michael today will take some of the skeptics on a tour of its new <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Gaylord</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Minn.</ENAMEX>, plant.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Michael Foods</ENAMEX> has attracted a good many short-sellers, the people who sell borrowed shares in a bet that a stock price will drop and allow the return of cheaper shares to the lender. Many analysts question management's credibility.
``The stock, in my opinion, is going to go lower, not only because of disappointing earnings but {because} the credibility gap is certainly not closing,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">L. Craig Carver</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dain Bosworth.</ENAMEX>
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Carver</ENAMEX> says that at a recent <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dain</ENAMEX>-sponsored conference in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>, he asked <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Michael</ENAMEX>'s chief executive officer if the fourth quarter would be down. The CEO, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Richard G. Olson</ENAMEX>, replied ``yes,'' but wouldn't elaborate. (The company didn't put out a public announcement. A spokesman said later that Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Olson</ENAMEX> was being ``conservative'' in his estimate. But the spokesman added that while Michael will earn less than last year's $1.20 a share, it thinks Street estimates of $1 or so are low.)
Analyst <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Robin Young</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">John Kinnard & Co.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Minneapolis</ENAMEX>, calls himself ``the last remaining bull on the stock.'' He argues that <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Michael Foods</ENAMEX> is misunderstood: ``This is a growth company in the packaged food industry -- a rare breed, like finding a white rhino.'' Earnings aren't keeping pace, he says, because of heavy investments in the egg technologies and drought-related costs in its potato business.
Prospective competition is one problem. Last week a closely held <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New Jersey</ENAMEX> concern, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Papetti High-Grade Egg Products Co.</ENAMEX>, rolled out an aseptically packaged liquefied item called Table Ready. Company President <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steve Papetti</ENAMEX> says <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Marriott</ENAMEX> will be among his clients as well.
