Shareholders of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nuovo Banco Ambrosiano S.p. A.</ENAMEX> voted to accept a bid of 5,500 lire ($4.03) a share by <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">France</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Credit Agricole</ENAMEX> for 13.32% of the bank, rejecting an earlier, equal offer by <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Italy</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Assicurazioni Generali S.p. A.</ENAMEX>
The move will give <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Nuovo Banco</ENAMEX> a badly needed foreign presence, and make <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Credit Agricole the bank</ENAMEX>'s largest shareholder. It also opens a rift in the bank's shareholders' syndicate that could lead to a battle for control of the concern. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Nuovo Banco</ENAMEX> will become <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Italy</ENAMEX>'s biggest private-sector bank when it completes its scheduled merger with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Banca Cattolica del Venetoen</ENAMEX> by year end.
The linkup with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Credit Agricole</ENAMEX> will give Nuovo <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Banco</ENAMEX> its first foreign presence since it was formed from the wreck of the old <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Banco Ambrosiano</ENAMEX>, which collapsed amid scandal after the death of Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Roberto Calvi</ENAMEX> in 1982. Since then, the bank has strengthened its Italian network, and has posted strong results.
``The shareholders felt we needed a foreign presence more than we needed links with an insurance company,'' an <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ambrosiano</ENAMEX> spokeswoman said.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Gemina</ENAMEX> said in a statement that ``it reserves the right to take any action to protect its rights as a member of the syndicate.'' A company spokeswoman said the company hadn't decided what measures to take, but didn't rule out legal action.
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Generali</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Italy</ENAMEX>'s biggest insurer, last month offered 5,500 lire a share for the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nuovo Banco</ENAMEX> stake held by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Banco Popolare di Milano</ENAMEX>, the bank's largest shareholder, which announced plans to sell the holdings earlier this year.
A <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Generali</ENAMEX> spokesman declined to comment on Nuovo <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Banco</ENAMEX>'s rejection of the insurer's offer.
On the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Milan</ENAMEX> stock exchange, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Nuovo Banco</ENAMEX>'s shares jumped to 4,830 lire each from 4,695 lire Friday.
