<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">INSURERS</ENAMEX> ARE FACING billions of dollars in damage claims from the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">California</ENAMEX> quake. But most businesses in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Bay</ENAMEX> area, including <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Silicon Valley</ENAMEX>, weren't greatly affected. Computer and software companies in the region are expecting virtually no long-term disruption in shipments. Also, investors quickly singled out stocks of companies expected to profit or suffer from the disaster.
Leveraged buy-outs may be curbed by two rules in pending congressional legislation. The provisions, in deficit-reduction bills recently passed by the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">House</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Senate</ENAMEX>, could raise the price tags of such deals by up to 10% and cool the takeover boom.
A bill giving the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Transportation Department</ENAMEX> the power to block airline leveraged buy-outs cleared a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">House</ENAMEX> panel. But Secretary <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Skinner</ENAMEX> said he would urge <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bush</ENAMEX> to veto the bill.
Housing starts sank 5.2% in September to a seven-year low. The drop, following a 6.2% decline in August, indicates the industry is still being hurt by the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Fed</ENAMEX>'s anti-inflation battle.
Stock prices rose slightly as trading slowed, while bonds ended little changed despite a slumping dollar. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> industrials gained 4.92, to 2643.65. But investors remain wary about stocks, partly because of turmoil in the junk-bond market.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">WCRS Group</ENAMEX> announced a major restructuring that largely removes it from the advertising business. The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX>-based concern will sell most of its ad unit to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">France</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Eurocom</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sears</ENAMEX> is negotiating to refinance its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sears</ENAMEX> Tower for close to $850 million, sources said. The retailer was unable to find a buyer for the building.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Whitbread</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> put its spirits division up for sale, setting off a scramble among distillers. The business includes Beefeater gin.
Markets --
Dollar: 141.45 yen, off 1.30; 1.8485 marks, off 0.0182.
