<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony Corp.</ENAMEX> asked a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Los Angeles</ENAMEX> court to deny <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner Communications Inc.</ENAMEX>'s request for an injunction preventing <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hollywood</ENAMEX> producers <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peter Guber</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John Peters</ENAMEX> from taking over the management of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Columbia Pictures Entertainment Inc.</ENAMEX>
The Japanese concern made its request in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Los Angeles Superior Court</ENAMEX>, where <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> last week filed a $1 billion breach of contract suit against <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony</ENAMEX>. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guber</ENAMEX> and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peters</ENAMEX> are currently under contract to produce movies exclusively for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony</ENAMEX>, which has agreed to pay $3.5 billion and to assume $1.5 billion in debt to buy <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Columbia</ENAMEX>, is also offering $200 million for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Guber Peters Entertainment Co.</ENAMEX>, of which the producers are co-chairmen and own a combined 28% stake.
While executives from both sides say the matter still could be settled, papers filed in the court by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony</ENAMEX> appear to heighten the acrimony of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hollywood</ENAMEX>'s most-watched legal battle. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony</ENAMEX> claims an injunction would leave it ``faced with the ominous possibility that it would complete a $5 billion entertainment company acquisition and be left with no management to run the company.'' <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony</ENAMEX> adds that ``<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> must be grinning from ear to ear at the possibility of leaving <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony</ENAMEX> in such a position and at the opportunity to prevent the revitalization of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Columbia</ENAMEX> into a strong competitor.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony</ENAMEX> disputes <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX>'s contention that its offer to Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guber</ENAMEX> and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peters</ENAMEX> violates their contract with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX>, which is in the process of being acquired by <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Time Warner Inc.</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Furthermore</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony</ENAMEX> claims that the contract as written -- and oral agreements that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> has denied exist -- allow the producers to take on such executive posts. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony</ENAMEX>'s legal argument even raises the novel idea that Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guber</ENAMEX> and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peters</ENAMEX> could actually make movies for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> while serving in executive posts at another studio.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony</ENAMEX> acknowledges that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX>'s contract prevents the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Guber-Peters</ENAMEX> team from being producers or executive producers of movies for another studio. But, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony</ENAMEX> says, that doesn't exclude them from taking an executive post at another company where they would be involved in choosing movies and in managing, but not in day-to-day production of movies. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony</ENAMEX> says <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Columbia</ENAMEX> ``could allow <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Guber and Peters</ENAMEX> to produce motion pictures for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> as soon as the acquisition is consummated.''
But <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony</ENAMEX> also says in its filing that the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> contract ``doesn't require that <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guber</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peters</ENAMEX> take any affirmative steps to produce motion pictures; it simply rewards them when they do and prohibits them from producing for another entertainment company.'' And <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony</ENAMEX> says <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> has already shown it doesn't need the producers ``by taking action to prevent <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Guber and Peters</ENAMEX> from completing production in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> properties.''
Among the arguments <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony</ENAMEX> makes is that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> should let the producers go to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Columbia</ENAMEX> because it already allowed the producers to become co-chairmen of publicly held <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Barris Industries Inc.</ENAMEX>, which earlier this year changed its name to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Guber Peters Entertainment</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony</ENAMEX> also says in its filing that Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guber</ENAMEX> and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peters</ENAMEX> were offered management posts at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Columbia</ENAMEX> once before in 1987, and that ``<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> approved and encouraged them to do so.''
But in a sworn affidavit last week, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner Bros.</ENAMEX> Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Robert Daly</ENAMEX> denied that. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Daly</ENAMEX> said that Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guber</ENAMEX> had mentioned such an offer, and that he responded that ``I thought the idea was a bad one from his point of view, and I understand he dropped the idea shortly thereafter.''
The two sides did some rival-bashing yesterday as well. In a sworn declaration, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Walter Yetnikoff</ENAMEX>, president of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CBS Records</ENAMEX> unit, said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steven Ross</ENAMEX> has an ``anti-Japanese, anti-<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony</ENAMEX>'' bias. But <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stuart Rabinowitz</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX>'s outside counsel, says <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony</ENAMEX> ``violates American business morality by secretly raiding major producers under exclusive contract to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner.</ENAMEX>''
In another sworn declaration yesterday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony Corp.</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">America</ENAMEX> Vice Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Michael Schulof</ENAMEX> said that while he was negotiating with Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guber</ENAMEX> and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peters</ENAMEX>, he relied on the producers' assurances that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> had previously agreed to let them terminate the contract and wouldn't have any trouble obtaining a release.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guber</ENAMEX>, meanwhile, in his own sworn declaration yesterday, maintained that running a studio has always been ``our professed goal,'' and that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> executives made an oral agreement that would free the producers from their contract should the opportunity arise. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peters</ENAMEX>, in his declaration, supported Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guber</ENAMEX>'s claims and said he is ``shocked'' by the assertions of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> executives that such an agreement was never made.
