<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Times Co.</ENAMEX>'s third-quarter earnings report is reinforcing analysts' belief that newspaper publishers will be facing continued poor earnings comparisons through 1990.
Analysts said the company's troubles mirror those of the industry. Retail advertising, which often represents half of the advertising volume at most daily newspapers, largely isn't rebounding in the second half from extended doldrums as expected. At the same time, newspapers are bedeviled by lagging national advertising, especially in its financial component. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones & Co.</ENAMEX> recently reported net fell 9.9%, a reflection, in part, of continued softness in financial advertising at The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Wall Street Journal</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Barron's magazine</ENAMEX>.
``We expect next year to be a fairly soft year in newspaper-industry advertising,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John Morton</ENAMEX>, an analyst for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lynch, Jones & Ryan</ENAMEX>. ``Next year, earnings will hold steady, but we just don't see a big turnaround in the trend in advertising.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John S. Reidy</ENAMEX>, an analyst for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Drexel Burnham Lambert Inc.</ENAMEX>, said, ``The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Times</ENAMEX> faces the same problem of other publishers: linage is down. It will be hard to do handstands until real linage starts heading back up.''
``With the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Edison</ENAMEX> plant coming on line next summer, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Times</ENAMEX> is facing some tough earnings comparison in the future,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peter Appert</ENAMEX>, an analyst with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">C.J. Lawrence</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Morgan Grenfell.</ENAMEX> ``But many newspapers are facing similar comparisons.''
The sale of the company's cable franchise brought an after-tax gain of $193.3 million, part of which will be used to reduce debt. The company also has a stock-repurchase plan.
Analysts said they were impressed by the performance of the company's newspaper group, which consists of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Times</ENAMEX>, 35 regional newspapers and a one-third interest in the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">International Herald Tribune</ENAMEX>; group operating profit for the quarter increased slightly to $34.9 million from $34.5 million on flat revenue.
