A group bidding for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Medical International Inc.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>, said it formally received the final financing needed for a $3 billion bid for about 86% of the hospital operator's stock.
In <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> composite trading yesterday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Medical</ENAMEX> closed at $23.625, up $1.875.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Medical</ENAMEX> has agreed to the offer, but earlier this month said it had received new ``expressions of interest'' from two previous bidders. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Medical</ENAMEX> said it would pursue the inquiries from the companies, but wouldn't identify them unless they make firm offers.
