<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Medical International Inc.</ENAMEX> said it hasn't received any other offers to acquire the owner and operator of hospitals, and took another step toward completion of its $3 billion acquisition by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IMA Holdings Corp.</ENAMEX>
Earlier this month <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IMA</ENAMEX>, an investment group that includes <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chicago</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Pritzker</ENAMEX> family and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Boston Corp.</ENAMEX>, submitted a reduced bid for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Medical</ENAMEX> after it couldn't finance its initial offer. Under the new offer, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IMA</ENAMEX> will pay $26.50 a share for 63 million shares, or about 86% of the shares outstanding. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IMA</ENAMEX> also will assume $1.4 billion in debt.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Medical</ENAMEX> said its directors have approved what is, in effect, a draft of a solvency opinion on the acquisition, submitted by the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Los Angeles</ENAMEX>-based investment banking and evaluation consulting firm of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Houlian Lokey Howard & Zukin Inc.</ENAMEX> A final opinion must be approved prior to the acceptance of tendered shares for payment under the offer, which was due to expire at 12:01 a.m. <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">EDT</ENAMEX> today.
Separately, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Moody's Investors Service Inc.</ENAMEX> downgraded the ratings of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Medical</ENAMEX>'s senior and subordinated debt issues and those of its international affiliate. The downgrade anticipates completion of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IMA Holdings</ENAMEX> acquisition today, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Moody's</ENAMEX> said.
The ratings concern said the acquisition should result in pretax losses from operations because of increases in interest expense and charges for depreciation and amortization, but that it expects the losses to be reduced through productivity gains and above average growth of the company's hospitals. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Moody's</ENAMEX> said the ratings anticipate a successful debt-reduction program and modest improvement in discretionary cash flow because of planned asset sales.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Moody</ENAMEX>'s changes affected the following issues: <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Medical International</ENAMEX>: Senior notes, sinking-fund debentures, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Euromarket</ENAMEX> notes, Eurobonds, Swiss franc bonds, unsecured loan stock to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ba3</ENAMEX> from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Baa2</ENAMEX>; convertible subordinated debentures, notes, and sinking-fund debentures to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">B2</ENAMEX> from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Baa3</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Medical International N.V.</ENAMEX>: <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Guaranteed Euroissues</ENAMEX> to Ba3 from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Baa2</ENAMEX>.
An <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Medical</ENAMEX> spokeswoman said the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Moody</ENAMEX>'s downgrading was expected because of the nature of the takeover.
