<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bankers Trust New York Corp.</ENAMEX>, as expected, reported a third-quarter loss of $1.42 billion, or $17.39 a share, following its $1.6 billion boost in reserves for losses on loans to less-developed countries.
The loss compares with net income of $162.1 million, or $2.01 a share, in the year-earlier period. Interest income rose 29% to about $1.35 billion from $1.05 billion. The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> bank holding company's assets at Sept. 30 climbed to $59.4 billion from $57.9 billion.
Excluding the increase in loan-loss reserves, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bankers Trust</ENAMEX> said third-quarter net income would have increased 11% to $180 million. A number of major banks have posted big losses after sharply increasing loan-loss reserves. Most of the loans in question are to Third World countries in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">South America</ENAMEX>.
In <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> composite trading yesterday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bankers Trust</ENAMEX> fell 12.5 cents to $50.50.
