The current debate over reinvigorating individual retirement accounts boils down to this: Would you prefer your tax break as an appetizer or as dessert?
Democrats would give taxpayers an immediate incentive to sock away more savings: Save $2,000, and you can deduct $1,000 on your tax return.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Republicans</ENAMEX> would defer the tax break: Save $2,000, and you'll escape taxes on all the interest that sum earns over the years till you retire.
Addressing the nation's savings shortage is once again politically fashionable. And there is ample reason for concern. The dearth of savings limits the resources available for investment in the future and forces the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> to import foreign savings.
But some economists suggest the politicians' new infatuation with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Iras</ENAMEX> may be misplaced at a time when <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Congress</ENAMEX> and the president aren't taking the more important step of shrinking the federal budget deficit. ``If increasing savings is the object,'' says economist <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jane Gravelle</ENAMEX> of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Congressional Research Service</ENAMEX>, ``a reduction in the deficit would be a more certain and more powerful way of achieving such an end.'' (The nation's total savings is what's left after substracting government borrowing from household and corporate savings.)
The differences between the two IRA alternatives involve more  than partisan manuevering -- although there's plenty of that.
The shortcoming of offering immediate rewards for putting money in an IRA, as the Democrats propose, is that it will widen the budget deficit by an estimated $12.5 billion over the next five years. ``The big problem is the up-front cost,'' says Sen. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">William Roth</ENAMEX> (R., <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Del.</ENAMEX>), chief Republican cheerleader for <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Iras</ENAMEX>.
The shortcomings of delaying the reward, as Sen. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Roth</ENAMEX> and Sen. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Robert Packwood</ENAMEX> (R., <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ore.</ENAMEX>) propose, is that it may not boost savings much and, if it does, it may widen deficits in the future. ``It looks like you haven't given anything away, but five, 10, 20, 40 years later, little bomblets go off,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Henry Aaron</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Brookings Institution</ENAMEX> economist.
Although <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IRA</ENAMEX> fans in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Congress</ENAMEX> have been talking about restoring incentives that were curtailed in 1986, they gained momentum only after <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Senate Finance Committee</ENAMEX> Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lloyd Bentsen</ENAMEX> (D., <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Texas</ENAMEX>) seized on Iras as an alternative to cutting capital-gains taxes.
Republican senators, unwilling to concede the popular IRA issue to Democrats, suddenly embraced a scheme Sen. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Roth</ENAMEX> had been pressing with little success. The Bush administration, which was planning to unveil an IRA proposal of its own next year, was quick to do the same. Both proposals would allow withdrawals not only for retirement, but also for buying a house or paying tuition bills.
Between 1981 and 1986, any worker could put $2,000 a year into an IRA and deduct that sum from his taxable income. As banks and mutual funds advertised heavily, hundreds of billions of dollars flowed into the accounts.
Economists still disagree on how much was new savings and how much was shifts of existing savings by taxpayers in order to cut their tax bill. Economist <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">David Wise</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Harvard University</ENAMEX> figures 70% was actually new savings; many prominent economists -- including <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Michael Boskin</ENAMEX>, chairman of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Council of Economic Advisers</ENAMEX> -- agree that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Iras</ENAMEX> did result in significant new savings.
But Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Aaron</ENAMEX>, among others, continues to insist that the data are inconclusive. And <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Robert Mcintyre</ENAMEX>, director of the labor-backed Citizens for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tax Justice</ENAMEX> and an admirer of the 1986 <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tax Reform</ENAMEX> Act that limited Iras, goes further. ``They don't work,'' he contends. ``They just give people a tax break for savings they would have done anyway.''
In any event, IRA contributions fell sharply after the 1986 law that restricted the full tax break to couples earning less than $40,000 a year and individuals earning less than $25,000. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Balances</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">IRA</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Keogh</ENAMEX> accounts (retirement accounts for the self-employed), which had swelled by $75 billion in 1986, grew by only $48 billion in 1988, including interest on past contributions.
It isn't clear how Americans would react to the new IRA proposals because they are so different from the old scheme.
Some economists predict any IRA plan will boost savings because brokerage houses, mutual funds and banks will advertise them heavily. ``It may well be that saving, like life insurance, is sold, not bought,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lawrence Summers</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Harvard University</ENAMEX>. He notes that as IRA ads vanished, even many middle-income Americans still eligible for the full IRA tax break stopped contributing.
Comparing the two proposals on the table, many economists say a rational person ought to prefer the Republican version because it offers a much bigger tax break.
Under the Democratic plan, a 40-year-old in the 33% tax bracket who saves $2,000 in an IRA would cut his tax bill by $175 immediately. When he retires 25 years later, his $2,000 -- assuming it were invested at 5% -- would be worth $6,773. But $5,773 of that would be taxed when withdrawn from the
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Republicans</ENAMEX> wouldn't give any up-front deduction for depositing $2,000 in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">IRA</ENAMEX>. But at retirement 25 years later, the entire $4,773 in interest could be withdrawn taxfree, along with the already taxed $2,000 initial contribution.
Nonetheless, some economists argue that Americans simply won't save unless the government gives them an immediate reward. ``This instant gratification overcomes the usual bias against savings,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John Skinner</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">University of Virginia</ENAMEX> economist. The clincher, he says, is that people who owed money to the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Internal Revenue Service</ENAMEX> were far more likely to put money in an IRA than those who were due a refund.
On the other hand, the case for delayed gratification is bolstered by evidence that a surprising number of upper-income Americans still are putting money in Iras even though the only tax break is deferring tax on the interest the contributions earn.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Employee Benefit Research Institute</ENAMEX> says about 23% of all workers earning more than $50,000 a year made IRA deposits in 1987, down from 56% in 1982 but still nearly one million people.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Donald Underwood</ENAMEX>, head of retirement planning for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merrill Lynch & Co.</ENAMEX>, says he was surprised to discover that more money flowed into the firm's IRA accounts in 1988 than in 1987. (A big IRA fan, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Underwood</ENAMEX>'s license plate reads:
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merrill Lynch</ENAMEX> is convinced the Republican IRA plan would appeal to its customers, and it is lobbying strongly for it. ``I think people are really concerned about what the tax rate will be in the future,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Underwood</ENAMEX> says. The higher tax rates go in the future, of course, the more valuable the future tax breaks.
The bigger the incentive the government offers for savings, the more tax revenues a scheme would lose -- or so many economists reason.
But that's not how Sen. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Roth</ENAMEX> and his allies look at it. First, they would allow people with old-fashioned <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Iras</ENAMEX> to shift the money to the new ones as long as they pay tax -- at today's lower tax rates -- on the previously deducted contributions. That would raise $11.5 billion for the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Treasury</ENAMEX> over the next five years, congressonal tax experts estimate. But allowing the interest buildup on those contributions to escape taxation would cost the Treasury far more than that sum in the long run, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Congressional Budget Office</ENAMEX> says. ``It's a huge giveaway,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Summers</ENAMEX> protests.
Second, Sen. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Roth</ENAMEX> insists that the extra savings his plan would produce would spur so much extra economic growth that the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Treasury</ENAMEX> wouldn't suffer. The claim is an echo of the supply-side promise that the 1981 tax cuts that bear Sen. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Roth</ENAMEX>'s name would finance themselves through added growth or added savings.
home. contribution.
purchase of home, college tuition and books, catastrophic health expenses. tax-free. law would continue to have that
