A simmering feud between the Thatcher government's two senior economic experts erupted with the abrupt resignation of Chancellor of the Exchequer <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Nigel Lawson</ENAMEX>, sending shock waves through an already shaken financial community and prompting an emergency cabinet shuffle.
Prime Minister <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Margaret</ENAMEX> Thatcher named Foreign Secretary <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John Major</ENAMEX> to succeed Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lawson</ENAMEX>. Sir <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Geoffrey Howe</ENAMEX>, deputy prime minister, rushed out a statement in the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">House of Commons</ENAMEX> that the government's economic and monetary policies would remain ``unchanged.'' Meanwhile, Sir <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Alan Walters</ENAMEX>, Mrs. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Thatcher</ENAMEX>'s controversial economic adviser and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lawson</ENAMEX>'s nemesis, also announced his resignation.
The pound, which has already slid about 10% against the West German mark in recent weeks, plunged further on the news. In late <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> trading yesterday, sterling was quoted at $1.5765, down sharply from $1.6145 late Wednesday. And brokers were bracing for a grueling Friday in financial markets here. ``You're going to get quite a major fall in the equity market and the gilt markets,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gwyn Hacche</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.K.</ENAMEX> economist with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">James Capel & Co.</ENAMEX> ``Markets hate uncertainty.''
Despite the Howe statement, the Thatcher government's economic policy appeared to be in chaos. One major question is just how the government will handle matters on which Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lawson</ENAMEX> and Sir <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Alan</ENAMEX> differed explosively. The two men clashed bitterly over the importance of exchange rates in setting monetary policy and the wisdom of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> fully joining the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">European Monetary System</ENAMEX>, which links together the major currencies in the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">European Community</ENAMEX>.
Though jolted by the surrounding confusion, Mrs. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Thatcher</ENAMEX> emerged in undisputed command of her government's economic program. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Neil Kinnock</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Labor Party</ENAMEX> leader, dubbed the 46-year-old Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Major</ENAMEX> a ``lap dog'' unlikely to veer from his boss's strongly held views, as Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lawson</ENAMEX> sometimes did.
From the standpoint of the financial markets, however, the prime minister's positions seem murky -- in large part because she has presided over dueling advisers for the last six months. ``I don't know where Thatcher stands,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Paul Horne</ENAMEX>, an economist with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Smith Barney</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Harris Upham & Co.</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Paris</ENAMEX>. ``She's played such a cat-and-mouse game with her advisers.''
Although sometimes arcane economic debates undergirded the <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lawson-Walters</ENAMEX> rift, the 57-year-old Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lawson</ENAMEX>'s surprise departure boiled down to a simple stand of he-goes-or-I-go. In his letter to Mrs. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Thatcher</ENAMEX>, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lawson</ENAMEX> stated: ``The successful conduct of economic policy is possible only if there is, and is seen to be, full agreement between the prime minister and chancellor of the exchequer. Recent events have confirmed that this essential requirement can not be satisfied so long as <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Alan Walters</ENAMEX> remains your personal economic adviser.''
The upheaval leaves the Thatcher government isolated within the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">European Community</ENAMEX>. Six months ago, the British prime minister's two senior cabinet members -- Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lawson</ENAMEX>, chancellor since 1983, and Sir <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Geoffrey</ENAMEX>, then the foreign secretary -- both supported <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX>'s early entry into the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">EMS</ENAMEX>. With Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lawson</ENAMEX> out of the cabinet, and Sir <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Geoffrey</ENAMEX> in the less-influential job of deputy prime minister, there's little to counter Mrs. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Thatcher</ENAMEX>'s innate suspicion of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">EC</ENAMEX>'s exchange-rate mechanism. Sir <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Alan</ENAMEX>, brought back to Downing Street last spring as her adviser, adamantly opposed it.
Indeed, the final fracas in the <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lawson-Walters</ENAMEX> battle involved the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">EMS</ENAMEX>. Sir <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Alan</ENAMEX>, who also works in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Washington</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">D.C.</ENAMEX>, as a consultant to the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">World Bank</ENAMEX> and a fellow at the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Enterprise Institute</ENAMEX>, said in a article to be published in a U.S. economic journal that the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">EMS</ENAMEX> was ``half-baked.''
The scoff, coming from the man many consider Mrs. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Thatcher</ENAMEX>'s most influential adviser, sparked considerable worry. It not only conflicted with Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lawson</ENAMEX>'s views but ran counter to the position Mrs. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Thatcher</ENAMEX> took at the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">EC</ENAMEX> summit in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Madrid</ENAMEX> last June. There, she said that <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> would join the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">EMS</ENAMEX> once the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">EC</ENAMEX> had completely liberalized restrictions on capital movements and exchange controls, and once <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX>'s inflation rate had fallen into line with the rest of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">EC</ENAMEX>. Economists expect those conditions to be met in 1990 or 1991.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lawson</ENAMEX> stated in a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">House of Commons</ENAMEX> debate this week that Sir <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Alan</ENAMEX>'s views ``aren't the view of the government.'' And in a subsequent television interview, he said, ``I think it is right that advisers do not talk or write in public.''
Worn down by the feud, he then made it clear to Mrs. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Thatcher</ENAMEX> that he expected the controversial adviser to be ousted. In remarks in Commons yesterday afternoon, the prime minister disappointed him. As she has done in the past, she stated her support for Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lawson</ENAMEX> but insisted on keeping on an adviser who opposed and disparaged his policies.
The EMS views of Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Major</ENAMEX>, who served as Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lawson</ENAMEX>'s deputy in 1987, aren't fully known. Speaking in the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">House of Commons</ENAMEX> last night, he said of Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lawson</ENAMEX>, ``I was proud to serve in his team and proud that he has been and will remain a good friend.''
To a great extent, the Downing Street blow-up is the result of Mrs. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Thatcher</ENAMEX>'s management approach. Fond of playing her senior advisers off against each other, the prime minister has often allowed rivalries and animosities to bubble up within her cabinet.
Financial markets prefer a clear message from the government on its economic priorities and strategies. Since the spring, the Thatcher government has instead broadcast a cacophony. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lawson</ENAMEX> carefully watched exchange rates and stood ready to increase U.K. interest rates when the pound slid too sharply against the dollar or the mark. By contrast, Sir <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Alan</ENAMEX> was viewed as a ``free-floater,'' or one who was inclined to let the currency markets set the level for the pound.
Last summer, when the skirmishing became obvious, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Smith Barney</ENAMEX>'s Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Horne</ENAMEX> said that the antipathies were ``adding confusion to an already murky situation'' in which sterling was becoming an increasingly volatile currency. ``I question the strategy of having an alternate economic adviser,'' he added.
Mrs. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Thatcher</ENAMEX>'s ties with Sir <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Alan</ENAMEX> were cemented during her first term, when the straight-talking economist served for three years as a key adviser. According to a former Downing Street aide, she would then say to him, ``You get the economics right, and I'll get the politics right.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Craig Forman</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Richard E. Rustin</ENAMEX> contributed to this article.
