<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bolar Pharmaceutical Co.</ENAMEX>, under pressure from the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Food and Drug Administration</ENAMEX>, agreed to recall its generic version of the antibiotic drug Macrodantin from retail shelves, according to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FDA</ENAMEX> officials.
It was another setback for <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bolar</ENAMEX>, the flagship of the generic drug industry. Earlier this month, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bolar</ENAMEX> began recalling its nitrofurantoin macrocrystalline capsules from wholesalers and distributors because of FDA evidence suggesting that the company passed off Macrodantin as its own to obtain <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FDA</ENAMEX> approval to market its generic product. At that time, however, the company balked at a retail recall, arguing that the evidence wasn't sufficient to justify such a move.
But on Oct. 25, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FDA</ENAMEX> offered additional evidence to buttress its case that the brand-name drug had been substituted for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bolar</ENAMEX>'s product in pre-market testing, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FDA</ENAMEX> officials said yesterday. The agency now has evidence that <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bolar</ENAMEX> submitted Macrodantin as its generic version for testing not only at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pharmakinetics Laboratories Inc.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Baltimore</ENAMEX>, but also at an independent laboratory in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Canada</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FDA</ENAMEX> investigators obtained a sample of the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Bolar</ENAMEX> drug from the Canadian lab, according to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FDA</ENAMEX> official <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Michael Shaffer</ENAMEX>. ``It turned out to be the brand-name product,'' he said.
In <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Copiague</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.Y.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Robert Shulman</ENAMEX>, president of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bolar</ENAMEX>, and sales director <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Karen Sattig</ENAMEX> couldn't be reached for comment.
The inspector general's office of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Health and Human Services Department</ENAMEX> already is conducting a criminal investigation of whether <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bolar</ENAMEX> filed ``false information'' with the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FDA</ENAMEX> in seeking clearance to market at least two generic drugs.
Meanwhile, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FDA</ENAMEX> is moving to withdraw its approval of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bolar</ENAMEX>'s nitrofurantoin macrocrystalline capsules, which are used primarily to treat urinary-tract infections. The brand-name drug is manufactured by <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Norwich Eaton</ENAMEX>, a subsidiary of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Cincinnati</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Procter & Gamble Co.</ENAMEX>
Although no health problems are known to have been caused by <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bolar</ENAMEX>'s product, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FDA</ENAMEX> officials said the agency can no longer ensure that it is the equivalent of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Macrodantin</ENAMEX>.
