<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Westinghouse Electric Corp.</ENAMEX>, capitalizing on a major restructuring program, expects operating margins of more than 10% and double-digit per-share earnings growth next year, top officers told securities analysts here.
Since 1983, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Westinghouse</ENAMEX> has shed 70 businesses that it didn't expect to produce 10% operating margins while acquiring 55 businesses.
In the past 20 months alone, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Paul E. Lego</ENAMEX>, president and chief operating officer, said the divestiture of $300 million of slow-growth, low-profit businesses has been more than offset by $600 million in profitable acquisitions.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Westinghouse</ENAMEX> expects to meet its corporate goals despite a softening in the economy. Even if the gross national product is either flat or in the growth range of 2% to 2.5%, ``we can handle that,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Marous</ENAMEX> said. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GNP</ENAMEX> is the total value of the nation's output of goods and services.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Westinghouse</ENAMEX> also is well positioned to sell steam turbine and gas turbine plants to independent power producers. The company's ability to respond to energy needs world-wide will be enhanced through a recently announced venture with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mitsubishi Heavy Industries</ENAMEX>, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lego</ENAMEX> said.
He said the independent power segment could grow to provide as much as 50% of near-term generation capacity, adding: ``We expect to supply a significant share of this market.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Westinghouse</ENAMEX> also expects its international sales to soon grow to 25% of total corporate sales from 20% last year. The company is negotiating with the Soviets to build a Thermo King truck-refrigeration plant that would produce about 10,000 units annually.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Marous</ENAMEX> said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Westinghouse</ENAMEX> would own 70% of the facility. The deal, which will involve an initial $20 million investment, was struck with a handshake, he added.
Company officials also said that any gain from the sale of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Westinghouse</ENAMEX>'s 55% stake in its transmission and distribution venture with the Swiss firm of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Asea Brown Boveri</ENAMEX> will be offset by a restructuring charge in the fourth quarter. The executives didn't disclose the size of the expected gain.
Capital expenditure in 1990 will rise slightly, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Marous</ENAMEX> said, from an estimated $470 million this year.
