<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Conner Peripherals Inc.</ENAMEX>, which has a near-monopoly on a key part used in many portable computers, is on target to surpass <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Compaq Computer Corp.</ENAMEX> as the fastest-growing start-up manufacturing firm in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> business history.
Analysts expect <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Conner</ENAMEX>'s earnings to reach roughly $40 million, or $1 to $1.05 a share, on sales of $650 million, for 1989, the company's third full year in business. That's a faster growth rate than reported by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Compaq</ENAMEX>, which didn't post similar results until its fourth year, in 1986. But <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Compaq</ENAMEX> had achieved that level of sales faster than any previous manufacturing start-up.
Today, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Conner</ENAMEX> controls an estimated 90% of the hard-disk drive market for laptop computers. The company supplies drives to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Compaq</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Zenith Data Systems</ENAMEX>, the top two U.S. manufacturers of laptops, and to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Toshiba Corp.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NEC Corp.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sharp Corp.</ENAMEX>, the leading Japanese laptop makers.
And the Japanese are likely to keep close on <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Conner</ENAMEX>'s heels. ``They are going to catch up,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">David Claridge</ENAMEX>, an analyst with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hambrecht & Quist</ENAMEX>. Both <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Toshiba</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NEC</ENAMEX> already produce hard-disk drives, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony</ENAMEX> also is studying the field, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Claridge</ENAMEX> said.
But <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Conner</ENAMEX> isn't standing still. Yesterday, the company introduced four products, three of which are aimed at a hot new class of computers called notebooks. Each of the three drives uses a mere 1.5 watts of power and one weighs just 5.5 ounces.
``Most of our competitors are announcing products based on our (older) products,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Finis Conner</ENAMEX>, chief executive officer and founder of the firm that bears his name. ``We continue to develop products faster than anyone else can.'' These new products could account for as much as 35% of the company's business in 1990, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Conner</ENAMEX> estimated. ``We're not afraid of obsoleting some of our old stuff to stay ahead of the competition,'' he said.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Conner</ENAMEX> already is shipping its new drives. Last week, for instance, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Compaq</ENAMEX> introduced its first notebook computer to rave reviews. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Conner</ENAMEX> is supplying hard-disk drives for the machine, which weighs only six pounds and fits in a briefcase.
From its inception, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Conner</ENAMEX> has targeted the market for battery-operated machines, building hard-disk drives that are smaller and use far less power than those offered by competitors such as <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Seagate</ENAMEX>. The availability of these drives, in turn, boosted demand for laptop computers, whose usefulness had been limited because of lack of storage.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Conner</ENAMEX> also makes hard-disk drives for desktop computers and is a major supplier to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Compaq</ENAMEX>, which as of July owned 40% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Conner</ENAMEX>'s stock. Sales to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Compaq</ENAMEX> represented 26% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Conner</ENAMEX>'s business in its third quarter, compared with 42% in the year-ago period.
