<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nissan Motor Co.</ENAMEX> expects net income to reach 120 billion yen (U.S. $857 million) in its current fiscal year, up from 114.6 billion yen in the previous year, Yutaka <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kume</ENAMEX>, president, said.
The executive said that the anticipated earnings increase is fairly modest because <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nissan</ENAMEX> is spending heavily to bolster its dealership network in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX> and because of currency-exchange fluctuations.
``By the end of the 1990s,'' he said, ``we want to be producing roughly two vehicles overseas for every vehicle that we export from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX>.'' That will involve a substantial increase in overseas manufacturing capacity, he acknowledged, but didn't provide specific details.
