Investors dumped stocks of big companies whose earnings fluctuate with the economy.
Recession fears are springing up again among investors. Analysts say that the selling of cyclical stocks yesterday will be followed by a sell-off in shares of companies with big debt loads on their balance sheets. In an economic slowdown, heavy debt loads reduce the flexibility of companies because cash that would normally be used to keep the company buoyant must be diverted to interest payments.
Many money managers are bracing for a decline in stocks of companies with big debt loads on their balance sheets. ``The junk bond market is being taken apart'' because of recession fears, said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">J. David Mills</ENAMEX>, senior vice president at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boston Company Advisers</ENAMEX>. ``Under this scrutiny, the first thing you do is sell your cyclical stocks and the second thing you do is sell your over-leveraged companies.''
In fact, much of the buying in blue chips yesterday was a pursuit of companies with lower debt levels. In a recent investment letter entitled ``Winners of the `Leverage <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Wars</ENAMEX>,' ``<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Edward Kerschner</ENAMEX>, chairman of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Painewebber</ENAMEX>'s investment policy committee, suggested that investors buy stocks of companies that have avoided loading up on debt.
``We're saying companies have to pay increasing attention to balance sheets,'' said Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kerschner</ENAMEX>. He suggested that investors buy the shares of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Great Atlantic & Pacific</ENAMEX> Tea, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">J. Baker</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mcdonald</ENAMEX>'s, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Philip Morris</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Sara Lee</ENAMEX>. He said that all of these companies will be able to compete fiercely in an economic downturn. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mcdonald</ENAMEX>'s has long-term debt equaling 91% of shareholder equity currently, but Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kerschner</ENAMEX> said the company is carrying real estate assets at about $2.6 billion below their real value.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coca-Cola</ENAMEX> climbed 1 3/8 to 72 1/8; <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mcdonald</ENAMEX>'s added 1 to 31 3/8, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Procter & Gamble</ENAMEX> gained 3/4 to 130 5/8. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">A&P</ENAMEX> fell 1 1/4 to 57 5/8, and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">J. Baker</ENAMEX> gained 3/8 to 21 1/4. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Philip Morris</ENAMEX> slipped 1/2 to 43 7/8, while <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sara Lee</ENAMEX> closed unchanged at 60 1/8.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Union Carbide</ENAMEX>, whose third-quarter earnings dropped about 35% from a year earlier and fell short of analysts' expectations, declined 1/2 to 24 1/2. Also, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Exxon</ENAMEX> went down 3/8 to 45 3/4 and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Allied-Signal</ENAMEX> lost 7/8 to 35 1/8 even though the companies' results for the quarter were in line with forecasts.
Elsewhere in the chemicals sector, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Chemical</ENAMEX> fell 1 1/4 to 97 1/2, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Monsanto</ENAMEX> lost 1 7/8 to 118, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">B.F. Goodrich</ENAMEX> slipped 2 1/4 to 44 3/4 and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Olin</ENAMEX> slid 1 to 57 3/4. Other stocks hurt by earnings-related selling included <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tandy</ENAMEX>, which dropped 1 3/8 to 44, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Eaton</ENAMEX>, which retreated 2 1/2 to 57 1/2. Third-quarter earnings at both companies were below analysts' forecasts.
After declining about 41% last week, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> advanced 9 7/8 to 178 3/8 on 1.1 million shares on anticipation of a revised takeover offer from a labor-management group for the parent company of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Airlines</ENAMEX>. However, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Delta Air Lines</ENAMEX> fell 1 1/2 to 67 1/2 and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Usair Group</ENAMEX> dropped 3/4 to 42 1/2.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ramada</ENAMEX> gained 7/8 to 11 1/4 after revamping the terms of its restructuring plan, which calls for the company to sell its hotel operations for $540 million and spin off its casino business to shareholders. The revision follows last month's withdrawal of a $400 million junk-bond offering for the new casino company, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Aztar Corp.</ENAMEX>
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mead</ENAMEX> gained 1 to 37 7/8. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">USA</ENAMEX> Today reported that the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Rales brothers</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Washington</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">D.C.</ENAMEX>-based investors who made an unsuccessful offer to acquire <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Interco</ENAMEX> last year, have bought nearly 3% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mead's</ENAMEX> common shares.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Carnival Cruise Lines</ENAMEX> Class A fell 1 3/4 to 20 3/4. The company said it had been notified unofficially that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Waertsilae Marine Industries</ENAMEX>, a Finnish shipyard building three cruise ships for the company, is having financial trouble and may already have filed for bankruptcy.
