<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mercury Savings & Loan Association</ENAMEX> said it retained <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merrill Lynch</ENAMEX> Capital Markets as its lead investment banker to advise it regarding a possible sale or other combination of the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Huntington Beach</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Calif.</ENAMEX>, thrift.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mercury</ENAMEX>, which has assets of more than $2 billion and 24 branches in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">California</ENAMEX>, said the action to improve its regulatory capital position is related directly to new capital requirements mandated by recently adopted federal legislation. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mercury</ENAMEX> also said it extended its two-year advisory relationship with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Montgomery Securities</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">San Francisco</ENAMEX>.
