<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones & Co.</ENAMEX> extended its tender offer of $18 a share, or about $576 million, for the 33% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate Inc.</ENAMEX> that it doesn't already own until 5 p.m. EST, Nov. 6.
The offer, which <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX>'s two independent directors have rejected as inadequate, previously had been scheduled to expire at midnight Friday. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> said it extended the offer to allow shareholders time to review a supplement to the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> tender offer circular that it mailed last Friday.
The supplement contains various information that has been filed with the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Securities and Exchange Commission</ENAMEX> since <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> launched the offer on Sept. 26, but it doesn't change the terms and conditions of the offer except to extend its expiration date.
In <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Delaware</ENAMEX> Chancery Court litigation, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX> has criticized <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> for not disclosing that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX>'s management expects the company's revenue to increase by 20% annually, while <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> based its projections of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX>'s performance on a 12% revenue growth forecast. In the tender offer supplement, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> discloses the different growth forecasts but says it views the 20% growth rate ``as a hoped-for goal'' of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX>'s management ``and not as a realistic basis on which to project the company's likely future performance.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX> shares fell 50 cents on Friday to close at $20 each in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> composite trading. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> shares also fell 50 cents to close at $36.125 in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Board</ENAMEX> composite trading.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> has said it believes the $18-a-share price is fair to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX>'s minority shareholders. Late last week, representatives of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Telerate</ENAMEX> began negotiations about the terms of the offer, but those talks didn't result in any changes in the offer.
