<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Airways PLC</ENAMEX>, a crucial participant in the proposed buy-out of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL Corp.</ENAMEX>, washed its hands of the current efforts to revive a bid for the parent of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Airlines</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Company</ENAMEX> officials said later that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Airways</ENAMEX> believes its involvement in the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> buy-out ended last Friday when the buy-out group, which also includes <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX>'s management and pilot union, failed to obtain financing for the $6.79 billion transaction.
The carrier stopped short of saying it wouldn't at some point reconsider participating in any new bid for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX>. However, company officials said they plan to take ``no initiatives'' to resurrect the transaction, and ``aren't aware'' of any restructured bid in the making.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Collectively</ENAMEX>, the statements raised questions about whether a new bid for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> will ever get off the ground. The transaction has had a series of setbacks since the financing problems became known last Friday, with no signs or statements from the buy-out group to indicate that any progress has taken place.
However, in response to the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Air</ENAMEX> decision, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United</ENAMEX>'s pilot union vowed to continue efforts to revive the buy-out. Pilot union Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Frederick C. Dubinsky</ENAMEX> said advisers to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> management and the union will begin meeting in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> today and will work through the weekend to devise a new proposal to present to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX>'s board ``at the earliest time possible.'' Pilot union advisers appeared confident that a new bid could go forward even without <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Air</ENAMEX>'s participation.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> declined to comment on <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Air</ENAMEX>'s statement. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stephen M. Wolf</ENAMEX>, who is leading the management end of the buy-out, hasn't provided investors with any assurances about the prospect of a new deal.
In another setback yesterday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United</ENAMEX>'s machinist union asked the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Treasury Department</ENAMEX> to investigate whether certain aspects of the original buy-out proposal violated tax laws. In an effort to derail the buy-out, the union has already called for investigations by the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Securities and Exchange Commission</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Transportation Department</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Labor Department</ENAMEX>.
But there was one bright spot yesterday. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United</ENAMEX> flight-attendants union agreed to negotiations that could lead to the flight attendants contributing concessions to a revived bid in exchange for an ownership stake. The pilot union, the only one to support the buy-out thus far, said the flight attendants' decision ``enforces our belief that an all-employee owned airline is practical and achievable.''
Still, without the assurance of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Airways</ENAMEX>' financial backing, it will be tougher for the buy-out group to convince already-reluctant banks to make loan commitments for a revised bid, especially since <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Air</ENAMEX>'s original investment represented 78% of the cash equity contribution for the bid.
Under the previous plan, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Air</ENAMEX> would have received a 15% stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> in exchange for a $750 million equity investment, with a 75% stake going to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> employees and 10% to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> management.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Air</ENAMEX> officials said the airline's chairman, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lord King</ENAMEX>, was concerned about news reports indicating that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Air</ENAMEX> might be willing to participate in a bid that included a lower purchase price and better investment terms for the British carrier.
The previous reports were based on remarks by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Air</ENAMEX>'s chief financial officer, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Derek Stevens</ENAMEX>, who said any revised bid would have to include a lower purchase price to reflect the sharp drop in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX>'s stock in the past week.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> declined to comment on <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Air</ENAMEX>'s statement.
In an interview Wednesday with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> Professional Investor Report, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stevens</ENAMEX> said, ``We're in no way committed to a deal going through at all. We're not rushing into anything. We don't want to be party to a second rejection.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Airways</ENAMEX> may have begun to have second thoughts about the transaction after the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Transportation Department</ENAMEX> forced <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Northwest's Airlines</ENAMEX>' new owners to restructure the equity contribution of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">KLM Royal Dutch Airlines</ENAMEX> in that carrier. Most of the department's statements since the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Northwest</ENAMEX> transaction indicated it planned to curtail foreign ownership stakes in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> carriers.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX>'s advisers have indicated previously that it may take a while to come forward with a revised plan since they want to have firm bank commitments before launching a new bid. They have maintained that banks remain interested in financing the transaction. The buy-out fell through after <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Citicorp</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chase Manhattan Corp.</ENAMEX>, the lead banks in the transaction, failed to obtain $7.2 billion in financing needed for the plan.
