Citizens <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Bancorp</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Inc.</ENAMEX> said it agreed to buy Lakeland <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Financial Group Inc.</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Succasunna</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.J.</ENAMEX>, bank holding company, for about $50.6 million in cash and stock.
Citizens First, which controls <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Citizens First National Bank</ENAMEX> and is based in <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Glen Rock</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.J.</ENAMEX>, will pay a maximum of 40% in cash for the parent of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lakeland Savings Bank</ENAMEX> and the remainder in convertible preferred stock, with a liquidation value of $18 a share. Lakeland holders will have the option to request either stock or cash.
