<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Avon Products Inc.</ENAMEX> posted a third-quarter profit of $34.6 million, reversing a year-earlier loss.
The cosmetics, jewelry and gift products concern had per-share earnings of 46 cents in the latest quarter. A year earlier, it reported a loss of $405.9 million, or $7.78 a share, due to a one-time $425 million charge for discontinued operations.
Sales rose 8% to $785.1 million from $725.6 million.
Avon said sales in the direct-selling division dropped 2% as sales of new products, especially gift and jewelry lines, were below expectations. The weak sales are expected to continue into the fourth quarter, Avon added.
``Third-quarter net was on target with expectations,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Andrew Shore</ENAMEX>, an analyst at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Shearson Lehman Hutton Inc.</ENAMEX> But the third quarter isn't the problem, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Shore</ENAMEX> added. ``It's the fourth quarter and what might linger beyond that.''
Last month, Avon executives indicated that the company would experience a $75 million to $90 million revenue shortage due to weakness in its gift and decorative lines.
In the nine months, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Avon</ENAMEX> earned $80.3 million, or 97 cents a share, compared with a net loss of $461.1 million, or $7.20 a share. Revenue rose 11% to $2.27 billion from $2.05 billion.
