Cineplex <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Odeon Corp.</ENAMEX> directors said the company's chairman and chief executive, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Garth Drabinsky</ENAMEX>, is considering bidding 780.6 million Canadian dollars (US$666 million) to acquire the company.
The directors said if <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Messrs</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Drabinsky</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gottlieb</ENAMEX> mail an offer to shareholders by Nov. 22, it will reimburse them a maximum of C$8.5 million for expenses related to a bid.
``We consider that his bid is an acceptable bid,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Sandra Kolber</ENAMEX>, spokeswoman for the independent directors' committee appointed last May to solicit and review bids for the company in the wake of a dispute between Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Drabinsky</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Cineplex</ENAMEX>'s major shareholder, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MCA Inc.</ENAMEX>
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MCA</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cineplex</ENAMEX>'s other major shareholder, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Montreal</ENAMEX>-based financier <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Charles Bronfman</ENAMEX> and his associates, have agreed to tender their holdings to an offer by Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Drabinsky</ENAMEX> unless a higher offer is made by another bidder. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MCA</ENAMEX> holds half of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cineplex</ENAMEX>'s equity and 33% of its voting rights through restricted voting shares, while Bronfman interests hold about 24% of the company's equity.
Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kolber</ENAMEX> said the committee had received other bids. She declined to identify other bidders but said Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Drabinsky</ENAMEX>'s offer ``is all cash, and it's for all of the company.'' Several Cineplex analysts have speculated that outside bids received by the committee were either disappointingly low or for only part of the company.
``All this has really established is that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MCA</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bronfmans</ENAMEX> have agreed on a price at which they can be bought out,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jeffery Logsdon</ENAMEX>, an analyst with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Crowell, Weedon</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Los Angeles</ENAMEX>. ``If a bid materializes at that price, shareholders will have every reason to be glad, but the question of financing still remains.''
Last April, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Drabinsky</ENAMEX> and a group of financial backers planned to acquire up to 30.2% of Cineplex for C$17.50/NNP a share from <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bronfman</ENAMEX> associates. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Drabinsky</ENAMEX>, who would have had the right to vote those shares for two years, said the purchase, subsequently rejected by regulators, was aimed at consolidating his control of the company. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MCA</ENAMEX> strongly opposed the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Drabinsky group</ENAMEX>'s move.
``This is being done at the suggestion of {Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Drabinsky</ENAMEX>} and to accommodate him, to facilitate his financing arrangements,'' Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kolber</ENAMEX> said.
In addition, the directors said if a bid by Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Drabinsky</ENAMEX> is successful, Cineplex expects Rank <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Organisation PLC</ENAMEX> to acquire the 51% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cineplex's Film House</ENAMEX> unit it doesn't own, and provide Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Drabinsky</ENAMEX> with additional loan financing.
Cineplex shareholders responded coolly to yesterday's announcement. In trading on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cineplex</ENAMEX> closed at $11, down 25 cents, with more than a million shares changing hands. On the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Toronto Stock Exchange</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cineplex</ENAMEX> closed at C$12.875, off 37.5 Canadian cents, well below the C$16.40 level.
``Where's the bid?'' asked <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Pierre Panet-Raymond</ENAMEX>, an analyst and broker with <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Toronto</ENAMEX> securities dealer Mcdermid <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">St. Lawrence Ltd.</ENAMEX> Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Panet-Raymond</ENAMEX> said he doesn't think <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Messrs</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Drabinsky</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gottlieb</ENAMEX> are ``anywhere close'' to arranging financing and that investors will need a solid offer before the stock begins to rise again.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Drabinsky</ENAMEX> couldn't be reached for comment.
