As expected, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner Bros.</ENAMEX> Records said it agreed to form a recorded-music and music-publishing joint venture with former <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MCA Records</ENAMEX> Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Irving Azoff</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> said it will provide financing for the venture, but didn't disclose terms. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Azoff</ENAMEX> hasn't named the company yet, but any records it produces will be distributed by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> is part of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner Communications Inc.</ENAMEX>, which is in the process of being acquired by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Time Warner Inc.</ENAMEX> Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Azoff</ENAMEX> resigned as head of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MCA Records</ENAMEX>, a unit of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MCA Inc.</ENAMEX>, in September, and had been discussing a joint venture with both <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MCA</ENAMEX>. In a statement yesterday, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Azoff</ENAMEX> said he chose <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX>, the largest record company, because ``their standing in the entertainment industry is second to none.
