<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Combustion Engineering Inc.</ENAMEX> said third-quarter net income of $22.8 million, reversing a $91.7 million year-earlier loss.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Stamford</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Conn.</ENAMEX>, power-generation products and services company said per-share earnings were 56 cents compared with the year-ago loss of $2.39. Sales fell 1.5% to $884 million from $897.2 million.
Strong profit in the process industries, including chemical and pulp and paper, were offset by higher interest expense and by lower earnings as the company closed out certain long-term contracts.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Combustion</ENAMEX> reported improved profits in its automation and control products businesses, and it narrowed its losses in its public sector and environmental segment. Power generation had higher sales but lower earnings; the company cited factors including work on certain low profit-margin contracts from previous years.
Net in the latest quarter included a pretax gain of $22.4 million from the sale of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Combustion</ENAMEX>'s minority interest in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Stein Industrie</ENAMEX> to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GEC Alsthom N.V.</ENAMEX> of the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Netherlands</ENAMEX>. Last year's results reflected a gain of $28.2 million on disposition of assets and a $165 million pretax provision mainly from costs of completing certain waste-to-energy and other power plants.
