<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cie.</ENAMEX> de <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navigation Mixte</ENAMEX> Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Marc Fournier</ENAMEX> said his board unanimously rejected as too low the $1.77 billion bid by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cie</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Financiere de Paribas</ENAMEX> to bring its stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navigation Mixte</ENAMEX> to 66.7%.
The chairman said his board members, including representatives of West German insurance giant <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Allianz AG</ENAMEX> and French banks <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Credit Lyonnais</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Societe Generale</ENAMEX>, hold nearly 50% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navigation Mixte</ENAMEX>'s capital.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Fournier</ENAMEX> said that as <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navigation Mixte</ENAMEX> chairman, he is prohibited by takeover regulations from organizing his own defense or doing anything besides managing current company business. But sources said he will be urging his allies to boost their stakes in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Navigation Mixte</ENAMEX>, which is being traded in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX> and is to resume trading in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Paris</ENAMEX> Tuesday. At the same time, he is expected to seek legal and regulatory means of blocking or delaying <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paribas</ENAMEX>'s bid. For the moment, the sources said, he has decided against seeking a white knight or organizing a counterbid for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paribas</ENAMEX>.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Fournier</ENAMEX> said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navigation Mixte</ENAMEX>'s 1989 unconsolidated, or parent-company, profit is likely to be 4.7 billion francs ($754.4 million), up from 633.8 million francs last year. That is due mostly to payments from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Allianz</ENAMEX> for most of the 50% stake it has agreed to acquire in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Navigation Mixte</ENAMEX>'s insurance business. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Fournier</ENAMEX> said the exceptional gain would mean nearly twice as high a dividend this year as last. If holders avoid tendering to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paribas</ENAMEX>, he added, they can expect strong dividends again next year.
``Without some unexpected ``coup de theatre'', I don't see what will block the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paribas</ENAMEX> bid,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Philippe de Cholet</ENAMEX>, analyst at the brokerage <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cholet-Dupont & Cie</ENAMEX>. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">de Cholet</ENAMEX> said Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Fournier</ENAMEX>'s biggest hope was to somehow persuade regulatory authorities to block the bid. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paribas</ENAMEX> still needs the go-ahead from the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Commission</ENAMEX> des <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Operations de Bourse</ENAMEX>, a government regulatory agency, but analysts said that is considered likely.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Fournier</ENAMEX> also noted that Navigation <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mixte</ENAMEX> joined <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paribas</ENAMEX>'s core of shareholders when <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paribas</ENAMEX> was denationalized in 1987, and said it now holds just under 5% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paribas</ENAMEX>'s shares. Once he realized that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paribas</ENAMEX>'s intentions weren't friendly, he said, but before the bid was launched, he sought approval to boost his <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paribas</ENAMEX> stake above 10%. The petition is still pending, but Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Fournier</ENAMEX> downplayed the likelihood of his organizing a takeover bid of his own for the much-larger <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paribas</ENAMEX>.
One big question now is the likely role of Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Fournier</ENAMEX>'s allies. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Fournier</ENAMEX> said the large institutions that hold nearly 50% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navigation Mixte</ENAMEX>'s capital all strongly support him, but some analysts said they aren't so sure. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Allianz</ENAMEX>, for example, has said in official comments so far that it will remain neutral. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paribas</ENAMEX> is <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Allianz</ENAMEX>'s lead French bank.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paribas</ENAMEX> said Monday that it intends to bid to boost its stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navigation Mixte</ENAMEX> to 66.7%, from the 18.7% it already owns. The purchase of the additional 48% stake is expected to cost more than 11 billion francs ($1.77 billion).
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paribas</ENAMEX> says it will offer 1,850 francs ($296.95) each for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navigation Mixte</ENAMEX> shares that enjoy full dividend rights, and 1,800 francs each for a block of shares issued July 1, which will receive only partial dividends this year. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Alternatively</ENAMEX>, it is to offer three <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paribas</ENAMEX> shares for one <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Navigation Mixte</ENAMEX> share. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paribas</ENAMEX> offer values <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navigation Mixte</ENAMEX> at about 23 billion francs, depending on how many of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navigation Mixte</ENAMEX>'s warrants are converted into shares during the takeover battle.
