In a sign the stock slump hasn't quieted <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Europe</ENAMEX>'s takeover fever, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Cie</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Financiere de Paribas</ENAMEX> said it intends to bid for one of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">France</ENAMEX>'s other large financial and industrial holding companies, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cie.</ENAMEX> de <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Navigation Mixte</ENAMEX>.
The move would greatly boost <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paribas</ENAMEX>'s stake in the insurance, transport and food businesses, where <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navigation Mixte</ENAMEX> is strong. It also would make Paribas a major French ally of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">West Germany</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Allianz AG</ENAMEX> insurance group.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Allianz</ENAMEX> holds a 50% stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navigation Mixte</ENAMEX>'s insurance interests, acquired three weeks ago. Those include <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rhin</ENAMEX> et <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Moselle Vie</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Via Assurances</ENAMEX>. Long considered a potential takeover target, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navigation Mixte</ENAMEX> had hoped <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Allianz</ENAMEX> would help protect it from raiders. That idea may have backfired. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paribas</ENAMEX> is <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Allianz</ENAMEX>'s main French bank, and the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Munich</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">group</ENAMEX> said it intends to stay neutral. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navigation Mixte</ENAMEX> said it wouldn't have any comment until its board meets Wednesday.
But <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navigation Mixte</ENAMEX> is loosely held and hard to defend. ``The defensive options are limited,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Philippe Braye</ENAMEX>, a partner in portfolio management concern <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">France Finance Quatre</ENAMEX>. ``Who would bid against <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paribas</ENAMEX>?''
If the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paribas</ENAMEX> bid succeeds, it will be the second time in two months a big French investment banking group has snapped up an insurance group. Last month, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paribas</ENAMEX>'s archrival, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cie</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Financiere de Suez</ENAMEX>, won a battle for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Groupe Victoire</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">France</ENAMEX>'s second-largest private-sector insurer, which itself had just acquired <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">West Germany</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Colonia Versicherung AG</ENAMEX>. That complex bid was billed as <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">France</ENAMEX>'s largest takeover ever (this one is slightly smaller). Moreover, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Suez</ENAMEX> had just finished winning an even larger battle last year for control of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Societe Generale</ENAMEX> de <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Belgique.</ENAMEX>
And <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navigation Mixte</ENAMEX> has a huge hidden attraction. Payment by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Allianz</ENAMEX> for the insurance interests it has just bought will help swell the French concern's treasury to an estimated 11 billion francs.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paribas</ENAMEX> said it would publish details of its bid once authorities clear it. This is one of the first bids under new takeover rules aimed at encouraging open bids instead of gradual accumulation of large stakes.
Some financial sources said privately that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paribas</ENAMEX> blundered in failing to move sooner for the insurance and industrial group, bidding only after speculation had pushed up the price. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Francois-Poncet</ENAMEX> responded that his group initially intended to take only a minority stake, striking an alliance with current management. When notoriously independent-minded <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navigation Mixte</ENAMEX> Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Marc Fournier</ENAMEX> rejected <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paribas</ENAMEX>'s offer and began buying <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paribas</ENAMEX> shares in retaliation, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Francois-Poncet</ENAMEX> said, he felt obliged to bid for control. He told reporters he had information that Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Fournier</ENAMEX> was preparing to buy as much as 20% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paribas</ENAMEX>, up from less than 5% currently.
A bid against <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paribas</ENAMEX> couldn't be ruled out. <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">France</ENAMEX>'s second-largest government-owned insurance company, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Assurances Generales de France</ENAMEX>, has been building its own <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navigation Mixte</ENAMEX> stake, currently thought to be between 8% and 10%. Analysts said they don't think it is contemplating a takeover, however, and its officials couldn't be reached.
