<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lionel Corp.</ENAMEX>'s board unanimously rejected a tender offer of $8 a share, or $95.4 million, for as much as 90% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lionel</ENAMEX> by a group with a 9.9% stake in the toy retailer.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lionel</ENAMEX> also urged holders of its stock and debt not to tender their securities, saying it wants to remain independent to pursue its business strategy. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lionel</ENAMEX> also said the offer by <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Robert I.</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Toussie Limited Partnership</ENAMEX> is inadequate, and full of conditions that leave it ``subject to substantial uncertainty.''
In addition, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lionel</ENAMEX> began a lawsuit in federal District Court in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> seeking to enjoin the offer, alleging, among other things, violations of federal securities law and fraudulent manipulation of the market for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lionel</ENAMEX>'s securities.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Robert I. Toussie</ENAMEX>, general partner of the investment group, said the Lionel response reflected management's entrenched position, saying officials had failed to come up with a better alternative to his group's offer. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Toussie</ENAMEX> said he would respond to <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lionel</ENAMEX>'s suit after his lawyers review it.
