The sales are expected to raise more than 600 million Australian dollars (US$462.2 million), Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Skase</ENAMEX> said. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qintex Australia</ENAMEX> hasn't disclosed its borrowings, but analysts estimate the company's debt at A$1.2 billion.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Skase</ENAMEX> also said the restructuring plan calls for the merger of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Qintex Australia</ENAMEX> with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qintex Ltd.</ENAMEX>, which owns 55% of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Qintex Australia</ENAMEX>. He said the move will ``significantly reduce administrative and operating costs,'' but he didn't provide details of the merger.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Company</ENAMEX> officials said over the weekend that <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Qintex Australia</ENAMEX>'s bank creditors have become concerned about a barrage of bad news at the company, including a failed US$1.5 billion plan to buy <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MGM/UA Communications Co.</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Beverly Hills</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Calif.</ENAMEX>, movie and television production concern.
The company's latest moves were disclosed after the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Australian Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> suspended trading in shares of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qintex Australia</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qintex Ltd.</ENAMEX> because the companies hadn't answered an exchange inquiry about the extent of their loans, investments and deposits at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qintex Entertainment</ENAMEX>.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Skase</ENAMEX>'s statement was addressed to the stock exchange and appeared to be a response to the inquiry. It said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qintex Entertainment</ENAMEX> owes <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qintex Australia</ENAMEX> US$38.1/NNP million in loans not secured by specific assets. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qintex Australia</ENAMEX> also said it has an investment of A$83.3 million in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qintex Entertainment</ENAMEX> shares.
In the statement, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Skase</ENAMEX> said that on the basis of current interest rates in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Australia</ENAMEX>, the company's asset sales would reduce interest expense by about A$120 million a year in addition to eliminating certain liabilities.
Before its shares were suspended from trading, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qintex Australia</ENAMEX> plunged to 16 Australian cents (12 U.S. cents) a share yesterday from 33 Australian cents Friday. The shares traded at about A$1.50/NNP in March, when the plan to acquire <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MGM/UA</ENAMEX> was announced. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qintex Ltd.</ENAMEX> shares sank to A$1.50/NNP yesterday from A$3.05/NNP Friday.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Skase</ENAMEX>'s statement cited four recent problems that he said had cut group cash flow by more than A$200 million.
Qintex <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Australia</ENAMEX> hasn't yet reported results for the fiscal year ended July 31. In his statement, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Skase</ENAMEX> said preliminary accounts showed that group profit before interest, tax and depreciation ``will exceed A$170 million.'' He gave no further details.
Shareholders' funds as of July 31 were estimated at more than A$1 billion, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Skase</ENAMEX> said, compared with A$725 million a year earlier.
The company will make ``adequate provisions'' to cover costs of the dispute with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MGM</ENAMEX>\ and any loss from the investment in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qintex Entertainment</ENAMEX>, he said.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Skase</ENAMEX> also disclosed a disagreement among directors of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Qintex Australia</ENAMEX> over certain fees claimed by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qintex Group Management Services Pty.</ENAMEX>, a management-services concern in which <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qintex Australia</ENAMEX> executives have an interest.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qintex Australia</ENAMEX> paid the management company A$32.6 million in the latest fiscal year. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Skase</ENAMEX> said most of the money went to other parties for expenses such as rent and travel, but a smaller portion is owed to senior executives and others for management services.
Non-executive directors of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Qintex Australia</ENAMEX>, who must approve payments to the senior executives, balked at the amount. Two of the directors resigned, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Skase</ENAMEX> said, so the payments haven't yet been approved.
