<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ENFIELD Corp.</ENAMEX> said in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Toronto</ENAMEX> that it hopes to raise 56 million Canadian dollars (US$47.7 million) through a rights offering to shareholders. Under the offer, shareholders can purchase one <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Enfield</ENAMEX> share at C$6.27 for each five shares held. In <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Toronto Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> trading Friday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Enfield</ENAMEX> closed at C$6.75, down 37.5 cents. The holding company said the rights offering should reduce its C$171 million debt to ``more manageable levels'' before Dec. 31 and allow it to finance future investments with equity capital. At last report, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Enfield</ENAMEX> had about 44.5 million shares outstanding.
