<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Commodore International Ltd.</ENAMEX> said it will report a loss for the first quarter ended Sept. 30 because sales of personal computers for the home market remained weak in some major countries.
That will mark the second consecutive quarterly loss for Commodore and will raise additional questions about whether it can sustain the turnaround it had seemed to be engineering. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Commodore</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">West Chester</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Pa.</ENAMEX>, had said in August that it was consolidating manufacturing to cut costs and expected to be profitable in the fiscal first quarter.
Reflecting concerns about Commodore's outlook, its stock has plunged more than 50% since May, closing yesterday unchanged at $8.875 a share in composite trading on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX>. The price can be expected to erode further, because the loss estimate came after the market closed.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Commodore</ENAMEX> has assembled an experienced management team, it has persuaded many more dealers to carry its products and it has unleashed a slick advertising campaign. But those represent long-term strategies that probably won't succeed quickly, even if they turn out to be the right ones. In the meantime, the strategies will increase expenses.
The Commodore 64 and 128, mainly used for children's educational software and games, had surprised market researchers by continuing to produce strong sales even though other low-profit personal computers now operate several times as fast and have much more memory. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Commodore</ENAMEX> has said it expects sales to rebound, but market researchers have said that sales of the low-end products may finally be trailing off.
