<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IMA</ENAMEX> is a group that includes <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Boston Corp.</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pritzker</ENAMEX> family of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chicago</ENAMEX> through the leveraged buy-out fund Harry Gray <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Melvyn Klein & Partners</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Harry J. Gray</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Melvyn N. Klein</ENAMEX>, along with five other <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IMA</ENAMEX> designees, were named to join <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Medical</ENAMEX>'s 10-member board.
The completion of the merger agreement follows months of twists and turns. In January, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Medical</ENAMEX> brought in a new chief executive officer, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Richard A. Gilleland</ENAMEX>, 45, who will remain as chairman, president and chief executive. A few days later, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Medical</ENAMEX> announced sharply lower earnings, taking charges of $24 million for insurance reserves and canceled real estate leases.
In March, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Medical</ENAMEX> received a $24-a-share offer to take the company private from an investor group including large holder <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">M. Lee Pearce</ENAMEX>. It also was considering a restructuring to help boost the stock price. A group including several members of the the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Bass</ENAMEX> family of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Texas</ENAMEX> urged the company to take some steps to maximize shareholder value.
The following month, the company put itself up for sale. It received more offers, but the auction was surprisingly won by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IMA</ENAMEX>, which bid $28 a share and asked Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gilleland</ENAMEX> to stay on as an equity participant. He indicated that some assets might be sold off to service the debt.
Other new board members include <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John S. Harrison</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mark A. Adley</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Boston</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">James F. Lyons</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">William S. Goldberg</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Harold S. Handelsman</ENAMEX>.
