Director <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steve Kloves</ENAMEX> took a big gamble on Michelle <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Pfeiffer</ENAMEX>'s voice. He'd cast the actress, not exactly known for her way with a song, as the singing star of ``The Fabulous <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Baker</ENAMEX> Boys'' -- and he wanted her to carry the tunes herself. So the call went out for <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Sally Stevens</ENAMEX>.
Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stevens</ENAMEX> is what is known in the trade as a studio singer. The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Los Angeles</ENAMEX>-based artist estimates that she's performed on 200-300 film scores, among them ``The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Abyss,'' ``Ironweed'' and ``Klute.</ENAMEX>'' Her voice is audible on the incidental music for the TV series ``The Wonder Years,'' ``<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Miami</ENAMEX> Vice'' and ``<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Matlock</ENAMEX>.'' She has also worked frequently as a lyricist and as a vocal contractor, hiring and conducting choruses to sing movie title tracks.
``Most of what I do is very anonymous. But I was not brave enough to say I was willing to starve to death to be a recording artist. And doing studio work has been a wonderful way to make a living for a long, long time,'' said Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stevens</ENAMEX>, who for five years in a row received the Most Valuable Player award as a female studio vocalist from the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">National Academy of Recording Arts and Sciences</ENAMEX>, the organization that hands out the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Grammys</ENAMEX>.
Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stevens</ENAMEX>'s involvement with ``<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Baker</ENAMEX> Boys'' was the result of a long affiliation with the movie's composer, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dave Grusin</ENAMEX>. ``I had written lyrics with him and had sung for him in various films and contracted voices for him,'' she said. ``He knew my work and he called. It was really funny. When you approach a singer and tell her you don't want her to sing you always run the risk of offending. He said, `I don't know if this is going to be a compliment or an insult but...' Then he explained that <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Michelle</ENAMEX> was going to do this film and the role she was playing was that of a singer and they wanted very much for her to do her own singing if that was possible.'' At that point nobody, including Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Pfeiffer</ENAMEX> herself, was certain it would be possible.
She had, after all, sung in only one movie, ``<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Grease II</ENAMEX>,'' and the vocal demands of ``<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Baker</ENAMEX> Boys'' -- singing standards with only a piano backup -- were considerably more imposing -- and exposing -- than belting out a rock'n' roll score in concert with several other singers and instruments.
If Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Pfeiffer</ENAMEX> wasn't sure she was up to putting over numbers like ``The Look of Love,'' ``Ten Cents a Dance'' and ``My Funny <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Valentine</ENAMEX>,'' Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stevens</ENAMEX> wasn't sure she was up to showing the way. ``I had not done any coaching before,'' she said. ``I have produced vocal performances in the studio for professional singers. But I had never taken anyone from scratch before. I had to go a lot by instinct. I think <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dave</ENAMEX> thought that in my career I had done what the <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Susie Diamond</ENAMEX> character had done and that <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Michelle</ENAMEX>, consciously or unconsciously, would pick up some things.''
One of the first lessons took place at the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cinegrill</ENAMEX>, a lounge in the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hollywood Roosevelt Hotel</ENAMEX> where Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stevens</ENAMEX> brought Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Pfeiffer</ENAMEX> to hear a nightclub singer and soak up some atmosphere. ``Her instincts were wonderfully astute,'' remembered Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stevens</ENAMEX>, who is in her 40s. ``<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Michelle</ENAMEX> sensed an undercurrent of anger in the singer's performance. I think it's true with a lot of club singers who haven't had the recognition they feel they deserve or that they had hoped for.'' <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Accordingly</ENAMEX>, Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Pfeiffer</ENAMEX> incorporated anger into the development of her character.
As for Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Pfeiffer</ENAMEX>'s vocal development: For five or six weeks, Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stevens</ENAMEX> made daily two-hour visits to the actress's <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Santa Monica</ENAMEX> home armed with sheet music, and on occasion albums by <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">June Christy</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Blossom Dearie</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ella Fitzgerald</ENAMEX>, artists Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Pfeiffer</ENAMEX> hadn't paid much mind to in the past. ``I suggested Michelle listen to <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ella</ENAMEX>,'' said Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stevens</ENAMEX>. ``Nobody sings better, not that I wanted her to sound like Ella but there's a quality artists of that period had that we felt the character <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Susie</ENAMEX> might have listened to.''
From the way she sang in those early sessions, it seemed clear that <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Michelle</ENAMEX> had been listening not to Ella but to <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bob Dylan</ENAMEX>. ``There was a pronunciation and approach that seemed Dylan-influenced,'' recalled Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stevens</ENAMEX>. Vowels were swallowed, word endings were given short or no shrift. ``When we worked it almost became a joke with us that I was constantly reminding her to say the consonants as well as the vowels.'' To explain exactly what she meant, Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stevens</ENAMEX> and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Grusin</ENAMEX> went into a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Los Angeles</ENAMEX> studio and recorded a vocal\ demo of the songs being considered for inclusion in the movie so that Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Pfeiffer</ENAMEX> could learn the numbers, correct enunciation and all. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Grusin</ENAMEX> also made a demo tape with just piano to provide accompaniment when Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Pfeiffer</ENAMEX> practiced.
What Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Pfeiffer</ENAMEX> had going for her besides determination -- Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stevens</ENAMEX> recalled that the actress was up one night until 3 a.m. practicing ``My Funny <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Valentine</ENAMEX>'' -- was an airy alto, a nice breathy quality and intelligence. ``When we first started working it was a matter of finding a language we both understood,'' Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stevens</ENAMEX> said. ``I couldn't talk with her as I would with someone who had a lot of vocal training.''
So what Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stevens</ENAMEX> talked about was the importance of saying the words at the front of the mouth with the lips and the teeth. She urged Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Pfeiffer</ENAMEX> to get the feeling of a smile in her throat and to put a smile on her face to give the pitch and the sound a lift. She kept harping on the importance of overdoing the consonants and percussive endings like ``T'' and ``K.'' She talked about using language as a tool, about flirting with the lyrics. And please, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Michelle</ENAMEX>, when you sing the line in ``<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Makin' Whoopee</ENAMEX>,'' about another sunny, funny honeymoon, don't say ``funn-ih,'' the way <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dylan</ENAMEX> would. Say ``funn-eeee.'' Put the clean vowel ending on it. And <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Michelle</ENAMEX>, must you continue to smoke two packs of cigarettes a day?
``It was a process of discovery,'' said Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stevens</ENAMEX>, who admitted she sometimes felt a bit like <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Henry Higgins</ENAMEX>. ``What I tried to do was take the sparks of the positive stuff and fan them. I tried not to do much `don't do this, don't do that.'''
There was another layer to the coaching: Helping Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Pfeiffer</ENAMEX> sing a song the way <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Susie Diamond</ENAMEX> would sing it. Not brilliantly, because, after all, this was a performer who was collecting paychecks from lounges at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hiltons</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Holiday Inns</ENAMEX>, but creditably and with the air of someone for whom ``Ten Cents a Dance'' was more than a bit autobiographical. ``It was an exercise of blending <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Michelle</ENAMEX>'s singing with <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Susie</ENAMEX>'s singing,'' explained Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stevens</ENAMEX>. ``If `Dangerous <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Liaisons</ENAMEX>' had been a musical she would have had to give a different vocal performance because she was a different character in that movie.''
Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Pfeiffer</ENAMEX>'s vocal performance in ``<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Baker</ENAMEX> Boys'' -- recorded for posterity on the soundtrack album (<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">GRP</ENAMEX>) -- is such that after her first number, ``More Than You Know,'' viewers begin murmuring to each other ``Is that really her singing? That isn't really her.'' ``I can swear that every single note in that movie was hers,'' averred Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stevens</ENAMEX>, who had begun kidding her protege that she was going to get a `<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Tonight Show</ENAMEX>' booking. ``Seeing Michelle up there,'' she added, ``was like watching myself or my daughter. I was so nervous. I wanted her to be so good. I didn't want to feel as if I'd let her down.''
Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kaufman</ENAMEX> is a free-lance writer based in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>.
