Four workers at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GTE Corp.</ENAMEX>'s headquarters have been diagnosed as having hepatitis, and city health officials are investigating whether a cafeteria worker may have exposed hundreds of other <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GTE</ENAMEX> employees to the viral infection, company and city officials said.
Hepatitis A, considered the least dangerous strain of the virus, has been confirmed in at least one <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GTE</ENAMEX> employee, company and city officials said.
``From a public health point of view we're relieved because hepatitis A is rarely life-threatening,'' said Dr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Frank Provato</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GTE</ENAMEX>'s medical director. ``It's a double-edged sword though, because it is also the most contagious kind of hepatitis.''
The company has begun offering shots of gamma globulin, which will diminish the flu-like symptoms of hepatitis A, in anyone who has contracted the disease, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mattausch</ENAMEX> said.
``We're strongly recommending that anyone who has eaten in the cafeteria this month have the shot,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mattausch</ENAMEX> added, ``and that means virtually everyone who works here.
