Cast as <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Violetta Valery</ENAMEX> in a new production of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Verdi</ENAMEX>'s ``<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">La Traviata</ENAMEX>,'' Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gruberova</ENAMEX> last week did many things nicely and others not so well. It isn't every day that we hear a Violetta who can sing the first act's high-flying music with all the little notes perfectly pitched and neatly stitched together. Never once did she gasp for air or mop her brow. She was as cool as a cucumber. But as you may know, things are not going well for <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Violetta</ENAMEX>. There are times when she must show a little emotion. She has TB, after all, and a weak-kneed lover; and though a successful courtesan, she is just about overdrawn at the bank.
Worse, her walls move all the time -- at least in this production. Just when Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gruberova</ENAMEX> sat down away from her guests to cough in private, her salon began sliding around the stage; her country hideaway also has a very active set of drapes. Hold on to those funny braids you wanted to caution her as the sets started to roll around once more. This is the most moving ``Traviata'' I've ever seen.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Normally</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Violetta</ENAMEX> can go about her business without wondering whether she is moving as gracefully as the scenery. But this is a production designed and directed by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Franco Zeffirelli</ENAMEX> and paid for by <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Sybil Harrington</ENAMEX>, who has no need to count her pennies, unlike <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Violetta</ENAMEX>, down to 20 louis at the opera's end. Seeing all those millions in action, I was just so relieved that Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gruberova</ENAMEX>, gawky thing that she is, didn't accidentally smother herself in a drape.
Large and lavish, ``Traviata'' is another addition to the Met's growing stock of cast-proof productions mostly by Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Zeffirelli</ENAMEX>. They have a life of their own and can be counted on to look good and perform whenever a cast isn't up to either. If a strike ever hits the Met, the company can still sell tickets to his ``Boheme'' and ``Turandot'' and boom out recordings (of another era). Last week's discerning audience gave a bigger hand to a greenhouse than to the tenor <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Neil Shicoff</ENAMEX>, who sang an aria inside it. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Inexplicably</ENAMEX> costumed as a rabbinical student, tottering around on lifts, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Shicoff</ENAMEX> hardly seemed the fellow to catch a fancy cocotte's eye. I wish he could wear lifts in his voice. Not nearly in his best form, the tenor made dullish sounds along with his usual clumsy hand gestures. Maybe Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Z.</ENAMEX> was too busy taming his set to work with his naturally ungainly <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Alfredo</ENAMEX>. Or is it that Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Z.</ENAMEX> is getting a little tired of ``Traviata''? This is the same production already seen in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Paris</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Florence</ENAMEX>, and its scenic ideas echo the movie he made with <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Placido Domingo</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Teresa Stratas</ENAMEX>. Decades earlier, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Maria Callas</ENAMEX> sang the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dallas</ENAMEX> staging that introduced the flashback idea. In an invention that drives <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Verdi</ENAMEX> purists bananas, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Violetta</ENAMEX> lies dying in bed during the prelude, rising deliriously when then she remembers the great parties she used to throw. The entire opera is her dream.
We know <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Verdi</ENAMEX>'s own contribution was mighty impressive since the operatic ``Libera me'' was reworked for the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Manzoni Requiem</ENAMEX>, of which he wrote every note himself having learned his lesson. The surprising discovery of the evening at Fisher was the high standard achieved by some of his now-obscure colleagues, notably <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Raimondo Boucheron</ENAMEX>. His melodious ``Confutatis'' was smoothly sung by bass <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Brian Matthews</ENAMEX>. Also, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Teodulo Mabellini</ENAMEX>'s ``Lux aeterna'' was intriguingly scored and splendidly put across by Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rilling</ENAMEX>. He brought along his <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Stuttgart</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Gaechinger Kantorei</ENAMEX> chorus, and even better, the Czech soprano <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gabriela Benackova</ENAMEX>. She was in her most radiant, expressive voice. Maybe she could step across the plaza to the Met -- where she has still to make her debut -- and help out her Czech compatriot by singing the slow parts of ``Traviata.''
Says director <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">George Miller</ENAMEX> (``Mad <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Max</ENAMEX>''): ``I think the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tokyo</ENAMEX> festival may become known as a major attraction for young directors because of the money as well as the recognition.''
There are drawbacks. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Vincent Tolentino</ENAMEX>, a correspondent for the French magazine Telerama, says of the recently ended <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tokyo</ENAMEX> festival: ``No one makes deals... and most of the films have been seen before at other festivals.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Belgium</ENAMEX> decided that investors who demand the delivery of their securities when they buy shares or domestic bonds will have to pay an additional 100 Belgian francs (about $2.60) for each transaction, bringing the total fee to 200 francs. While no figures exist, it is thought that many small investors in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Belgium</ENAMEX> store securities privately, in some cases to avoid paying high inheritance taxes. The law could redound to the advantage of brokers and banks, who incur high administrative costs to deliver securities to investors.
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX> is considering giving aid to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hungary</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Poland</ENAMEX> to support their recent political reforms, a spokesman for the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Foreign Ministry</ENAMEX> said. ``This is the first time, if we decide to do so, for <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX> to extend aid of this kind to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Eastern European</ENAMEX> countries,'' the spokesman said. He said Prime Minister <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Toshiki Kaifu</ENAMEX> also is studying the possibility of a visit to the two <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Eastern bloc</ENAMEX> nations and to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Western Europe</ENAMEX> next January.
Drugs were a major issue in two days of talks between French President <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Francois Mitterrand</ENAMEX> and Spanish Prime Minister <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Felipe Gonzalez</ENAMEX>. ``I demand the utmost severity in the fight against drug traffickers,'' President <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mitterrand</ENAMEX> said after the meeting in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Valladolid</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Spain</ENAMEX>. He added: ``<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Banks</ENAMEX> must open their books.'' The leaders' talks coincided with a meeting in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Madrid</ENAMEX> of anti-drug experts from the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">France</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Italy</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Spain</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Peru</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Bolivia</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Colombia</ENAMEX>. That conference, which began yesterday, was expected to cover such matters as police training and extradition agreements, Spanish officials said.
Three Soviet government officials -- the ministers of railroads, of foreign economic relations and of heavy-machine building -- will visit Tehran next month for talks, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Iran</ENAMEX>'s official news agency reported. Under an agreement signed last June, the Soviets will help <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Iran</ENAMEX> in oil exploration and other areas in return for exports of Iranian natural gas. And in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Paris</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mahmoud Vaezi</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Iran</ENAMEX>'s vice minister of foreign affairs, began a five-day visit to discuss such matters as compensation to French enterprises for contracts broken by the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Khomeini</ENAMEX> regime.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hector Castaneda Jimenez</ENAMEX>, chief prosecutor at the Attorney <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">General's Office</ENAMEX>, said that an estimated $82.8 million in government property and unpaid taxes have been recovered in the campaign to root out official corruption.
``The rest will probably not be recoverable either because the statute of limitations expired or because many prefer to spend additional time in jail rather than return the money,'' the prosecutor said.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Nations</ENAMEX>, which is distributing farm tools to returning refugees in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Namibia</ENAMEX>, is rethinking a plan to hand out machetes because of the tense political climate during preparations for independence from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">South Africa</ENAMEX>. ``The decision to distribute machetes at this time, which could be used as weapons, is under review,'' said a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.N.</ENAMEX> spokesman.... Sources close to the family of Pakistani Prime Minister <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Benazir Bhutto</ENAMEX> said she is expecting a second child, probably early next year.
