For more than a decade, banks have been pressing <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Congress</ENAMEX> and banking regulators for expanded powers to act like securities firms in playing Wall Street's lucrative takeover game, from giving mergers advice all the way to selling and trading high-yield junk bonds.
Those expanded powers reached their zenith in July when <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bankers Trust New York Corp.</ENAMEX> provided mergers advice, an equity investment and bank loans for the $3.65 billion leveraged buy-out of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Northwest Airlines</ENAMEX> parent <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NWA Inc.</ENAMEX>
One of the major selling points used by <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Los Angeles</ENAMEX> financier <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Alfred Checchi</ENAMEX> in getting the takeover approved was that the deal didn't include any junk bonds. That was seen as an advantage in lobbying airline employees and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Washington</ENAMEX> regulators for approval of the contested takeover. All $3.35 billion in debt for the deal was supplied by banks.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Charles Nathan</ENAMEX>, co-head of mergers and acquisitions at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Salomon Brothers Inc.</ENAMEX>, says it is natural for banks to try to expand beyond their bread-and-butter business of providing senior debt for buy-outs. But the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> collapse, he says, ``may tell you it's not going to work that easily.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">David Batchelder</ENAMEX>, a mergers adviser in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">La Jolla</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Calif.</ENAMEX>, who aided <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Los Angeles</ENAMEX> investor <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Marvin Davis</ENAMEX> on the bids which put both <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NWA</ENAMEX> in play as takeover candidates this year, says that banks have been ``preparing to play a larger and larger role in acquisition financing.''
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Batchelder</ENAMEX> says that in the past, banks would normally have loaned 65% of a total buy-out price, with the loans secured by the target company's assets. Another 20% of the borrowed funds would come from the sale to investors of junk bonds, which offer less security and typically carry higher yields than bank loans. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Checchi</ENAMEX>'s purchase of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NWA</ENAMEX>, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Batchelder</ENAMEX> notes, ``was probably the most aggressive to date,'' with bank debt at 85% of the purchase price.
But Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Batchelder</ENAMEX> says that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Citicorp</ENAMEX>'s ``failure to deliver'' on its promise to raise the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> bank debt for a labor-management buy-out group ``is very distressing to potential users of a `highly-confident' letter from commercial banks.'' His client, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Davis</ENAMEX>, used just such a letter from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Citicorp</ENAMEX> in pursuing <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX>; <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Citicorp</ENAMEX> later agreed to work with a competing <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> buy-out group.
Executives of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Citicorp</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chase Manhattan</ENAMEX> declined to comment on either the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> situation, or on the changing nature of banks' role in financing takeovers.
In the wake of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Campeau</ENAMEX>'s problems, prices of junk bonds tumbled, throwing into doubt the ability of corporate acquirers to finance large takeovers with the help of junk bond sales.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mark Solow</ENAMEX>, senior managing director at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Manufacturers Hanover Trust Co.</ENAMEX>, says the falloff in junk bonds may yet open new business opportunities to banks in structuring takeovers. But he warns that banks will have ``to have enough discipline'' not to make loans that are too risky.
In fact, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Manufacturers Hanover</ENAMEX> said in its third-quarter earnings report that fees from syndicating loans to other banks dropped 48%, to $21 million. ``We didn't take part in a lot of deals because their credit quality was poor,'' says a bank spokesman.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">James B. Lee</ENAMEX>, head of syndications and private placements at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chemical Banking Corp.</ENAMEX>, said he believes banks can still make a credible offer of one-stop shopping for takeover finance. As evidence, he cites yesterday's arrangement for the final financing of a $3 billion bid for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Medical International Inc.</ENAMEX> in which <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chemical</ENAMEX> served as both the lead bank and an equity investor.
Beyond the current weakness in the junk bond market, banks have another advantage over investment banks in financing contested takeovers. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Arthur Fleischer Jr.</ENAMEX>, a takeover lawyer at Fried <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Frank Harris Shriver & Jacobson</ENAMEX>, notes that ``a political and emotional bias'' has developed against junk bonds.
One hostile bidder who deliberately avoided using junk bonds was <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paramount Communications Inc.</ENAMEX> in its initial offer to acquire <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Time Inc.</ENAMEX> for $10.7 billion, or $175 a share. A <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paramount</ENAMEX> spokesman says that decision was based on the financial, not political, drawbacks of junk bonds.
But some observers believe <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paramount</ENAMEX> Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Martin Davis</ENAMEX> wanted to avoid the possible taint of being perceived as a corporate raider in his controversial bid for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Time.</ENAMEX> In the end, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Davis</ENAMEX> used junk bonds so that he could raise <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paramount</ENAMEX>'s bid to $200 a share. Some Monday-morning quarterbacks said the initial lower bid, without junk bonds, was a factor in his losing the company. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Time</ENAMEX> eluded <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paramount</ENAMEX> by acquiring <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner Communications Inc.</ENAMEX>
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Takanori Mizuno</ENAMEX>, chief economist of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Institute for Financial Affairs Inc.</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tokyo</ENAMEX> research center on finance and economics, says, ``The junk bond market became very jittery, and there's a fear of a coming recession and the possible bankruptcy of LBO companies. These factors have combined to deter LBO lending by Japanese banks''. provided solely by banks, not high-yield junk
