<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Moody's Investors Service Inc.</ENAMEX> said it downgraded about $970 million of senior debt of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Arkla Inc.</ENAMEX> in response to the company's increased financial leverage, related primarily to restructuring plans that include taking a $189 million charge.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Moody</ENAMEX>'s contends the natural gas company's debt has risen principally because of large prepayments to producers to settle take-or-pay claims, and due to aggressive efforts to increase market opportunities through acquisitions, which were partially financed by debt.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Arkla</ENAMEX> is based in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Shreveport</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">La.</ENAMEX>
Downgraded by the ratings concern are <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Arkla</ENAMEX>'s first mortgage bonds to single-A-3 from single-A-2; notes to single-A-3 from single-A-2; debentures to single-A-3 from single-A-2; shelf registration to a preliminary rating of single-A-3 from a preliminary rating of single-A-2; convertible preferred stock to Baa-1 from single-A-3, and the concern's rating for commercial paper to Prime-2 from Prime-1. Also downgraded were the company's <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Entex Inc.</ENAMEX> unit's first mortgage bonds to single-A-3 from single-A-2 and debentures to single-A-3 from single-A-2. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Arkla</ENAMEX> acquired Entex in 1988.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Moody's</ENAMEX> said the rating action takes into account Arkla's plan for an initial public offering of as much as 18% of the common stock of its oil and gas exploration and development subsidiary, proceeds of which will be used to repay debt.
