<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Credit Lyonnais S.A.</ENAMEX> said it agreed to acquire slightly more than 50% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Thomson-CSF Finance S.A.</ENAMEX> in an asset swap between the two French state-controlled groups.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">bank</ENAMEX> said it will acquire the stake in the finance unit of defense and electronics group <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Thomson-CSF S.A.</ENAMEX> in exchange for almost 14% of its own capital. No value was given for the transaction, which will create the sort of financial-industrial tandem common in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">West Germany</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX>.
Although <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Thomson</ENAMEX>'s banking activities will become a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Credit Lyonnais</ENAMEX> subsidiary, they are to remain a separate entity and, according to sources, will continue to handle <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Thomson</ENAMEX>'s own international financing needs. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Thomson-CSF Finance</ENAMEX>, the largest finance unit of any French industrial company, also will gain access to products offered by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Credit Lyonnais</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">France</ENAMEX>'s secondbiggest commercial bank in terms of assets, behind <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Banque Nationale de Paris</ENAMEX>.
The accord will strengthen <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Credit Lyonnais</ENAMEX>'s corporate financial affairs because of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Thomson-CSF Finance</ENAMEX>'s expertise in using hedging and treasury-management products.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Thomson-CSF Finance</ENAMEX> posted profit of 1.8 billion francs ($288.9 million) in 1988, an official said. He added that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Thomson</ENAMEX> consolidated earnings won't be affected by the accord. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Credit Lyonnais</ENAMEX> reported 1988 consolidated profit of 2.06 billion francs after payments to minority interests.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Thomson</ENAMEX> common shares and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Credit Lyonnais</ENAMEX> non-voting stock were suspended yesterday before the announcement at their respective Wednesday closing prices of 194.50 francs ($31.22) and 642 francs ($103.05) each. They were expected to resume trading today.
