The approval, which had been expected, permits <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">West Germany</ENAMEX>'s second-largest bank to acquire shares of the French investment bank.
In a first step, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dresdner Bank</ENAMEX> will buy 32.99% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">BIP</ENAMEX> for 1,015 French francs ($162) a share, or 528 million francs ($84.7 million). <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dresdner Bank</ENAMEX> said it will also buy all shares tendered by shareholders on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paris Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> at the same price from today through Nov. 17. In addition, the bank has an option to buy a 30.84% stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">BIP</ENAMEX> from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Societe Generale</ENAMEX> after Jan. 1, 1990 at 1,015 francs a share.
