<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Amdura Corp.</ENAMEX> said its bank group, led by <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chicago</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Continental Bank</ENAMEX>, agreed to extend its $40 million bridge loan until March 31, 1990, and gave it a new $30 million credit line.
Under terms of the loan agreement, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Amdura</ENAMEX> said it will omit the next quarterly dividends on its Series A, B, C and D preferred shares, which are due Nov. 15. Since the preferred stock is cumulative, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Amdura</ENAMEX> said it will pay all omitted dividends, which range from $1.19 to $4.88 a share, when debt-reduction requirements have been  met.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Amdura</ENAMEX>'s bridge loan, part of the financing for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Amdura</ENAMEX>'s acquisition of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coastamerica</ENAMEX> in December 1988, was to come due next Friday. The company's new management, which took control of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Amdura</ENAMEX>'s board after a consent solicitation last month, wanted to extend the loan while it tries to sell two units. Proceeds from those sales will be used to reduce debt.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Amdura</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Denver</ENAMEX> hardware and automotive distributor, said the new credit agreement will provide the working capital needed to meet ongoing requirements.
