<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dun & Bradstreet Corp.</ENAMEX> posted a 15% rise in third-quarter earnings.
But revenue declined more than 2%, reflecting in part a continuing drop in sales of credit services in the wake of controversy over the company's sales practices. The information company also cited the stronger dollar, the sale last year of its former <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Official Airline Guides</ENAMEX> unit and other factors.
In composite trading on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dun & Bradstreet</ENAMEX> closed yesterday at $53.75, down 25 cents a share.
Analysts said the results were as expected, but several added that the earnings masked underlying weaknesses in several businesses. ``The quality of earnings wasn't as high as I expected,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Eric Philo</ENAMEX>, an analyst for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Goldman, Sachs & Co.</ENAMEX>
For example, he noted, operating profit was weaker than he had anticipated, but nonoperating earnings of $14.6 million and a lower tax rate helped boost net income.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dun & Bradstreet</ENAMEX> said operating earnings rose 8%, excluding the sale of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Official Airline</ENAMEX> Guides.
Third-quarter sales of U.S. credit services were ``disappointingly below sales'' of a year earlier, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dun & Bradstreet</ENAMEX> said. As previously reported, those sales have been declining this year in the wake of allegations that the company engaged in unfair sales practices that encouraged customers to overpurchase services. The company has denied the allegations but has negotiated a proposed $18 million settlement of related lawsuits. Analysts predict the sales impact will linger. ``There isn't much question there will continue to be a ripple effect,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John Reidy</ENAMEX>, an analyst with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Drexel Burnham Lambert Inc.</ENAMEX>
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dun & Bradstreet</ENAMEX> noted that price competition in its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nielsen Marketing Research</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nielsen Clearing House</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Donnelley Marketing</ENAMEX> businesses also restrained revenue growth. It cited cyclical conditions in its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Moody's Investors Service Inc.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">D&B Plan Services</ENAMEX> units.
