The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FTC</ENAMEX> ordered the companies not to use rating bureaus in those six states. The commission order named the following companies: <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ticor Title Insurance Co.</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">California</ENAMEX>, a unit of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Los Angeles</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ticor</ENAMEX>; <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chicago Title Insurance Co.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Safeco Title Insurance Co.</ENAMEX>, units of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chicago Title & Trust Co.</ENAMEX>; <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lawyers Title Insurance Corp.</ENAMEX>, a unit of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Richmond</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Va.</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Universal Corp.</ENAMEX>; and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Stewart Title Guaranty Co.</ENAMEX>, a unit of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Houston</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Stewart Information Services Corp.</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chicago Title & Trust</ENAMEX> acquired <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Safeco</ENAMEX> in 1987 and changed the unit's name to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Security Union Title Insurance Co.</ENAMEX>
A lawyer for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lawyers</ENAMEX> Title said that, because the named companies no longer use the type of cooperative rating bureaus attacked by the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FTC</ENAMEX>, the commission's order won't have much practical impact. Officials for the other named companies didn't return telephone calls seeking comment.
