<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qintex Entertainment</ENAMEX> also said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">David Evans</ENAMEX>, its president and chief executive, and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Roger Kimmel</ENAMEX>, a director, both resigned. Neither could be reached for comment.
Earlier this month, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qintex Australia</ENAMEX>'s $1.5 billion agreement to acquire <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MGM/UA Communications Co.</ENAMEX> collapsed because of a dispute over a $50 million letter of credit the Australian operator of television stations and resorts was to have supplied as security in the transaction. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Evans</ENAMEX> had been the de facto head of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MGM/UA</ENAMEX> for months.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qintex Entertainment</ENAMEX>, a producer and distributor of television programs most noted for its co-production of the hit miniseries ``<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lonesome Dove</ENAMEX>,'' said it filed for Chapter 11 protection after <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qintex Australia</ENAMEX> failed to provide it with $5.9 million owed to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MCA Inc.</ENAMEX> in connection with the distribution of ``The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New Leave</ENAMEX> It to Beaver Show.''
After the announcement of the bankruptcy filing, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qintex Entertainment</ENAMEX> stock sank $2.625 in over-the-counter trading to close at $1.50 on heavy volume of more than 1.4 million shares. The stock traded as high as $10 this past summer.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jonathan Lloyd</ENAMEX>, executive vice president and chief financial officer of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qintex Entertainment</ENAMEX>, said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qintex Entertainment</ENAMEX> was forced to file for protection to avoid going into default under its agreement with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MCA</ENAMEX>. The $5.9 million payment was due Oct. 1 and the deadline for default was Oct. 19. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lloyd</ENAMEX> said if <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qintex</ENAMEX> had defaulted it could have been required to repay $92 million in debt under its loan agreements. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MCA</ENAMEX> on Friday said that as a result of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qintex</ENAMEX>'s failure to make the required payment it was terminating the distribution agreement on ``The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New Leave</ENAMEX> It to Beaver'' as well as other <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MCA</ENAMEX> properties.
Qintex <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Australia</ENAMEX> was ``saying as recently as last weekend that they would take care of the situation. They continued to represent that to the board,'' said Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lloyd</ENAMEX>. ``We were reassured they would stand behind the company.''
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lloyd</ENAMEX> said both <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qintex Entertainment</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qintex Australia</ENAMEX> had attempted to secure a loan that would allow the company to make the $5.9 million payment but the request was turned down by an unidentified lender on Oct. 14. At that point, he said, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Qintex Australia</ENAMEX> stated it would ``endeavor to arrange'' the financing.
However a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qintex Australia</ENAMEX> spokesman said his firm had never ``promised or guaranteed'' to make the payment. In a prepared statement from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Australia</ENAMEX>, the company also said that, following the breakdown of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MGM</ENAMEX> talks, it ``had been re-evaluating its position as a significant shareholder and a substantial creditor of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qintex Entertainment</ENAMEX>'' and had ``resolved to minimize the degree of further loans to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qintex Entertainment</ENAMEX> in excess of that previously made.''
The report of the bankruptcy filing stunned <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hollywood</ENAMEX> executives and investors. ``It's a shocker,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Joseph Di Lillo</ENAMEX>, chairman of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Drake Capital Securities</ENAMEX>, a brokerage firm that has an investment in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qintex Entertainment</ENAMEX>. Qintex <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Australia</ENAMEX> was ``going to pay more than $1 billion for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MGM</ENAMEX>\ and then they couldn't come up with the far smaller sum of $5.9 million.''
The announcement seemed to further damp prospects that talks between <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Qintex Australia</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MGM/UA</ENAMEX> might be revived. It's understood that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MGM/UA</ENAMEX> recently contacted <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rupert Murdoch</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">News Corp.</ENAMEX>, which made two failed bids for the movie studio, to see if the company was still interested. However, ``we aren't currently doing anything. It isn't a current topic of conversation at the company,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Barry Diller</ENAMEX>, chairman and chief executive officer of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Fox Inc.</ENAMEX> unit of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">News Corp.</ENAMEX>
