<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Control Data Corp.</ENAMEX>, which just months ago was hemorrhaging financially, thinks it will be healthy enough soon to consider repurchasing public debt.
Moreover, the company, whose go-it-alone approach nearly proved fatal, now sees alliances with others as the way back to prosperity in what it calls ``the data solutions'' business.
``I'm not saying everything is hunky-dory, but we have completed the transition,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Robert M. Price</ENAMEX>, chairman and chief executive, said in an interview. ``Transition'' is a reference to the company's five-year restructuring effort. During that time, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Control Data</ENAMEX> had losses of more than $1 billion.
``We'd like to continue to reduce debt,'' President <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lawrence Perlman</ENAMEX> said. Noting that the company is offering to buy back $154.2 million in senior notes paying 12 3/4%, he said the response will help determine future debt-reduction efforts. The offer was automatically triggered by the recent sale of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Control Data</ENAMEX>'s Imprimis disk-drive business to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Seagate Technology Inc.</ENAMEX>
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Perlman</ENAMEX>, who is also acting chief financial officer and the odds-on favorite to become the next chief executive, said the company is achieving ``modest positive cash flow from operations, and we expect that to continue into 1990.''
Loan covenants require that the company achieve specified levels of operating earnings and meet a rolling four-quarter profitability test. Last week <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Control Data</ENAMEX> reported third-quarter earnings of $9.8 million, or 23 cents a share, on revenue of $763 million. Through the first nine months, the company had a loss of $484 million, largely reflecting the closing of its supercomputer unit.
While a few assets are still being shopped -- including the sports and entertainment ticketing portion of the company's <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ticketron</ENAMEX> unit -- Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Price</ENAMEX> said future restructuring would be a question of strategy. ``We don't need the cash.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ticketron</ENAMEX>'s automated wagering business, which operates lotteries in a half dozen states, is not for sale, the company said. Rather, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Perlman</ENAMEX> said, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Control Data</ENAMEX> intends to bid for the coming <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Minnesota</ENAMEX> lottery contract and is seeking new applications for the technology overseas, where ``there is great interest in games of skill.'' He wouldn't elaborate.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Control Data</ENAMEX>'s semiconductor business, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">VTC Inc.</ENAMEX>, continues to lose money, the executives acknowledged, but they said they consider some of the technology vital to national defense and so are reluctant to dispose of it.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">James E. Ousley</ENAMEX>, computer products group president, said such arrangements could help slash <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Control Data</ENAMEX>'s computer research and development costs in half by the end of 1990. He disclosed that before <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Control Data</ENAMEX> scrapped its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ETA Systems Inc.</ENAMEX> supercomputer business this past spring, those costs were running at nearly 35% of group revenue. At the same time four of six design projects were spiked, he said.
Asked how the company hopes to expand its computer hardware business, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ousley</ENAMEX> said it sees good opportunities in systems integration. ``We think we're getting only 10% of the integration dollars our customers are spending,'' he said. ``We're in environments that are going to spend a lot of money on that.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Control Data</ENAMEX> mainframes are designed for numerically intensive computing users, such as the scientific, engineering and academic communities. Utilities management is a major commercial niche.
Reviewing the company's scrape with disaster, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Price</ENAMEX> conceded it had tried to do too much on its own. ``Absolutely,'' he said.
But while its stock is selling at about half <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Control Data</ENAMEX>'s estimated breakup value, neither <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Messrs</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Perlman</ENAMEX> nor <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Price</ENAMEX> said he spends much time considering the possibility of a hostile takeover. ``We've been listed as a candidate for so long it's not worth worrying about,'' said Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Price</ENAMEX>.
