NEW ENGLAND <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CRITICAL CARE Inc.</ENAMEX> offered $35 million in convertible subordinated debentures through <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Morgan Stanley & Co.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Prudential-Bache Capital Funding.</ENAMEX> The debentures, due in 2014, have a coupon of 7 3/4%, payable semiannually. The debentures may be converted into common stock of the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Westborough</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mass.</ENAMEX>, home health care concern at $52.50 a share. Proceeds will be used for working capital and general corporate purposes, including expansion of the company's operations.
