<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Montedison S.p. A.</ENAMEX> definitively agreed to buy all of the publicly held shares of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Erbamont N.V.</ENAMEX> for $37 each.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Montedison</ENAMEX> now owns about 72% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Erbamont</ENAMEX>'s shares outstanding.
The companies said the accord was unanimously approved by a special committee of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Erbamont</ENAMEX> directors unaffiliated with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Montedison</ENAMEX>.
Under the pact, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Montedision</ENAMEX> will make a $37-a-share tender offer for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Erbamont</ENAMEX> stock outstanding. The tender offer will be followed by the sale of all of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Erbamont</ENAMEX>'s assets, subject to all of its liabilities, to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Montedison</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Erbamont</ENAMEX> will then be liquidated, with any remaining <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Erbamont</ENAMEX> holders receiving a distribution of $37 a share.
The companies said the transaction is being structured this way because the laws of the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Netherlands</ENAMEX> Antilles, under which <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Erbamont</ENAMEX> is organized, don't provide for merger transactions.
