Insiders have been selling shares in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dun & Bradstreet Corp.</ENAMEX>, the huge credit-information concern.
The stock, in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> composite trading yesterday, closed at $51.75, up 62.5 cents, well below the $56.13 to $60 a share the insiders received for their shares. Much of the recent slide in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dun & Bradstreet</ENAMEX>'s stock came late last week, after negative comments by analysts at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merrill Lynch & Co.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Goldman, Sachs & Co.</ENAMEX>
A company spokesman declined to comment and said that the officials who sold shares wouldn't comment.
One of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dun & Bradstreet</ENAMEX>'s chief businesses is compiling reports that rate the credit-worthiness of millions of American companies. It also owns <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Moody's Investors Service</ENAMEX>, which assigns credit-ratings to bonds and preferred stock; <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">A.C. Nielsen</ENAMEX>, known for its data on television-viewing patterns, and Yellow-pages publisher <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Donnelley</ENAMEX>.
Last March, this newspaper reported on widespread allegations that the company misled many customers into purchasing more credit-data services than needed. In June, the company agreed to settle for $18 million several lawsuits related to its sales practices, without admitting or denying the charges. An investigation by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.S. Postal inspectors</ENAMEX> is continuing.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John C. Holt</ENAMEX>, an executive vice president and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dun & Bradstreet</ENAMEX> director, sold 10,000 shares on Aug. 31 for $588,800, filings show. He retains 9,232 shares.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">William H.J. Buchanan</ENAMEX>, the firm's secretary and associate general counsel, sold 7,000 shares in two separate sales in September for $406,000. The shares represented 66% of his <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dun & Bradstreet</ENAMEX> holdings, according to the company.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dun & Bradstreet</ENAMEX>'s stock price began its recent spiral downward last Wednesday, when the company reported third-quarter results. Net income rose to 83 cents a share from 72 cents a share the year-earlier period. But analysts focused more on the drop in revenue, to $1.04 billion from $1.07 billion, reflecting in part a continuing drop in sales of the controversial credit-reporting services.
Last Thursday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merrill Lynch</ENAMEX> securities analyst <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peter Falco</ENAMEX> downgraded his investment rating on the firm, according to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones Professional Investors Report</ENAMEX>, citing a slowdown in the credit-reporting business. He cut his rating to a short-term hold from above-average performer and reduced his 1990 earnings estimate. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Falco</ENAMEX> continues to rank the stock a longterm buy. The stock slid $1.875 on more than four times average daily volume.
The stock received another blow on Friday, when <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Goldman Sachs</ENAMEX> analyst <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Eric Philo</ENAMEX> advised that investors with short-term horizons should avoid <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dun & Bradstreet</ENAMEX> stock because it is unlikely to outperform the market. The stock fell 75 cents.
Insider selling is not unusual at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dun & Bradstreet</ENAMEX>; in fact, the recent pace of selling is just about average for the company, according to figures compiled by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Invest</ENAMEX>\, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">North Miami</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Fla.</ENAMEX>, firm that specializes in tracking and analyzing <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">SEC</ENAMEX> insider filings.
But previous sales have often been sales of shares purchased through the exercise of stock options and sold six months later, as soon as allowed, said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Robert Gabele</ENAMEX>, president of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Invest</ENAMEX>\. The most recent sales don't appear to be option-related, he said.
TASTY PROFITS: <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Michael A. Miles</ENAMEX>, chief executive officer of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Philip Morris Cos.</ENAMEX>' Kraft <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">General Foods</ENAMEX> unit, bought 6,000 shares of the company on Sept. 22 for $157 each. The $942,000 purchase raised his holdings to 74,000 shares.
A spokesman for Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Miles</ENAMEX> said he bought the shares because he felt they were ``a good investment.'' The executive made his purchases shortly before being named to his current chief executive officer's position; formerly he was Kraft <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">General Foods</ENAMEX>' chief operating officer.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">SHEDDING GLITTER</ENAMEX>: Two directors of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pegasus Gold Inc.</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Spokane</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Wash.</ENAMEX>, precious-metals mining firm, sold most of their holdings in the company Aug. 31. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John J. Crabb</ENAMEX> sold 4,500 shares for $11.13 each, leaving himself with a stake of 500 shares. He received $50,085. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peter Kutney</ENAMEX> sold 5,000 shares, all of his holdings, for $11.38 a share, or $56,900.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gary Straub</ENAMEX>, corporate counsel for the company, said the directors sold for ``personal financial reasons.'' Both insiders declined to comment.
On Wall Street, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Merrill Lynch & Co.</ENAMEX> analyst <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Daniel A. Roling</ENAMEX> rates the stock ``neutral'' and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Drexel Burnham Lambert Inc.</ENAMEX> lists it as a ``buy.'' Pegasus Gold ``has been on a lot of recommended lists as a junior growth company stepping into the big leagues,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Marty Mcneill</ENAMEX>, metals analyst at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dominick & Dominick</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> investment firm. ``It's a good company, and growing; there's nothing that would warrant that it be sold.''
