<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Royal Business Group Inc.</ENAMEX> said it filed suit in federal court here charging <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Realist Inc.</ENAMEX> and its directors with violating federal securities laws ``by engaging in a scheme to prevent'' Royal from acquiring <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Realist</ENAMEX>.
Royal withdrew its offer to buy <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Realist</ENAMEX>, a maker of optical and electronic products based in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Menomonee Falls</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Wis.</ENAMEX>, for $14.06 a share in July after <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Realist</ENAMEX> disclosed the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ammann</ENAMEX> purchase. The suit seeks ``in excess of $350,000 in damages.''
A <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Realist</ENAMEX> official said the company hadn't yet received the full complaint and wouldn't have a response until it had an opportunity to review it.
