<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jayark Corp.</ENAMEX> agreed to pay $4 million in cash, $2 million of 12% convertible debentures, and 1.6 million common shares to acquire closely held <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Kofcoh Imports Inc.</ENAMEX>
In over-the-counter trading Friday, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jayark</ENAMEX> was quoted at 87.5 cents bid, down 15.625 cents. At the market price, the transaction has a total indicated value of $7.4 million.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Kofcoh</ENAMEX> is a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> holding company for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rosalco Inc.</ENAMEX>, which imports furniture and other items. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">David L. Koffman</ENAMEX>, president and chief executive officer of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jayark</ENAMEX>, holds about 40% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Kofcoh</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Jayark</ENAMEX> said.
The transaction is subject to approval by a panel of disinterested directors, the company said, adding that shareholder approval isn't needed.
