As the leading candidate for president of his country in next year's election, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mario Vargas Llosa</ENAMEX> ought to be in an enviable position. But his country is <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Peru</ENAMEX>, where political visibility, especially for a believer in democracy and free enterprise -- a right winger in Latin American eyes -- makes a man a target for assassination. For almost any Peruvian these days, to show an interest in public office is a heroic gesture; for Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Vargas</ENAMEX> Llosa especially so, since he already has achieved a high position in the world's eyes as a writer. Published everywhere to universal acclaim, doted on like a movie star in the Hispanic world from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Barcelona</ENAMEX> to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ushuaia</ENAMEX>, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Vargas Llosa</ENAMEX> could live comfortably on his royalties and console his political conscience with the thought that <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peru</ENAMEX> is a hopeless mess not of his making and that he already did his best to reform it with his magnificently cinematic novel about the years of military dictatorship of his youth, ``Conversation in the Cathedral.''
But, after some hesitation, he is back on the stump and also still writing important novels about <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Peru</ENAMEX>. ``The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Storyteller'' (Farrar, Straus & Giroux</ENAMEX>, 246 pages, $17.95), splendidly translated by <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Helen Lane</ENAMEX>, first appeared in Spanish in 1987 before the Peruvian economy had reached its present state of virtual collapse. And in any case the story takes place a bit earlier than that, when the guerrilla war in the highlands had not yet made internal travel a gamble with destiny. Even still, the very first sentence of this fable that weaves together <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peru</ENAMEX>'s most advanced and most primitive cultural strands speaks of ``my unfortunate country.'' The narrator may be talking about the depredations of the Shining Path <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Maoists</ENAMEX> among the Indians of the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Andes</ENAMEX>, or he may be referring to the plunging inti, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peru</ENAMEX>'s rubber currency, or the corrupting effect of the cocaine trade. But he is swiftly drawn into a tangle of memories about a less newsworthy and more exotic part of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Peru</ENAMEX>: its corner of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Amazon</ENAMEX> jungle.
This narrator is a foil for Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Vargas Llosa</ENAMEX>, a cosmopolitan writer with one well-tailored leg in journalism. He is in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Florence</ENAMEX> to shake himself free of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Peru</ENAMEX> and get some writing done, just as Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Vargas Llosa</ENAMEX> has gone to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Paris</ENAMEX> and now goes frequently to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX> for the same purpose. But this narrator happens upon some photographs in a gallery, pictures taken in Peruvian Amazonia of the untamed and nomadic <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Machiguenga</ENAMEX> tribe. And they remind him of his own experiences with that unhappy scattered culture and of his friend at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lima's University</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">San Marcos</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Saul Zuratas</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Saul</ENAMEX> was a high-strung student of ethnography, a Jew marked doubly as an outsider because of a huge wine-dark birthmark on his face, for which people called him Mascarita, Mask Face. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Saul</ENAMEX> knew about the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Machiguengas</ENAMEX> from his studies, and through him the narrator became interested in this most recalcitrant and un-Westernizable of all the indigenous peoples who had come under the Spanish yoke. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Saul</ENAMEX>, meanwhile, came to believe that anthropology, even at its most benign, was as insidious a form of cultural imperialism as the superficially more blatant activities of Christian missionaries. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Saul</ENAMEX> mysteriously disappears.
This is what we know at the end of the opening section of ``The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Storyteller.</ENAMEX>'' The next voice we hear sounds like this: ``There was no evil, there was no wind, there was no rain. The women bore pure children. If Tasurinchi wanted to eat, he dipped his hand into the river and brought out a shad flicking its tail...'' And this: ``Moving, walking. Keeping on, with or without rain, by land or by water, climbing up the mountain slopes or climbing down the ravines.'' The speaker is never identified. He tells his stories in his majestically simple way, in a ``language'' all his own. There are creation myths and cosmologies and hunting stories -- a whole culture is contained within these dreamy narratives. It is as though Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Vargas Llosa</ENAMEX> had recorded a storytelling session at a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Machiguenga</ENAMEX> campfire. And this is just the effect he hopes to have on the reader, as he alternates chapters in his ``own'' voice with chapters somehow ``borrowed'' from the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Machiguenga</ENAMEX> storyteller.
For most of the book, there is no direct connection between its urban and its Amazonian modes. But the contrast between them becomes a living thing through the brilliant contrast of narrative styles that Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Vargas Llosa</ENAMEX> creates. He controls this counterpoint like a novelistic <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bach</ENAMEX>, reaching an audacious extreme in a hilarious chapter in which the ``<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Vargas Llosa</ENAMEX>'' voice relates his adventures as an inept television newsman. But the joke turns serious when a reportage takes him to Amazonia and he encounters the missionaries who know more than anyone else about the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Machiguengas</ENAMEX>. By this point, the narrator has become obsessed with finding out about the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Machiguenga</ENAMEX> storytellers, who, he had heard years before, functioned like cultural glue for a tribe split into many small bands in constant motion through the jungle. The storytellers traveled among the bands, reminding them of their identity. But why would no Machiguenga the narrator meets during his reportage even admit that there were storytellers?
The narrator eventually deduces the extraordinary answer, which is confirmed in a literally Kafkaesque manner by a storyteller in the next chapter. I am trying to give away as little as possible, but this is not really a mystery or some kind of jungle thriller. It will be read for the brilliant clash of styles of narration and the even more brilliant way that they have been tied together into a large metaphor for literature and its function in society.
A baby boom in sub-<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Saharan Africa</ENAMEX>, the world's poorest region, poses a threat for the area's future.
The region's population, currently estimated at some 500 million people, is growing by 3.2% a year -- ``faster than any major region has ever experienced over a sustained period,'' the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">World Bank</ENAMEX> noted in a recent review of the region between the great desert and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">South Africa</ENAMEX>. This is more than six times the rate for industrial nations.
``Rapid population growth impedes sub-<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Saharan Africa</ENAMEX>'s progress toward virtually all its major goals,'' including higher living standards, the bank said. Noting that traditional African culture respects a woman with many offspring, it said substantial resources, including foreign aid, are needed to effect change.
Otherwise, the bank said, ``By the time a child born today is 22, if present trends continue, sub-<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Saharan Africa</ENAMEX>'s population will have doubled. When that child is 40, it will have quadrupled.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">West Germany</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lufthansa</ENAMEX> has agreed to buy a 10% stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Austrian Airlines</ENAMEX> when the Austrian government continues next spring to sell parts of the carrier to the public, an <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Austrian Airlines</ENAMEX> spokesman said. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Swissair</ENAMEX> will at the same time raise its stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Austrian Airlines</ENAMEX> to 10% from the current 8% holding, he added. Elsewhere, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Singapore Airlines Ltd.</ENAMEX>, following its recently announced tie-up with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Delta Air Lines Inc.</ENAMEX>, is now ``contemplating an alliance'' with one of several European carriers, Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">J.Y. Pillay</ENAMEX> said.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">King Fahd</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Saudi Arabia</ENAMEX> dismissed as untrue allegations that his country's relations with <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Kuwait</ENAMEX> were marred by the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Saudis</ENAMEX>' execution last month of 16 Kuwaiti <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Shiites</ENAMEX>; the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Shiites</ENAMEX> had been convicted for bombings at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mecca.</ENAMEX> The king stressed to the Kuwaiti <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Al-Seyassah</ENAMEX> newspaper that the terrorists were given a fair trial in accordance with Islamic law. ``Those people have been convicted after committing an awful crime,'' the king said. The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Kuwaiti</ENAMEX> government hasn't issued any comment on the executions.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Israel</ENAMEX> is ending six weeks of seizing property from Palestinians who refuse to pay income and value-added taxes in the occupied <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">West Bank</ENAMEX> town of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Beit Sahour</ENAMEX>, despite having failed to break the revolt, security sources said. Troops and tax collectors have confiscated cars, furniture and goods valued at about $1.5 million from residents of the mainly Christian middle-class town, sparking international protests. The army gave no explanation for calling off the seizures, less than a month after <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Defense</ENAMEX> Minister <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Yitzhak Rabin</ENAMEX> vowed to break the tax rebels.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Asian Development Bank</ENAMEX> denied media speculation that it's about to resume lending to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">China</ENAMEX>. The bank cut off loans to the country in the wake of the June 4 massacre in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Beijing</ENAMEX>. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ADB</ENAMEX> staff is continuing to ``prepare loan proposals for <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">China</ENAMEX>'' to present to the bank's board, said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">R.D. Pacheco</ENAMEX>, the bank's chief information officer. Other <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ADB</ENAMEX> officials said the board wasn't ready to consider resuming loans to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">China</ENAMEX> because leading ADB members, including the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX>, remain opposed to a return to normal business with <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Beijing</ENAMEX>.
As <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX> formally announced it's joining an international ban on trading ivory, hundreds of angry ivory traders and carvers marched in downtown <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hong Kong</ENAMEX> to protest the ban. Some of the marchers presented a petition to the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> consulate demanding that <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Washington</ENAMEX>, which earlier banned the import of ivory, help the endangered industry. <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hong Kong</ENAMEX> traders have until Jan. 19 to sell off their stockpile of 670 tons of ivory.
Environmental groups urged <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX> to stop importing timber from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Malaysia</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Sarawak state</ENAMEX>, where they say loggers are destroying rain forests and trampling on the rights of natives.
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX> imports about 50% of the logs exported from the state, which is on the island of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Borneo</ENAMEX>. The call came as the council of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">International Tropical Timber Organization</ENAMEX> opened a nine-day session in the Japanese city of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Yokohama</ENAMEX>. Dr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mikhail Kavanagh</ENAMEX>, an official of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">World Wide Fund</ENAMEX> for Nature, said that ``anything that the Japanese can do to influence the trade is going to come straight back in to influence how the forests are managed.'' He urged <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX> to reduce ``wasteful use of tropical timbers,'' such as disposable chopsticks.
One study group says <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX>'s consumption of disposable chopsticks has doubled in the past decade, reaching 20.5 billion pairs in 1988.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pravda</ENAMEX> said that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nikolai Vasilenko</ENAMEX>, a Soviet farmer, dug up a gold bar valued at $235,000, but consumer-goods shortages left him little to spend it on during a trip to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Vladivostok</ENAMEX>. He wanted to buy, but couldn't find, a shaving brush, a sewing machine and a colander... <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">China</ENAMEX> is facing a musical talent shortage because top artists are leaving for foreign countries, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">China Youth News</ENAMEX> said. The official daily said that 470 musicians went abroad at their own expense in the past decade, and it implied that few are likely to return.
