Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Johnson</ENAMEX> has been a managing director at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Shearson Lehman Hutton</ENAMEX> since 1985, and before that was president of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Public Strategies</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Washington</ENAMEX> consulting firm. He is well-known in Democratic circles, having been executive assistant to Vice President <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Walter Mondale</ENAMEX> and chairman of Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mondale</ENAMEX>'s 1984 presidential campaign.
At <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Fannie Mae</ENAMEX>, he will take responsibility for the corporation's financial and legal areas and will work with <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">David Maxwell</ENAMEX>, chairman and chief executive officer, and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Roger Birk</ENAMEX>, president and chief operating officer, on strategic planning.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Fannie Mae</ENAMEX> also said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">James A. Aliber</ENAMEX>, chairman of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Federal of Michigan</ENAMEX> and a director since 1985, moved up the date of his retirement from the board to accommodate Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Johnson</ENAMEX>'s election as a director. The board has 13 members elected by holders and five presidential appointees.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Fannie Mae</ENAMEX>, a federally chartered, shareholder-owned corporation, operates a secondary market for mortgage loans, buying loans from lenders, packaging some into securities for sale to investors and keeping the rest in its portfolio.
