<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Trinova</ENAMEX> said it will close, move or overhaul 40 of its 170 manufacturing facilities and over the next three years cut 1,500 jobs from its current world-wide payroll of 22,300 employees. Most of the factory closings and job cutbacks will affect <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Trinova</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Aeroquip</ENAMEX> operations, which manufacture automotive plastics, hoses and other industrial and automotive parts. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hoses</ENAMEX> and plastics together account for about 42% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Trinova</ENAMEX>'s total annual sales.
In a separate announcement, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Trinova</ENAMEX> said the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Aeroquip group</ENAMEX> has agreed to sell its spring-brake, piston-brake and related businesses to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Midland Brake Inc.</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Branford</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Conn.</ENAMEX> Terms weren't disclosed.
To provide for the restructuring's costs, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Trinova</ENAMEX> said it took an after-tax charge of $38.5 million, or $1.13 a share, in the third quarter. The $29.7 million net loss compares with net income of $19.6 million, or 57 cents a share, a year earlier. Sales rose 8% to $456.2 million from $422 million.
