In a last-ditch effort to keep its sales force and customer base, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Integrated Resources Inc.</ENAMEX> said it agreed in principle to transfer ownership of its broker-dealer subsidiary to two of its top executives.
The financial-services firm, struggling since summer to avoid a bankruptcy-law filing after missing interest payments on about $1 billion of debt, will retain the right to regain the subsidiary. It said it will exercise that right only if it sells substantially all of its other core businesses. It also can sell the right to regain the subsidiary to another party.
In the transaction, Integrated will transfer 100% ownership of the subsidiary to <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gerard M. Lavin</ENAMEX>, executive vice president of Integrated and head of back-office operations at the subsidiary, and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gary W. Krat</ENAMEX>, executive vice president of the parent and president of the subsidiary.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Integrated</ENAMEX> will pump $3.5 million to $4 million into Royal Alliance as initial funding.
In an interview, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Krat</ENAMEX> said that based on criteria yet to be determined, he expects to distribute 49% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Royal Alliance</ENAMEX> to the representatives, who sell Integrated's insurance and mutual-fund products. If Integrated regains Royal Alliance, the representatives will retain their 49% ownership.
The subsidiary isn't expected to be profitable for at least one year. If Integrated regains the unit, it would receive any profit the unit reports, even while the unit is independent. If the deal closes, the two officers will draw salaries from the independent operation, not from Integrated.
