Guardian <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Royal Exchange Assurance PLC</ENAMEX>, a major British composite insurer, said it is taking a stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nationwide Anglia Building Society</ENAMEX>'s estate agency business as part of a plan to create a range of commercial linkages in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.K.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Europe</ENAMEX>.
Officials declined to disclose the value of the transaction or the exact stake that <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">GRE</ENAMEX> will hold in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nationwide Anglia Estate</ENAMEX> Agents. But the companies said that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nationwide Anglia Estate</ENAMEX> Agents will market GRE life insurance, pension and investment products through its more than 1,000 retail outlets in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.K.</ENAMEX>
Besides the marketing agreement, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GRE</ENAMEX> said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nationwide Anglia</ENAMEX> has agreed to develop life insurance products with the composite insurer.
