<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Viacom Inc.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>, reported that its third-quarter loss widened to $21.7 million, or 41 cents a share, primarily because of interest expense of $70.1 million.
A year ago, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Viacom</ENAMEX> had a net loss of $56.9 million, or $1.07 a share. Interest expense in the 1988 third quarter was $75.3 million. In the year-ago quarter, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Viacom</ENAMEX> also paid preferred stock dividends of $17 million; <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Viacom</ENAMEX> exchanged its preferred stock for debt in March.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Viacom</ENAMEX> attributed the improvement to higher earnings from operations in its networks segment, which includes the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">MTV</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Showtime</ENAMEX> networks.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Viacom</ENAMEX> said it also restructured bank debt under a $1.5 billion unsecured bank agreement that offers significant interest rate savings. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Sumner M. Redstone</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Viacom</ENAMEX>'s chairman, said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Viacom</ENAMEX> ``emerged from our leveraged buy-out structure and gained substantial operating and financial flexibility through'' the bank pact.
