<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">DPC Acquisition Partners</ENAMEX>, a hostile suitor for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dataproducts Corp.</ENAMEX>, filed a petition in federal district court in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Los Angeles</ENAMEX> seeking to have its standstill agreement with the computer printer maker declared void, and it proceeded with a $10-a-share tender offer for the company.
Lawyers representing <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">DPC</ENAMEX> declined to elaborate, saying they didn't have a final copy of the filing. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jack Davis</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dataproducts</ENAMEX>' chairman, said he hadn't yet seen the filing and couldn't comment.
