<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Crossland Savings Bank</ENAMEX>'s stock plummeted after management recommended a suspension of dividend payments on both its common and preferred stock because <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Crossland</ENAMEX> may not meet the new government capital criteria effective Dec. 7.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Crossland</ENAMEX> said it retained three investment bankers to assist it in developing and implementing a financial restructuring plan. It wouldn't identify the bankers.
The spokesman said that the proposed guidelines caused <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Crossland</ENAMEX> to revise its business objectives and, consequently, to write down the asset value of some previous acquisitions. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Crossland</ENAMEX> recorded an additional $20 million in loan loss reserves in the third quarter.
Net interest income for the third quarter declined to $35.6 million from $70.1 million a year ago. However, non-interest income rose to $23.5 million from $22 million. Third-quarter loan originations dropped sharply to $663 million from $1 billion a year ago.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Standard & Poor's Corp.</ENAMEX> lowered the rating on <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Crossland</ENAMEX>'s preferred stock to double-C from single-B-minus and placed it on Creditwatch for possible further downgrade. It also placed on Creditwatch for possible downgrade other securities, including the double-B-minus\ rating of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Crossland</ENAMEX>'s certificates of deposit and the single-B rating of its senior subordinated capital notes. About $518 million of debt is affected.
