An <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Telephone & Telegraph Co.</ENAMEX> unit, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AT&T Nassau Metals Corp.</ENAMEX>, said it was soliciting bids for its <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Gaston</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">S.C.</ENAMEX>, and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chandler</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ariz.</ENAMEX>, metal-processing operations, which produce annual revenue of about $400 million.
The unit didn't disclose any asking price, and an <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AT&T</ENAMEX> spokesman in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Parsippany</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.J.</ENAMEX>, said he couldn't supply one. An industry analyst, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Robert B. Morris III</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Goldman, Sachs & Co.</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">San Francisco</ENAMEX> office, said the value of the operations isn't clear because <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AT&T</ENAMEX> hasn't disclosed their book value or earnings.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AT&T Nassau</ENAMEX> said the operations on the block are no longer ``strategic to the core business'' of the company, which is telecommunications. The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Gaston</ENAMEX> operation processes metal scrap and supplies copper rod, largely to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AT&T</ENAMEX> itself. Also on the block is a small metal chopping operation in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chandler</ENAMEX>.
Increasingly, copper-based technology has been superseded by light-wave technology, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Morris</ENAMEX> said.
