Trading in Cineplex <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Odeon Corp.</ENAMEX> shares was halted on the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Toronto</ENAMEX> stock exchanges late yesterday afternoon at the company's request, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Toronto Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> officials said.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Brian Hemming</ENAMEX>, a spokesman for the company's committee of independent directors, established in May to solicit and evaluate offers for the company, said it was expected to make an announcement early this morning. But Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hemming</ENAMEX> said he wasn't aware of the nature of the talks under way between committee members and their advisers.
Cineplex traded on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> at $11.25 a share, up $1.125, before trading was halted.
Analysts have speculated in recent days that the value of offers received by the committee fell well short of what they had hoped, or even that the company's chairman, president and chief executive officer, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Garth Drabinsky</ENAMEX>, is the only bidder for the company as a whole. The current effort to auction off the company was triggered by a dispute between Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Drabinsky</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Toronto</ENAMEX>-based movie chain's major shareholder, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MCA Inc.</ENAMEX>
