The biotechnology concern said Spanish authorities must still clear the price for the treatment, but that it expects to receive such approval by year end. Four other countries in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Europe</ENAMEX> have approved Proleukin in recent months. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cetus</ENAMEX> is currently trying to obtain federal regulatory clearance for U.S. distribution.
