At a time when <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jon Levy</ENAMEX> should be planning the biggest spring season in his dress company's 17 years, his work day is studded with intense moments of concern about one of his biggest customers, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Campeau Corp.</ENAMEX>
``The dress business has always been a gamble, but it's never been like this,'' says Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Levy</ENAMEX>, president of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">St. Gillian Group Ltd.</ENAMEX>, which has become a hot name thanks to a campaign of sexy TV commercials.
Every day, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Levy</ENAMEX> checks orders from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Campeau</ENAMEX> department store chains, trying to guess if he will be paid. ``I'm now monitoring every major account.''
The risk of doing business with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Campeau</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federated and Allied</ENAMEX> department store chains is about to increase greatly, not only for Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Levy</ENAMEX> but for hundreds of other small apparel makers, button suppliers, trucking firms and fabric houses.
Next week, the country's top designers and manufacturers will begin showing fashions for spring 1990, the second most important selling season of the year. And as the applause dies down in showrooms along <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Seventh Avenue</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Broadway</ENAMEX>, stylishly clad <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Campeau</ENAMEX> buyers will begin writing orders.
Orders from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Campeau</ENAMEX> retailers used to be cause for celebration. This is no longer true because of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Campeau</ENAMEX>'s massive debt load.
``It's all anybody wants to talk about,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Richard Posner</ENAMEX>, executive vice president for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Credit Exchange Inc.</ENAMEX>, a leading credit service. ``People wonder what's going to happen next.''
Many manufacturers are worried about being paid for merchandise already shipped to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Campeau</ENAMEX> stores. But those dollars at risk pale in comparison to the investment required to make and ship spring goods to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Campeau</ENAMEX> stores.
``The few million dollars I could lose today is nothing against what I could lose on the spring line,'' says Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Levy</ENAMEX>, who estimates that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Campeau</ENAMEX> stores will sell $25 million worth of his clothes this year. ``I'm buying fabric right now for clothes which I may not be paid for until April or May. What happens to me if <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Campeau</ENAMEX> collapses between now and then?''
Some credit concerns, such as <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bernard Sands Credit Consultants Inc.</ENAMEX>, have told clients not to ship anything to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Federated</ENAMEX> or <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Allied</ENAMEX> stores on credit. ``This is especially true for spring merchandise,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jim Rindos</ENAMEX>, credit manager at <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Bernard Sands</ENAMEX>. ``<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Campeau</ENAMEX> has too much debt.''
Other credit houses, such as <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Credit Exchange</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Solo Credit Service Corp.</ENAMEX>, are suggesting that their clients study each order before shipping. ``Payments are good right now, but we aren't recommending any long-term lines of credit,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Richard Hastings</ENAMEX>, a retail credit analyst, referring to credit lines which make inventory purchases automatic. ``The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Campeau</ENAMEX> situation is a little uncertain and very difficult to analyze.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Howard Bloom</ENAMEX>, president of the dress firm <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chetta B Inc.</ENAMEX>, says: ``It's big time chaos today. I'm going to ship and hope I get paid. If I need to ask for money up front later, I will.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Carol Sanger</ENAMEX>, vice president, corporate communications at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Campeau</ENAMEX>, says that all of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federated and Allied</ENAMEX> chains are paying their bills in a timely manner. ``They continue to pay their bills and will do so,'' says Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Sanger</ENAMEX>. ``We're confident we'll be paying our bills for spring merchandise as well.''
But manufacturers now buying fabric for spring season goods won't be paid until March, April or even May. Some in the market question whether <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Campeau</ENAMEX> will be in a position to pay bills at that time.
``Everybody is worried about the possibility of cancellations,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kurt Barnard</ENAMEX>, publisher of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Barnard's Retail Marketing Report</ENAMEX>. ``The buyers who work for the various <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Campeau</ENAMEX> chains may lose their jobs. The stores they work for may be sold. What that will mean for manufacturers is anybody's guess.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Campeau</ENAMEX>'s financial situation is complicated by an estimated $1.23 billion in debt due next spring. This includes a working capital facility for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Allied Stores</ENAMEX> of $350 million that matures March 15, 1990, and an $800 million bridge loan due April 30, 1990. The company has stated in recently filed financial documents that it anticipates refinancing its March 1990 payments. In recent months, numerous retailers have filed for Chapter 11 bankruptcy protection, including <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bonwit Teller</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">B. Altman & Co.</ENAMEX>, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Miller & Rhoads Inc.</ENAMEX> Those filings, plus the expected sale of a number of financially healthy chains, such as <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Saks Fifth Avenue</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Marshall Field</ENAMEX>'s and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bloomingdale</ENAMEX>'s, have added to the anxiety.
Other manufacturers are equally cautious. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bud Konheim</ENAMEX>, president of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nicole Miller Inc.</ENAMEX>, says his company is now shipping only to the flagship stores of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federated and Allied</ENAMEX> chains. This limits his financial exposure, he says.
``The branches are just warmed over, empty halls,'' says Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Konheim</ENAMEX>. ``Why should I be part of that problem? I've got limited production, and I can't give it to underperformers.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Campeau</ENAMEX>'s Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Sanger</ENAMEX> disputes Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Konheim</ENAMEX>'s comments. ``Many of the branches are very lucrative,'' she says. ``That's just nonsense.''
As for Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Levy</ENAMEX> at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">St. Gillian</ENAMEX>, he says he will maintain his credit lines with the various <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Campeau</ENAMEX> stores unless they miss a payment. ``If they slip for 10 cents for 10 minutes, I'll stop,'' he says.
