When <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Walter Yetnikoff</ENAMEX>, the president of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony Corp.</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CBS Records</ENAMEX>, last month told producer <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peter Guber</ENAMEX> that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony</ENAMEX> was about to make a $3.4 billion bid for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Columbia Pictures</ENAMEX> and needed someone to run the studio, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guber</ENAMEX> jumped at the chance.
Within two days, he was on his way to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tokyo</ENAMEX> to meet with top brass at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony</ENAMEX>. And before the week was out, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony</ENAMEX> had offered Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guber</ENAMEX> and his partner, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jon Peters</ENAMEX>, the most lucrative employment contracts in the history of the movie business. Not only that, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony</ENAMEX> also agreed to give them a stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Columbia</ENAMEX>'s future profits and buy their company, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Guber Peters Entertainment Co.</ENAMEX>, for $200 million, almost 40% more than the market value of the company.
There was just one sticking point: The two had a prior commitment. Just seven months earlier, they had signed a five-year exclusive contract to make movies for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner Bros.</ENAMEX> for which they had just produced the smash hit ``Batman.'' But Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guber</ENAMEX> figured that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner Communications Inc.</ENAMEX> chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steven Ross</ENAMEX>, would empathize and let the producers go, knowing the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony</ENAMEX> offer was ``the culmination of a life's work.''
That two successful producers who aren't all that well known outside <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hollywood</ENAMEX> could occasion such a clash of corporate titans suggests how desperate the quest for proven talent is in the movie business. And they are a very odd team in any case. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guber</ENAMEX> was raised in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Boston</ENAMEX> and educated in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>. He is a lawyer with a string of academic degrees. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peters</ENAMEX> is a high-school dropout who came to fame as <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Barbra Streisand</ENAMEX>'s hairdresser. Yet, they are far and away the most prolific producers in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hollywood</ENAMEX>. And despite their share of duds, they make movies that make money.
That is a skill <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony</ENAMEX> badly needs -- and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> is loath to lose.
Although <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Columbia</ENAMEX> had a good summer with ``Ghostbusters II'' and ``When <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Harry Met Sally</ENAMEX>,'' rivals such as <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paramount Pictures</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Walt Disney Co.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Universal Studios</ENAMEX> have been thrashing <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Columbia</ENAMEX> at the box office. After five years of management turmoil, with four different studio heads, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Columbia</ENAMEX> sorely needs a stable, savvy team to restore its credibility and get it back in the business of making hits.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guber</ENAMEX> and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peters</ENAMEX> aren't universally loved in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hollywood</ENAMEX> but they are well connected. Their stock in trade as ``executive producers'' is sniffing out hot properties, locking them up and then getting big studios to bankroll and distribute them. Sometimes Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guber</ENAMEX> and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peters</ENAMEX> do little more than grab the first draft of a screenplay for a ``<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Flashdance</ENAMEX>,'' or buy rights to a best seller such as ``The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Color Purple.</ENAMEX>'' It falls to others to do the writing, directing and producing.
``They're the best production talent around,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Brian De Palma</ENAMEX>, beholden to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Guber Peters</ENAMEX> for hiring him to direct the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> movie of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Tom Wolfe</ENAMEX>'s novel ``Bonfire of the Vanities.'' On that film, which is to start shooting in a few months, ``they've been very much involved, hiring talent and discussing the development of the script. And when you're making a movie this big, you need all the help you can get,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">De Palma</ENAMEX> adds. ``I wish they were around 24 hours a day.''
And some movies seem to have been hurt by their inattention. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> executives blame Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guber</ENAMEX>'s and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peters</ENAMEX>'s lack of involvement in ``<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Caddyshack II</ENAMEX>'' for casting and production problems and the film's ultimate dismal failure. ``We've had a few bombs,'' admits Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peters</ENAMEX>. ``But by and large this company has only been profitable.'' He says his company's prowess at packaging and marketing ``is why we'll be good at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Columbia</ENAMEX>. We practically ran our own studio.'' Longtime <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hollywood</ENAMEX> associates describe Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guber</ENAMEX> as the intellectual powerhouse of the two, a man with a flair for deal-making and marketing. ``<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peter</ENAMEX> is a major piece of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hollywood</ENAMEX> manpower who has really earned his success,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Robert Bookman</ENAMEX>, an agent at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Creative Artists Agency</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mark Johnson</ENAMEX>, the producer of ``<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rainman</ENAMEX>,'' chimes in: ``He has a great ability to hire terrific people and delegate authority.... It's no accident that they've been able to develop such successful material.''
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peters</ENAMEX>, on the other hand, has fewer fans in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hollywood</ENAMEX>, and his detractors like to characterize him as something of a hot-tempered bully. He gets better reviews as a creative whiz, an enthusiast, an idea man. He also had to fight harder for credibility than his partner did. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Barbra Streisand</ENAMEX> made him famous. He cut her hair. He lived with her. He came to produce her records and her movies -- ``A Star Is Born'' and ``The Main Event.''
Thrice married but now single, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peters</ENAMEX> got plenty of ink last summer for an on-set romance with actress <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kim Basinger</ENAMEX> during the making of ``Batman.'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guber</ENAMEX>, by contrast, has been married to one woman for more than 20 years. But for all their intellectual and stylistic differences, they make the perfect ``good cop, bad cop'' team, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hollywood</ENAMEX> associates say. ``<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peter</ENAMEX> is the bright, sympathetic guy when you're doing a deal,'' says one agent. ``If there's a problem, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peter</ENAMEX> disappears, and all of a sudden <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jon</ENAMEX> shows up.''
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guber</ENAMEX> and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peters</ENAMEX> rub many people in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hollywood</ENAMEX> the wrong way. Producers <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Don Simpson</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jerry Bruckheimer</ENAMEX>, who shepherded ``Flashdance'' through several scripts and ultimately produced the movie, bristle when <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Messrs</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guber</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peters</ENAMEX> take credit for the film. Says Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Simpson</ENAMEX>: ``The script was unreadable. We reinvented it. We are the producers of that movie. They got a small piece of the net profits and a screen credit'' as executive producers.
When <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Roger Birnbaum</ENAMEX>, an executive who worked for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Guber Peters</ENAMEX> in the early 1980s, left to take a job as head of production at the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Artists</ENAMEX> studio, they made him forfeit all credits and financial interest in the films he had helped develop, including ``<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rainman</ENAMEX>'' and ``Batman.'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peters</ENAMEX> acknowledges that and says it's not unlike the situation he and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guber</ENAMEX> are in with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX>. ``I was upset with <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Roger</ENAMEX>, I fumpered and schmumpered,'' says Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peters</ENAMEX>. ``But he wanted to pursue his own dream, and he went.''
Still, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Birnbaum</ENAMEX> says his relationship with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Guber Peters</ENAMEX> was ``one of the most successful I've had in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hollywood</ENAMEX>.'' The two ``have a wonderful chemistry -- <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jon</ENAMEX> is very impulsive, and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peter</ENAMEX> is very compulsive,'' adds Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Birnbaum</ENAMEX>, who is now head of production at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">News Corp.</ENAMEX>'s 20th <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Century Fox Film Co.</ENAMEX> ``<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jon Peters</ENAMEX> will come barreling into a room, say he's got a great idea, and be gone. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peter</ENAMEX> will take the kernel of that idea and make it grow into something specific....''
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Birnbaum</ENAMEX> recalls that Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guber</ENAMEX> and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peters</ENAMEX> shifted into high gear a few years back upon learning that they had competition for the story of the murdered naturalist <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dian Fossey</ENAMEX>, which became ``Gorillas in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mist.</ENAMEX>'' He says, ``Within a few weeks, we made deals with the government of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rwanda</ENAMEX> and everyone who had ever met or talked to <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dian Fossey</ENAMEX>. I think <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peter</ENAMEX> even made some deals with the gorillas.'' <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Universal Studios</ENAMEX> was working on a competing film, but the studio and its producers ultimately agreed to co-produce the film with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Guber Peters</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX>.
It's hardly astonishing (given the men's track record) that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony</ENAMEX> wants Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guber</ENAMEX> and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peters</ENAMEX>. But it is puzzling to some <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hollywood</ENAMEX> executives that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony</ENAMEX> rushed to hire them without clearing up the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> situation first. Some note that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony</ENAMEX> might have saved itself some trouble by just hiring Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guber</ENAMEX> and letting Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peters</ENAMEX> stay on to fulfill the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> contract. But though ``people in town may ask why <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Guber needs Peters</ENAMEX>, it's good to have a partner, and obviously the chemistry works,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steven Tisch</ENAMEX>, a producer who once worked for Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guber</ENAMEX>. ``This business isn't about personalities at the end of the day -- its about whether the ink is red or black. In the case of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peter</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jon</ENAMEX>, the ink has been very, very black.''
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guber</ENAMEX> got his start in the movie business at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Columbia</ENAMEX> two decades ago. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Recruited</ENAMEX> from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York University</ENAMEX>'s MBA program, he rose within two years to head of production, overseeing such films as ``The Way We Were,'' ``<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Taxi Driver</ENAMEX>,'' ``Tommy'' and ``<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Shampoo.</ENAMEX>'' In 1976, he teamed up with record producer <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Neil Bogart</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Casablanca Records</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Filmworks</ENAMEX> -- later called <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Polygram Pictures</ENAMEX> -- where they produced such hits as as ``The Deep,'' and ``<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Midnight Express.</ENAMEX>''
In 1980, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guber</ENAMEX> got together with Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peters</ENAMEX>, by then a successful producer in his own right, after the death of Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bogart</ENAMEX>. While <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Guber Peters</ENAMEX> produced a number of hits for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> and others, their record wasn't always so impressive. Among their clinkers were ``The Legend of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Billie Jean</ENAMEX>,'' ``Visionquest,'' ``Clue'' and ``Clan of the Cave Bear.'' And the failures make it possible for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> in its current lawsuit to paint the producers as ingrates. The studio says it stuck with them ``even in the early years when the creative partnership was not particularly profitable for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner.</ENAMEX>''
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guber</ENAMEX> and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peters</ENAMEX> maintain that executives at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> have always known of their ambitions to run a major entertainment powerhouse, but that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> never felt threatened until they linked up with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony</ENAMEX>. ``From the beginning, {they} knew we had a goal and a dream,'' says Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guber</ENAMEX>. On a number of occasions, he adds, he tried to get Warner to buy <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Guber Peters</ENAMEX> outright. ``They always listened, but they never acted,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guber</ENAMEX> says.
In 1987, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guber</ENAMEX> and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peters</ENAMEX> contributed their company's assets in exchange for a 28% stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Barris Entertainment</ENAMEX>, a small-fry TV production company controlled by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Giant Industries Inc.</ENAMEX> Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Burt Sugarman</ENAMEX>. In July a year later, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> agreed to release the producers from their old contract when <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Messrs</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guber</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peters</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Sugarman</ENAMEX> made a $100 million offer to buy 25% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MGM/UA</ENAMEX>. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guber</ENAMEX> and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peters</ENAMEX> planned to run the nearly dormant <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MGM</ENAMEX> studio, and the two even tried to interest <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner Bros.</ENAMEX>' President <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Terry Semel</ENAMEX> in becoming a partner after he advised them on the deal.
The new deal was considered the most generous of its kind, both financially and in terms of creative freedom. But it paled by comparison to what <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony</ENAMEX> was to offer last month: the chance, at last, to run a major studio, about $50 million in deferred compensation, up to 10% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Columbia</ENAMEX>'s future cash flow, 8% of the future appreciation of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Columbia</ENAMEX>'s market value, and annual salaries of $2.7 million for each. The producers' 28% share of publicly held <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Guber Peters</ENAMEX> would net them an additional $50 million. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony</ENAMEX> also agreed to indemnify the producers against any liability to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony</ENAMEX> is paying a hefty price for a company that had revenue of only $42 million last year. And earnings have been erratic. In the the latest quarter, thanks in part to ``Batman,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Guber Peters</ENAMEX> earned $5.8 million, or 50 cents a share, compared to a loss of $6.8 million, or 62 cents a share, in last year's quarter. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Guber Peters</ENAMEX> stock, which traded as low as $6 a share last year, closed yesterday at $16.625.
The two sides now are accusing each other of lying. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guber</ENAMEX> and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peters</ENAMEX> claim they have an oral agreement with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> executives that allows them to terminate their contract should the opportunity to run a major studio arise. But in affidavits filed yesterday in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Los Angeles</ENAMEX> court, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ross</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner Bros.</ENAMEX> Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Robert Daly</ENAMEX> and President <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Semel</ENAMEX> deny that such an oral agreement was ever made. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX>, in its court filings, calls it ``a piece of fiction created for this litigation.''
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Daly</ENAMEX> in his affidavit acknowledges that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> agreed to release the producers last year to take over <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MGM</ENAMEX> but says that situation was altogether different. For one thing, according to Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Daly</ENAMEX>, the producers requested a release in advance. Moreover, the old contract was about to expire, and the lineup of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Guber Peters</ENAMEX> pictures for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> wasn't as strong as it is now. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> itself was in negotiations with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MGM</ENAMEX> over certain movie and other rights, and it was ``in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX>'s interest to accommodate <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MGM/UA</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Guber and Peters</ENAMEX> by permitting them to become <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MGM</ENAMEX> executives,'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Daly</ENAMEX> said in his affidavit.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> obviously doesn't think that it is in its own interests to let Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guber</ENAMEX> and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peters</ENAMEX> go off to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Columbia</ENAMEX>. At the very least, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ross</ENAMEX> clearly sees an opportunity to use the two men to get a pound of flesh from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony</ENAMEX>. During settlement talks, for example, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> demanded such things as cable TV rights to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Columbia</ENAMEX> movies and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Columbia</ENAMEX>'s interest in the studio it jointly owns with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX>, according to executives involved in the talks. In any settlement, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> is almost certain to demand rights to most of the 50 or so projects Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guber</ENAMEX> and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peters</ENAMEX> have locked up for the next few years, notably sequels to ``Batman.''
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Guber</ENAMEX> and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peters</ENAMEX> refuse to concede that they may have made a tactical error in accepting the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony</ENAMEX> offer before taking it up with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX>. And they say there are plenty of precedents in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hollywood</ENAMEX> for letting people out of contracts. The last time <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Columbia Pictures</ENAMEX> was looking for a studio chief, they note, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX> released producer <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">David Puttnam</ENAMEX> from his contract, then took him back after he was subsequently fired by his bosses at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Columbia</ENAMEX>. In his affidavit filed yesterday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Warner</ENAMEX>'s Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ross</ENAMEX> indicated he isn't buying any such argument: ``If <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sony</ENAMEX> succeeds here, no written contract in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hollywood</ENAMEX> will be worth the paper it's written on.
