<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sea Containers Ltd.</ENAMEX> said it might increase the price of its $70-a-share buy-back plan if pressed by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Temple Holdings Ltd.</ENAMEX>, which made an earlier tender offer for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sea Containers</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sea Containers</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hamilton</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Bermuda</ENAMEX>-based shipping concern, said Tuesday that it would sell $1.1 billion of assets and use some of the proceeds to buy about 50% of its common shares for $70 apiece.
The move is designed to ward off a hostile takeover attempt by two European shipping concerns, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Stena Holding AG</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tiphook PLC</ENAMEX>. In May, the two companies, through their jointly owned holding company, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Temple</ENAMEX>, offered $50 a share, or $777 million, for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sea Containers</ENAMEX>. In August, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Temple</ENAMEX> sweetened the offer to $63 a share, or $963 million.
Yesterday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sea Containers</ENAMEX>' chief executive officer, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">James Sherwood</ENAMEX>, said in an interview that, under the asset-sale plan, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sea Containers</ENAMEX> would end up with a cash surplus of approximately $620 million. About $490 million of that would be allocated to the buy-back, leaving about $130 million, he said.
That $130 million, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Sherwood</ENAMEX> said, ``gives us some flexibility in case <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Temple</ENAMEX> raises its bid. We are able to increase our price above the $70 level if necessary.'' He declined to say, however, how much <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sea Containers</ENAMEX> might raise its price.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Sherwood</ENAMEX> speculated that the leeway that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sea Containers</ENAMEX> has means that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Temple</ENAMEX> would have to ``substantially increase their bid if they're going to top us.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Temple</ENAMEX>, however, harshly criticized <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sea Containers</ENAMEX>' plan yesterday, characterizing it as a ``highly conditional device designed to entrench management, confuse shareholders and prevent them from accepting our superior cash offer.''
A spokesman for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Temple</ENAMEX> estimated that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sea Containers</ENAMEX>' plan --if all the asset sales materialize --would result in shareholders receiving only $36 to $45 a share in cash. The lower figures, the spokesman said, would stem from preferred shares being converted to common stock and the possibility that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sea Containers</ENAMEX>' subsidiaries might be required to place their shares in the open market.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Temple</ENAMEX> added that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sea Containers</ENAMEX> is still mired in legal problems in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Bermuda</ENAMEX>, where the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Supreme Court</ENAMEX> has temporarily barred <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sea Containers</ENAMEX> from buying back its own stock in a case brought by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Stena</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tiphook.</ENAMEX> {The court has indicated it will rule on the case by the end of the month.}
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Temple</ENAMEX> also said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sea Containers</ENAMEX>' plan raises ``numerous legal, regulatory, financial and fairness issues,'' but didn't elaborate.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Sherwood</ENAMEX> said reaction to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sea Containers</ENAMEX>' proposal has been ``very positive.'' In <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> composite trading yesterday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sea Containers</ENAMEX> closed at $62.625, up 62.5 cents.
