<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Delta Air Lines</ENAMEX>, in a move that could help it thwart the kind of takeover attempts that have bedeviled other airlines this year, agreed to sell about 5% of its stock to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Singapore Airlines Ltd.</ENAMEX>
It was the second such transaction for the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Atlanta</ENAMEX>-based airline, which this summer sold a 5% stake to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Swissair</ENAMEX> and placed another 14% of its stock in employees' hands.
As part of a 10-year marketing agreement with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Singapore Airlines</ENAMEX> announced yesterday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Delta</ENAMEX> also agreed to spend about $183 million -- the same amount <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Singapore Airlines</ENAMEX> will spend for its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Delta</ENAMEX> shares -- to buy a similar stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Singapore Airlines</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Delta</ENAMEX> wouldn't comment on whether the moves were anti-takeover measures. But they come after a period during which three of the carrier's largest rivals were the subject of takeover bids.
With its fat profits, low debt levels and steady growth, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Delta</ENAMEX> has been considered by Wall Street analysts as likely prey for corporate raiders. Its shares have risen nearly 15% over the past six months. Yesterday, it closed at $66.375 in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> composite trading, down 12.5 cents.
Under the terms of equity cross-purchase agreements, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Singapore Airlines</ENAMEX> agreed to buy 2.5 million shares of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Delta</ENAMEX> common stock for 110% of its closing price for the four days surrounding its purchase announcement. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Delta</ENAMEX> agreed to buy the same dollar amount of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Singapore Airlines</ENAMEX> shares.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Singapore Airlines</ENAMEX> also agreed not to transfer its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Delta</ENAMEX> shares and to vote those shares in the same proportion as all other shares are voted or as recommended by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Delta</ENAMEX>'s board. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Delta</ENAMEX> made a similar pact regarding its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Singapore Airlines</ENAMEX> holdings.
As part of the 10-year marketing agreement, the two airlines also plan to coordinate their schedules and possibly operate joint service on certain routes.
An added benefit for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Delta</ENAMEX> is that its agreement with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Singapore Airlines</ENAMEX> provides a toehold in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Pacific</ENAMEX>, where <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> airlines face the best possibility of expansion.
