The per-share loss was $5.32. In the year earlier period, the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> parent of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Republic National Bank</ENAMEX> had net income of $38.7 million, or $1.12 a share. Excluding the provision, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Republic</ENAMEX> earned $44.6 million, up 15% from a year ago.
The bank's medium-term and long-term loans to less-developed countries total $293 million, of which $146 million aren't accruing interest, the bank said. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Republic</ENAMEX>'s total of nonperforming assets was $167 million at Sept. 30, with its reserve for loan losses now standing at $357 million.
