<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Applied Solar Energy Corp. of City of Industry</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Calif.</ENAMEX>, said it and its majority shareholder, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Cyanamid Co.</ENAMEX>, signed a non-binding letter of intent for the acquisition of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Applied Solar</ENAMEX> by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mcdonnell Douglas Corp.</ENAMEX> for about $38 million.
The proposed acquisition provides for a cash payment of $10 a share at closing and a contingent payment of as much as 80 cents a share placed in escrow. Details of the escrow agreement haven't been completed, the companies said. There are 3.5 million shares of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Applied Solar</ENAMEX>, of which <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Cyanamid</ENAMEX> owns 2.7 million. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Cyanamid</ENAMEX> is a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Wayne</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.J.</ENAMEX>, chemicals, drugs and fertilizer concern.
A spokeswoman for the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">St. Louis</ENAMEX> aerospace and defense concern said it wanted the acquistion because <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Applied Solar</ENAMEX> is involved in solar cells and solid-state laser components, and this fits with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mcdonnell</ENAMEX>'s business of laser applications for military space.
