(See: ``Dividend News: <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Payout Stalled</ENAMEX> at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Quantum Chemical Corp.</ENAMEX> -- Firm Posts Quarterly Loss, Plans a Stock Dividend to Take Place of Cash'' -- <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">WSJ</ENAMEX> Oct. 27, 1989
