<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Airways PLC</ENAMEX> said it is seeking improved terms and a sharply lower price in any revised bid for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Airlines</ENAMEX> parent <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL Corp.</ENAMEX> following the collapse of a $6.79 billion, $300-a-share buy-out bid.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Derek Stevens</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Air</ENAMEX>'s chief financial officer, told <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Jones</ENAMEX> Professional Investor Report a price of $230 a share is ``certainly not too low,'' and indicated his company would like to reduce the size of its $750 million cash investment.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stevens</ENAMEX>'s remarks, confirming a report in The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Wall Street Journal</ENAMEX> that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Air</ENAMEX> wants to start from scratch in any new bid for the nation's second-largest airline, helped push <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> stock lower for the fourth straight day.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> fell $6.25 a share to $191.75 on volume of 2.3 million shares in composite trading on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> as concern deepened among takeover stock traders about the length of time it will take to revive the purchase.
Under the original buy-out approved by the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> board Sept. 14, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX>'s pilots planned to put up $200 million in cash and make $200 million in annual cost concessions for a 75% stake. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> management was to pay $15 million for 10%, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Air</ENAMEX> was to receive a 15% stake.
The buy-out fell through when <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Citicorp</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chase Manhattan Corp.</ENAMEX> unexpectedly failed to obtain bank financing. Since then, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> stock has fallen 33% in what may rank as the largest collapse of a takeover stock ever.
The tenor of Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stevens</ENAMEX>'s remarks seemed to indicate that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Air</ENAMEX> will take a more active, high-profile role in pursuing any new bid. He said he believes <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> management was badly advised on the funding of its original transaction.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stevens</ENAMEX> said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Air</ENAMEX> hasn't received any new buy-out proposals from the labor-management group, led by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stephen Wolf</ENAMEX>, and hasn't received any indication of when one might be forthcoming. ``As far as we're concerned, we're waiting for the dust to settle,'' he said.
Although <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Air</ENAMEX> is waiting to see what the buy-out group comes up with, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stevens</ENAMEX> said a revised transaction with less debt leverage is likely to be more attractive to banks. He said the original proposal is dead, and all aspects of a revised version are up for change, in light of the changes in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX>'s market price, the amount of debt banks are willing to fund, and the price <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Air</ENAMEX> would be willing to pay.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stevens</ENAMEX> said he expects the new price will be considerably lower, but declined to specify a figure. Asked whether a $230-a-share figure circulating in the market yesterday is too low, he said, ``It's certainly not too low.''
He added the original offer was ``a pretty full price,'' and that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Air</ENAMEX>'s contribution ``was quite a large chunk for us.'' <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Air</ENAMEX> was originally attracted to the chance of obtaining a 15% stake in the company, but wasn't particularly happy with paying $750 million.
In the event that the buy-out group stalls in reviving its bid, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> board could remain under some pressure to seek another transaction, even without any legal obligation to do so. Roughly one-third of its stock is believed held by takeover stock traders, who could vote to oust the board if they become impatient.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX>'s management agreed to reduce the seniority of those pilots in exchange for the support of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United</ENAMEX> pilot union for the buy-out proposal. The 220 pilots involved in the suit aren't members of the union. The airline had allowed them to move ahead of some union members in seniority following the 1985 strike, a move the union had contested in a previous lawsuit.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Judith Valente</ENAMEX> contributed to this article.
