The natural gas pipeline concern said the 500 million cubic feet a day capacity pipeline would be built by a proposed joint venture between two <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Panhandle Eastern</ENAMEX> units-<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Texas  Eastern Transmission Corp.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Trunkline Gas Co.</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Texas Eastern Transmission</ENAMEX> will build and operate the system, which will connect the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Arkoma Basin</ENAMEX> with several interstate pipelines.
