<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bally Manufacturing Corp.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> developer <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Donald Trump</ENAMEX> have agreed in principle to a $6.5 million settlement of shareholder litigation stemming from Bally's alleged greenmail payment to Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Trump</ENAMEX>.
According to lawyers familiar with the settlement talks, the verbal agreement to end a lawsuit filed more than two years ago was reached last week and will soon be submitted to a federal judge in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Camden</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.J.</ENAMEX>
In February 1987, Bally thwarted a possible hostile takeover bid from Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Trump</ENAMEX> by agreeing to buy 2.6 million of Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Trump</ENAMEX>'s 3.1 million Bally shares for $83.7 million -- more than $18 million above market price. The term greenmail refers to a situation where a company pays a premium over market value to repurchase a stake held by a potential acquirer.
Lawyers for shareholders, Bally and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Trump</ENAMEX> all declined to talk publicly about the proposed settlement, citing a request by a federal court magistrate not to reveal details of the agreement until it is completed.
But some attorneys who are familiar with the matter said the $6.5 million payment will be shared by Bally and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Trump</ENAMEX>, with the casino and hotel concern probably paying the bulk of the money.
The amount Bally and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Trump</ENAMEX> will pay to settle the class-action suit pales in comparison to the $45 million <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Walt Disney Co.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Saul Steinberg</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Reliance Group Holdings Inc.</ENAMEX> agreed to pay to settle a similar suit in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">July</ENAMEX>. That settlement represented the first time shareholders were granted a major payment in a greenmail case. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steinberg</ENAMEX> made a $59.7 million profit on the sale to Disney of his investment in the company in 1984.
But lawyers said Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steinberg</ENAMEX> probably faced much more potential liability because, when he sued <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Disney</ENAMEX> during his takeover battle, he filed on behalf of all shareholders. When <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Disney</ENAMEX> offered to pay Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steinberg</ENAMEX> a premium for his shares, the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> investor didn't demand the company also pay a premium to other shareholders. When Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Trump</ENAMEX> sued Bally, he sued only on behalf of himself.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Trump</ENAMEX> and Bally also appeared to have some leverage in the case because in the state of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Delaware</ENAMEX>, where Bally is incorporated, courts have held that greenmail is often protected by the business-judgment rule. That rule gives boards of directors wide latitude in deciding how to deal with dissident shareholders.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">SENATE</ENAMEX> HEARS final arguments in impeachment trial of federal judge.
Yesterday, U.S. Judge <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Alcee Hastings</ENAMEX> faced his jury -- the full <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.S. Senate</ENAMEX> -- and said, ``I am not guilty of having committed any crime.''
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Senate</ENAMEX>'s public gallery was packed with Judge <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hastings</ENAMEX>' supporters, who erupted into applause after he finished his argument. Judge <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hastings</ENAMEX>, who was acquitted of similar charges by a federal jury in 1983, claims he is being victimized and that the impeachment proceedings against him constitute double jeopardy.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Senate</ENAMEX> will deliberate behind closed doors today and is scheduled to vote on the impeachment tomorrow. If the judge is impeached, as is thought likely, he will be removed from office immediately.
However, Judge <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hastings</ENAMEX> has said he will continue to fight and is contemplating an appeal of any impeachment to the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.S. Supreme Court</ENAMEX>.
COMPANIES SEEKING to make insurers pay for pollution cleanup win court victory.
In a case involving <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Avondale Industries Inc.</ENAMEX> and its insurer, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Travelers Cos.</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Second U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> ruled in favor of the company on two issues that lawyers say are central to dozens of pollution cases around the country.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Travelers</ENAMEX> and other insurers have maintained that cleanup costs aren't damages and thus aren't covered under commercial policies. They also have argued that government proceedings notifying a company of potential responsibility don't fit the legal definition of a lawsuit; thus, such governmental proceedings aren't covered by the policies, the insurers say.
The appeals court disagreed on both counts. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Avondale</ENAMEX> was notified by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Louisiana</ENAMEX> officials in 1986 that it was potentially responsible for a cleanup at an oil-recycling plant. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Avondale</ENAMEX> asked <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Travelers</ENAMEX> to defend it in the state proceeding, but the insurer didn't respond. The appeals court upheld a district judge's ruling that the insurer had to defend the company in such proceedings.
The appeals court also said, ``We think an ordinary businessman reading this policy would have believed himself covered for the demands and potential damage claims'' stemming from any cleanup.
``This decision will have a very considerable impact,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kenneth Abraham</ENAMEX>, professor of environmental law and insurance law at the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">University of Virginia</ENAMEX>, because many commercial insurance policies are issued by companies based in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Barry R. Ostrager</ENAMEX>, an attorney for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Travelers</ENAMEX>, said, ``there are procedural bases on which this case will be appealed further.''
``The report provides detailed documentation of the extent and nature of the problem and indicates how we may want to shape solutions,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Joseph Genova</ENAMEX>, chairman of the committee that oversaw the survey and a partner at the law firm of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Milbank</ENAMEX>, Tweed, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hadley & Mccloy.</ENAMEX>
According to the study, slightly more than 34% of those surveyed reported having at least one housing problem every year for which they had no legal help. Nearly 36% ranked housing problems as their most serious unmet legal need. Other areas targeted by the survey's respondents included difficulty obtaining or maintaining public benefits (22%), consumer fraud (15.4%), and health-care issues (15%).
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Genova</ENAMEX> said the committee may meet to propose solutions to the problems identified in the study.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">PROSECUTOR TO JOIN Gibson Dunn</ENAMEX>: Assistant U.S. Attorney <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Randy Mastro</ENAMEX>, who headed the government's racketeering case against the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">International Brotherhood</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Teamsters</ENAMEX>, will join <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gibson</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dunn & Crutcher</ENAMEX> in its <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> office. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mastro</ENAMEX> has been with the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> U.S. attorney's office for nearly five years. In 1987 he became deputy chief of the civil division. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mastro</ENAMEX> will do civil litigation and white-collar defense work for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Gibson Dunn</ENAMEX>, which is based in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Los Angeles</ENAMEX>.
FORMER <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">APPLE COMPUTER Inc</ENAMEX>. general counsel <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John P. Karalis</ENAMEX> has joined the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Phoenix</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ariz.</ENAMEX>, law firm of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Brown & Bain.</ENAMEX> Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Karalis</ENAMEX>, 51, will specialize in corporate law and international law at the 110-lawyer firm. Before joining Apple in 1986, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Karalis</ENAMEX> served as general counsel at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sperry Corp.</ENAMEX>
