<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Express Co.</ENAMEX> posted a 21% increase in third quarter net income despite a sharp rise in reserves for Third World loans at its banking unit.
The year-earlier figures included $9.9 million, or three cents a share, in income from discontinued operations. Income from continuing operations was up 26%. Revenue rose 24% to $6.5 billion from $5.23 billion.
The travel, investment services, insurance and banking concern added $110 million to reserves for credit losses at its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Express Bank</ENAMEX> unit, boosting the reserve to $507 million as of Sept. 30. The bank's Third World debt portfolio totals $560 million, down from $2.2 billion at the end of 1986. The bank charged off $53 million in loans during the quarter.
At the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Express Travel Related Services Co.</ENAMEX> unit, net rose 17% to a record $240.8 million on a 19% revenue increase. The figures exclude businesses now organized as <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Express Information Services Co.</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Express</ENAMEX> card charge volume rose 12%. Travel sales rose 11%, led by gains in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX>
At <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IDS Financial Services</ENAMEX>, the financial planning and mutual fund unit, net rose 19% to a record $47.6 million on a 33% revenue gain. Assets owned or managed rose 20% to $45 billion, and mutual fund sales rose 45% in the quarter to $923 million.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Express Bank</ENAMEX> earnings fell 50% to $21.3 million from $42.5 million despite a 29% revenue gain. The results include $106 million of tax benefits associated with previous years' Third World loan activity, compared with $15 million a year earlier.
Profit rose 38% at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Express Information Services</ENAMEX> to $21.6 million. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Shearson Lehman Hutton Holdings Inc.</ENAMEX>, as previously reported, had net of $65.9 million, reversing a $3.5 million loss a year earlier; its latest results include a $37 million gain from the sale of an institutional money management business. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Express</ENAMEX>'s share of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Shearson</ENAMEX>'s earnings was $41 million, after preferred stock dividends; it owns about 68% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Shearson</ENAMEX>'s common.
