<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Stateswest Airlines</ENAMEX> said it submitted an offer to the directors of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mesa Airlines</ENAMEX> to acquire the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Farmington</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.M.</ENAMEX>, carrier.
Except to characterize its offer as ``fair and generous and in the best interests of Mesa shareholders,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stateswest</ENAMEX> declined to discuss details of its proposal. It also asked Mesa to keep the proposal confidential. A Mesa official confirmed receipt of the offer and said directors would meet to consider it.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Stateswest</ENAMEX> operates four twin-engine turboprop aircraft, connecting 10 cities in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">California</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Arizona</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Nevada</ENAMEX>. The carrier hasn't yet turned a profit.
