In a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Securities and Exchange Commission</ENAMEX> filing, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Simmons</ENAMEX> said he and companies he controls, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NL Industries Inc.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NL Chemicals Inc.</ENAMEX>, hold 6,744,600 shares of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lockheed</ENAMEX>, of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Calabasas</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Calif</ENAMEX>. They include 122,700 shares bought Friday for between $47.125 and $48 each.
Earlier this week, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Simmons</ENAMEX> objected to published reports quoting him as saying he planned to sell his <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lockheed</ENAMEX> stake because ``the defense industry seems to be getting more uncertain.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Valhi Inc.</ENAMEX>, another of Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Simmons</ENAMEX>' companies, responded to an article Monday in The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Wall Street Journal</ENAMEX>, which credited a story in the Sunday <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Los Angeles</ENAMEX> Daily News. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Valhi</ENAMEX> said the articles didn't accurately reflect <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Valhi</ENAMEX> and its affiliates' intentions toward <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Lockheed</ENAMEX>. Instead, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Valhi</ENAMEX> said, they may increase, decrease or retain their <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lockheed</ENAMEX> holdings, depending on a number of conditions.
