<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cray Research Inc.</ENAMEX> forecast that 1990 will be a no-growth year for its supercomputer line.
In what has become a series of bad-news announcements, the world's largest maker of supercomputers said that after reviewing its order prospects, ``we have concluded it is prudent to plan for next year on the assumption that revenue again will be flat.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Cray</ENAMEX> jolted the market in July when it slashed revenue and earnings projections for this year, citing a slowing economy that has delayed orders from government as well as commercial customers.
The company made its 1990 projection -- an unusual event for <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Cray</ENAMEX> -- in announcing improved net income for the third quarter. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cray</ENAMEX> said it earned $30.6 million, or $1.04 a share, up 35% from $22.6 million, or 73 cents a share, a year ago. Revenue gained 45% to $210.2 million from $145.2 million.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cray</ENAMEX> said its order backlog at Sept. 30 was $315 million, down $25 million from June 30. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Marcello Gumucio</ENAMEX>, president, said the company ``did well in the quarter as far as revenues and earnings are concerned, and not quite as well in terms of signing orders.''
As for the current period, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gumucio</ENAMEX> said, ``We anticipate that fourth-quarter revenue and earnings will be substantially greater than any of the preceding three quarters, but not up to the record levels of last year's fourth quarter'' when <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cray</ENAMEX> earned $88.5 million, or $2.80 a share.
He added that the company expects ``strong'' operating profit for the year, ``but at a level significantly lower than last year.'' He said 1989's net income could be 11% to 13% of revenue, which, assuming current expectations, would be 40% to 45% below 1988's level. Last year, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cray</ENAMEX> earned $156.6 million, or $4.99 a share, on revenue of $756.3 million.
Next year ``looks dismal,'' said analyst <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Paul Luber</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Robert Baird & Co.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Milwaukee</ENAMEX>. Noting that <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Cray</ENAMEX> doesn't have a low-end supercomputer to compete with the likes of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Convex Computer Corp.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">International Business Machines Corp.</ENAMEX>, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Luber</ENAMEX> said such a machine would be necessary ``to get things back on line here.'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Cray</ENAMEX> has indicated it will decide on whether to build such a machine before year end.
