Former <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">USX Corp.</ENAMEX> Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">David M. Roderick</ENAMEX> may have been lucky he retired last May.
As he handed over the reins to successor <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Charles A. Corry</ENAMEX>, steel profits were close to a cyclical peak. Though imports were troublesome, they weren't running away with the market, and American companies had high hopes that steel import quotas would be extended for another five years. Perhaps most important, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Carl Icahn</ENAMEX>, who had once threatened a hostile takeover bid, was subdued. He and Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Roderick</ENAMEX> were even dining out together.
Today, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Corry</ENAMEX> presides over a company whose fortunes have changed abruptly. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Icahn</ENAMEX>, the company's deep-pocketed, tenacious adversary, recently disclosed that he had raised his <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">USX</ENAMEX> stake to 13.1%, and he again threatened a takeover. A battle with Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Icahn</ENAMEX> would rattle even the most seasoned chief executive, to say nothing of one who took the helm less than five months ago.
In addition, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">USX</ENAMEX>'s giant steel segment, representing 34% of its 1988 sales, is facing softening demand and slipping prices as well as increasing competition from foreign steelmakers and low-cost minimills. The import quotas got only a 2 1\ extension, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">USX</ENAMEX> is laboring under a staggering $5.8 billion debt at a time when it must spend money to upgrade steel mills and drill for oil. ``It's a baptism of fire for <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Corry</ENAMEX>,'' says one <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">USX</ENAMEX> executive.
The burning question is whether the new chief can parry Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Icahn</ENAMEX> without being pushed into unwelcome moves. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Corry</ENAMEX> might have to dismember the company more than he wants to. Or he might have to incur a huge expense of either buying Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Icahn</ENAMEX>'s stock, possibly at a premium, or paying stockholders a special dividend partly because of Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Icahn</ENAMEX>'s pressure.
With his recent purchases of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">USX</ENAMEX> common stock, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Icahn</ENAMEX> shattered a three-year-old, unwritten standstill agreement with Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Roderick</ENAMEX>. In 1986, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Roderick</ENAMEX> adroitly dodged Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Icahn</ENAMEX>'s first bullet after the takeover specialist had built up an 11.4% stake. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Roderick</ENAMEX> did so by having <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">USX</ENAMEX> redeem a series of guaranteed notes, a move that, in effect, raised the cost of a $7.19 billion Icahn bid by about $3 billion. And he managed to fend off further advances and even strike up an unlikely friendship with the interloper. Over dinners at <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sky Club</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Links Club</ENAMEX> restaurants, the steel executive and the big investor talked steel, international trade and thoroughbred horses.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Corry</ENAMEX>, who has boned up on corporate raiders by reading <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">T. Boone Pickens</ENAMEX>'s autobiography, had hoped the detente would continue. He was shocked, associates say, to learn of Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Icahn</ENAMEX>'s new takeover threat. (Both men declined to be interviewed for this article.) But the fiercely competitive Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Corry</ENAMEX> quickly showed he's no pushover. He huddled with directors at a special meeting two weeks ago and tried to block his opponent.
Although the board believed that Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Icahn</ENAMEX> is more interested in talking the stock price higher than acquiring <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">USX</ENAMEX>, it adopted a poison-pill defense, to be swallowed if anyone amasses a 15% stake.
Now, it's Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Icahn</ENAMEX>'s move. Will he try to gain a seat on or control of the board and force a radical split of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">USX</ENAMEX> into separate oil and steel companies? Given the weakness of the junk-bond market, can he finance a buy-out? Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Icahn</ENAMEX> may not want to sell out unless he can get a special dividend similar to one he received before selling his stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Texaco Inc.</ENAMEX> in June -- a coup that gave him enough cash to make his <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">USX</ENAMEX> move.
In fact, it's barely begun for Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Corry</ENAMEX>, who faces tough decisions before he has had a chance to get settled into his new job. ``He's in a vulnerable position because he hasn't established much credibility on his own,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bryan Jacoboski</ENAMEX>, a securities analyst at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Painewebber Inc.</ENAMEX>
The 57-year-old tax attorney never even aspired to the job of chief executive. An undistinguished college student who dabbled in zoology until he concluded that he couldn't stand cutting up frogs, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Corry</ENAMEX> wanted to work for a big company ``that could do big things.'' But after joining the tax department of a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">USX</ENAMEX> subsidiary 30 years ago, he set the modest goal of becoming tax manager by the age of 46. For years, he quietly stuck to the back accounting rooms, wearing a hat to work because everyone else did. ``I was never a rebel,'' he said in an earlier interview. ``I don't think most of the people that have been around me would ever say they've seen me pound the table or get angry.''
Yet, the unassuming Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Corry</ENAMEX> helped chart <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">USX</ENAMEX>'s transition from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Steel</ENAMEX> to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Big Oil.</ENAMEX> He served as Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Roderick</ENAMEX>'s front man in tense negotiations for the 1982 purchase of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Marathon Oil</ENAMEX> for $5.9 billion.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Corry</ENAMEX> expected the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Texas Oil & Gas</ENAMEX> sale to delight Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Icahn</ENAMEX> by addressing his concern about boosting shareholder value. But when the two men met in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> a day after Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Icahn</ENAMEX> disclosed the rise in his <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">USX</ENAMEX> stake, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Corry</ENAMEX> learned that Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Icahn</ENAMEX> wanted him to sell all of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Texas Oil</ENAMEX> -- not just its reserves of about 1.2 trillion cubic feet of natural gas and 28 million barrels of oil but also its pipeline, gas-gathering and contract-drilling operations. That would leave <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">USX</ENAMEX> with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Marathon</ENAMEX>, its steel mills and its diversified business segment, which includes, among other things, mineral and transportation products.
Some speculate that Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Corry</ENAMEX> would agree if he could find a buyer at the right price. The problem is that Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Icahn</ENAMEX> is pushing him to move faster and further in restructuring USX than Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Corry</ENAMEX> had planned. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Icahn</ENAMEX> has long believed, associates say, that the company, whose 1988 sales totaled $16.88 billion, is worth $70 a share if broken up. The stock closed yesterday at $33.625, giving Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Icahn</ENAMEX>'s 33.6 million shares a value of $1.13 billion.
Moreover, the opportunity to sell steel at a price acceptable to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">USX</ENAMEX> may be gone, for now. ``The time has passed for us to spin off steel,'' either in a public offering or to a buyer, one executive contends. About the only way that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">USX</ENAMEX> now can get out of steel is to dish it out, piece by piece, in separate joint ventures, he adds.
With Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Icahn</ENAMEX> breathing down his neck, however, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Corry</ENAMEX> may have little choice but to sell at a weak price, even if it means losing some steel-related tax-loss carryforwards. That would leave <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">USX</ENAMEX> essentially an oil company with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Marathon</ENAMEX> as its core. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Marathon</ENAMEX> has benefited from higher crude-oil prices and strong demand for refined products.
Oil has long been Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Corry</ENAMEX>'s pet. Indeed, when the Bush administration finally decided this summer to renew import restrictions -- arguably the most important decision to affect the steel industry in five years -- Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Corry</ENAMEX> and his directors were aboard helicopters, high above <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Marathon</ENAMEX>'s rich oil reserves in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">North Sea</ENAMEX>.
Should USX be left with only <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Marathon</ENAMEX>, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Corry</ENAMEX> might well feel pushed to scout out other energy companies. However, even <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">USX</ENAMEX> executives who work closely with him aren't sure about his long-term goals. ``I don't think he has a clear sense of where he wants the company to go,'' one says. Right now, the executive adds, ``he wants to continue to focus on paying down'' <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">USX</ENAMEX>'s debt by selling assets.
When negotiating, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Corry</ENAMEX> played his cards close to the vest. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Johnnie Johnson</ENAMEX>, who worked for Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Corry</ENAMEX> in strategic planning, recalls how his boss would routinely ask a subordinate to research an entire industry to target acquisition candidates. ``What he really wanted to know was about a particular company, but you didn't know that. He wanted your own unbiased, virgin opinion,'' says Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Johnson</ENAMEX>, now managing director at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Georgeson & Co.</ENAMEX>, a proxy-solicitation and investor-relations firm.
Ever the pragmatist, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Corry</ENAMEX> said in August that he realized that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">USX</ENAMEX> is on ``acquisition screens all over the country.''
``It's part of the capitalistic market system that equity can be bought and equity is bought,'' he said. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">USX</ENAMEX>, he noted, was formed 88 years ago, ``by in effect buying out a bunch of other companies.... People got rich through takeovers in those days, as they do today.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Thomas F. O'Boyle</ENAMEX> contributed to this article.
