<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ryder System Inc.</ENAMEX> posted a third-quarter net loss of $27.6 million, because of an expected $57 million after-tax charge and continued weakness in the company's truck-rental business.
The latest quarter's after-tax charge -- which is 75 cents a share -- was related to adjustments to reserves for workers' compensation claims; reductions in vehicle fleets, staff and facilities; and writedowns of assets. Although <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ryder</ENAMEX> didn't break out the charge, analysts estimated that the majority of the $57 million was linked to workers' compensation reserves and anticipated losses on the disposal of trucks.
Many analysts said they weren't surprised that problems in many of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ryder</ENAMEX>'s lines of business continued to plague the company. ``It pretty much confirms what we had been expecting,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Anthony Hatch</ENAMEX>, an analyst at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Painewebber Inc.</ENAMEX>
In <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> composite trading yesterday, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ryder</ENAMEX> closed at $22.25, down 37.5 cents.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">M. Anthony Burns</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ryder</ENAMEX>'s chairman and chief executive officer, said: ``We're constantly trying to find ways to regain the earnings momentum. But we're still at the beginning stages of some of these changes.'' He said the fourth quarter will be ``challenging,'' and maintained his conservative forecast that 1990 ``won't be a barn burner.''
